<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="0.86.1">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="0" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="16" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="132" left="108" width="364" height="18" font="0"><i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics 8 (1996)</i></text>
<text top="185" left="108" width="360" height="32" font="1"><i><b>Questions on</b></i><b> Relevance</b></text>
<text top="270" left="108" width="380" height="18" font="3">ISAO HIGASHIMORI &amp; DEIRDRE WILSON</text>
<text top="342" left="162" width="75" height="18" font="4"><b>Abstract</b></text>
<text top="388" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">The following questions (prepared by Isao Higashimori and answered by Deirdre Wilson)</text>
<text top="408" left="162" width="592" height="15" font="5">were used to introduce a general discussion on relevance theory at the end of a Relevance</text>
<text top="427" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">Theory Workshop organised by Yuji Nishiyama and Isao Higashimori at Keio University</text>
<text top="447" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">in March 1996. We would like to thank Yuji Nishiyama and the other organisers of the</text>
<text top="467" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">Keio Conference on the Interface between Grammar and Cognition, of which this</text>
<text top="487" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">Workshop formed a part. Many of the questions relate to changes proposed in the Postface</text>
<text top="507" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">to the second edition of Relevance (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995). Others relate to more general</text>
<text top="526" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="5">issues currently under discussion. We thought them worth circulating as a contribution to</text>
<text top="546" left="162" width="104" height="15" font="5">that discussion.</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="289" height="18" font="4"><b>1 The second edition of <i>Relevance</i></b></text>
<text top="662" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="4"><b>1.0</b> The second edition of <i>Relevance</i> preserved the original text, but added a Postface</text>
<text top="685" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">surveying recent developments in the theory and proposing several changes of</text>
<text top="709" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">terminology or substance. The following questions relate to the Postface, or to the</text>
<text top="733" left="108" width="646" height="18" font="3">explanatory Notes to the Second Edition, which commented on the original text.</text>
<text top="805" left="108" width="336" height="18" font="4"><b>1.1 One or two principles of relevance?</b></text>
<text top="851" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the first edition of <i>Relevance</i>, there was only a single Principle of Relevance</text>
<text top="875" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995: 155-63). In the second edition, this is renamed the Second, or</text>
<text top="899" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">Communicative, Principle of Relevance, and a First, or Cognitive, Principle is added</text>
<text top="923" left="108" width="76" height="18" font="3">(260-66):</text>
<text top="970" left="123" width="391" height="18" font="0"><i>The First (or Cognitive) Principle of Relevance:</i></text>
<text top="994" left="123" width="565" height="18" font="3">Human cognition tends to be geared to the maximisation of relevance.</text>
<text top="1041" left="123" width="458" height="18" font="0"><i>The Second (or Communicative) Principle of Relevance:</i></text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="7" size="16" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">2</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Every act of ostensive communication communicates a presumption of its own optimal</text>
<text top="218" left="123" width="77" height="18" font="3">relevance</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Why is it necessary to propose 'not one but two principles of Relevance'? In other words,</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="668" height="18" font="3">what is the difference between 'maximisation of relevance' and 'optimal relevance'?</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">  </text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: The move from one to two Principles of Relevance was purely terminological,</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">and was designed to draw attention to the distinction between maximal and optimal</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="446" height="18" font="3">relevance, which our earlier formulation had obscured. </text>
<text top="408" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">In the first edition, we distinguished between maximal relevance (the greatest possible</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">effects for the smallest possible effort) and optimal relevance (adequate effects for no</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">unjustifiable effort), and argued that while cognition tends to be geared to the</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">maximisation of relevance, communication merely creates an expectation of <i>optimal</i></text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance. Two generalisations were made, but only the second was singled out and called</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a Principle of Relevance. This led to misunderstandings. Reviewers tended to overlook</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the distinction between maximal and optimal relevance, and took us to be arguing for a</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">single principle of maximal relevance, governing both communication and cognition. By</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="604" height="18" font="3">distinguishing two Principles of Relevance, we hope to avoid this situation.</text>
<text top="622" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">The first edition gives several reasons for distinguishing maximal and optimal</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance. The Postface offers some more. On the cognitive side, we cite evolutionary</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">arguments for the view that cognition tends to be geared to maximal relevance (Postface,</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">sections 3.1-3.2). On the communicative side, our concern has been to show how the</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">addressee's expectation of relevance is <i>justifiable</i> given the Cognitive Principle of</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Relevance; in the Postface we modify our original definition of optimal relevance to deal</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="464" height="18" font="3">with a range of cases we had previously not incorporated.</text>
<text top="788" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">It is easy to show that, despite what the addressee might want, a communicator cannot</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">always be expected to produce the most relevant possible utterance: she may be unwilling</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">or unable to give the most relevant information, or to present it in the most appropriate</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">way. The notion of optimal relevance is designed to spell out what the addressee <i>is</i></text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">entitled to expect in terms of effort and effect. For reasons given in the Postface (section</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="455" height="18" font="3">3.3: 270), we propose the following revised formulation:</text>
<text top="954" left="123" width="289" height="18" font="0"><i>Presumption of Optimal Relevance</i>:</text>
<text top="978" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">(a) The ostensive stimulus is relevant enough for it to be worth the addressee's effort</text>
<text top="1002" left="162" width="104" height="18" font="3">to process it;</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="3">3</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">(b) The ostensive stimulus is the most relevant one compatible with the</text>
<text top="218" left="162" width="334" height="18" font="3">communicator's abilities and preferences.</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="241" height="18" font="4"><b>1.2 Positive cognitive effects</b></text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the revised definition of <i>relevance to an</i> <i>individual</i> (Postface: 265) why did</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">you introduce the notion of 'positive cognitive effect'? How does this notion relate to your</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">distinction between 'cognitive effects that are merely treated by the individual as true' and</text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">'cognitive  effects that actually are true' (Wilson 1996a), and to your comment that</text>
<text top="431" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">'Relevant information is information worth having. False information is generally not</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="666" height="18" font="3">worth having; it detracts from cognitive efficiency' (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995: 264)?</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Our original aim was to capture an intuitive connection between relevance and</text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">cognitive efficiency. In the first edition, we hoped to do this by defining relevant</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">information as information that can be productively processed. On this account, relevance</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">depends on contextual (cognitive) effects and processing effort: the greater the contextual</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">effects, and the smaller the processing effort needed to achieve them, the greater the</text>
<text top="621" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance. Relevant information (whether true or false) is information that can be</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">productively processed, yielding contextual effects that might themselves be either true</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="65" height="18" font="3">or false.</text>
<text top="693" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">In the Postface (section 3.2.1), we raised the following question. Suppose I acquire</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">some false belief, which can be productively processed to yield many further false beliefs:</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">does this really contribute to cognitive efficiency, and hence to relevance, or does the</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="330" height="18" font="3">information merely <i>seem</i> relevant to me?</text>
<text top="788" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Our answer was that information which leads only to false beliefs should not be treated</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">as relevant, however much it may seem so to the individual processing it. We proposed</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to capture this intuition by distinguishing two types of cognitive effect: positive cognitive</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">effects (e.g. true beliefs), which contribute to cognitive efficiency, and hence to relevance,</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and others (e.g. false beliefs), which are not worth having, and hence irrelevant. In the</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">second edition, relevance to an individual is defined in terms of positive cognitive effects</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and processing effort: the greater the positive cognitive effects, and the smaller the effort</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">needed to achieve them, the greater the relevance. Thus, cognitive efficiency and</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="282" height="18" font="3">productive processing come apart. </text>
<text top="1001" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Notice that on this new account, false information may still be relevant, as long as it has</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">positive cognitive effects. Stories, jokes, hypotheses may all contribute to cognitive</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">4</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">efficiency. Truth of the input is neither a necessary nor a sufficient condition for</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="369" height="18" font="3">relevance; it is truth of the output that counts.</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="459" height="18" font="4"><b>1.3 Contextual effects and weakening of assumptions </b></text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the first edition (107-17), relevance is defined in terms of three types of</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">contextual effect: contextual implication, strengthening of existing assumptions, and</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">contradiction and elimination of existing assumptions. In Notes to the Second Edition (2d:</text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">294),  you consider 'a fourth type of contextual effect, namely weakening of existing</text>
<text top="431" left="108" width="587" height="18" font="3">assumptions'. Are there any reasons for adding this fourth type of effect?</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: It has sometimes been noted that if relevance can be achieved by strengthening</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">existing assumptions, it should also be achievable by weakening existing assumptions.</text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">The question then arises, what place is given to weakening of assumptions in our</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="96" height="18" font="3">framework?</text>
<text top="574" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">There are two separate issues here. The first is whether weakening contributes to</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance. We have always assumed that it does, and that any alteration in the strength of</text>
<text top="621" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">existing assumptions contributes to relevance. This is taken account of in our formal</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">definition of the conditions under which a contextualisation has contextual effects (note</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">26: 286). The second issue is whether weakening of existing assumptions should be</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">treated as a distinct type of contextual effect, on a par with contextual implication,</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">strengthening, and contradiction and elimination of existing assumptions. We assume that</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it should not. Our claim is that weakening of assumptions is never achieved directly, but</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">only as a by-product of some more basic contextual effect: for example, contradiction and</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">elimination of an existing assumption weakens all contextual implications which</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">depended on it for some support. We therefore do not treat weakening of assumptions as</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="623" height="18" font="3">a distinct type of contextual effect; it contributes only indirectly to relevance.</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="268" height="18" font="4"><b>1.4 Pragmatics and modularity</b></text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the first edition of <i>Relevance</i> (chapter 2), you treat pragmatics as an</text>
<text top="977" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">inferential system involving central, non-specialised thought processes. In the second</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="570" height="18" font="3">edition (1995: 293), you modify this treatment, with the comment that:</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="3">5</text>
<text top="194" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="3">In the last ten years, there has been growing evidence that so-called central</text>
<text top="218" left="162" width="369" height="18" font="3">systems should be analysed in modular terms.</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">This view is reiterated in Wilson 1996b. What are its implications, in particular for the</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="395" height="18" font="3">domain-specificity of central thought processes? </text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: In <i>The Modularity of Mind</i> (1983), Fodor distinguished modular from central</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">systems and proposed a 'First Law of the Nonexistence of Cognitive Science', which says,</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">in essence, that the central thought processes are too complex to be understood. For</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Fodor, pragmatics is a central system, and as such lies beyond the scope of cognitive</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">science. In <i>Relevance</i>, Dan Sperber and I tried to show that even if pragmatics is a central</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="448" height="18" font="3">system, interesting pragmatic theories can be produced.</text>
<text top="479" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">In recent years, there has been increasing evidence against a sharp division between</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">central and modular systems, and for a substantially modular view of mind (see e.g.</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Hirschfeld &amp; Gelman 1994, Sperber 1996). Sperber (1996) directly addresses the issue</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">and argues for an alternative, fully modular picture. There is room for debate about the</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">appropriate level of generality for a modular pragmatics: for example, should it deal with</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">ostensive communication in general, or only verbal communication? Whatever the</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">answer, it would be an inferential rather than a decoding system, and our arguments</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">against a modular pragmatics viewed as an extension of the language module still stand.</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="219" height="18" font="4"><b>2 Relevance and concepts</b></text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="170" height="18" font="4"><b>2.1 Ad hoc concepts</b></text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: According to the classical view of concepts, concepts form discrete, all-or-none</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">categories. The classical view is often combined with a decompositionalist approach to</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">word meaning, which is rejected by many relevance theorists in favour of a more Fodorian</text>
<text top="882" left="108" width="465" height="18" font="3">view (cf. Carston 1985: 30; Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995: 91). </text>
<text top="906" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Sperber &amp; Wilson (1995, chapter 2) treat concepts as consisting of lexical, logical and</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">encyclopaedic entries. Not all the encyclopaedic information at our disposal is accessed</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">in interpreting an utterance on a given occasion. The Communicative Principle of</text>
<text top="977" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Relevance is a good tool for determining which set of assumptions will be assembled for</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="300" height="18" font="3">a given concept on a given occasion. </text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">6</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">However, novel (or creative) categories such as 'things that could fall on your head'</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">cannot be explained in terms of memorized prototypes or ready-made encyclopaedic</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">schemas. How does Relevance Theory deal with the understanding of novel categories,</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concept acquisition, complex concepts such as SWEET WATER, which refers to 'water</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">which is fresh and pure and free from  pollution' rather than 'water which tastes sweet',</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="333" height="18" font="3">novel uses of idioms as in (1), and so on?</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(1)</text>
<text top="360" left="162" width="415" height="18" font="3">George: Did the old man kick the bucket last night?</text>
<text top="384" left="162" width="276" height="18" font="3">Edward: Nah, he barely nudged it.</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Relevance theory provides several means of extending the individual's conceptual</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">repertoire. The role of concept narrowing, loose use and attributive use in language</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">acquisition and language change was discussed in a draft of <i>Relevance</i> (Sperber &amp; Wilson</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">1983) and developed in more recent work (e.g. Sperber 1996, Sperber &amp; Wilson</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">forthcoming). For example, on hearing a new word like 'gerbil' in a situation which makes</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it clear that a gerbil is a kind of pet, the child might construct an attributive concept, to</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">represent what others are referring to when they use the word, with partial lexical, logical</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and encyclopaedic entries to be filled out over time. Similar accounts, based on loose use</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">or attributive use, might cover the borrowing of words from other languages, and</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">pragmatically conditioned changes in meaning (e.g. <i>greve</i>, from 'river bank', a place where</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="321" height="18" font="3">strikers used to gather, to mean 'strike').</text>
<text top="741" left="108" width="326" height="18" font="4"><b>2.2 Concept narrowing or enrichment</b></text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the Postface to the second edition, you stress the importance of concept</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="699" height="18" font="3">narrowing, or enrichment. How would this notion apply to the following types of case?</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">In (2), the encoded concept APPLE can be understood as referring not to the whole apple</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">but merely to the edible part, excluding the core and even the skin (in Japan we normally</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="364" height="18" font="3">don't eat apple skins) (cf. Higashimori 1996).</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="29" height="18" font="3">(2) </text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="114" height="18" font="3">I ate an apple.</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">In (3), the encoded concept FLOWERS can be understood as referring to the whole plant</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="525" height="18" font="3">(i.e. root, stem, blossoms, leaves) rather than the blossoms alone:</text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="8" size="19" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="3">7</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="28" height="18" font="3">(3) </text>
<text top="194" left="162" width="300" height="18" font="3">I planted some flowers in my garden.</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Neither (2) nor (3) looks like a typical case of enrichment (e.g. BACHELOR</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">understood as ELIGIBLE BACHELOR), in which only a subset of the original extension</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">is picked out. In (2), the question is not how many apples or what type of apples, but</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">rather what parts of an apple were eaten; (3) looks more like a case of polysemy, or of</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="296" height="18" font="3">loose use, than a case of enrichment.</text>
<text top="360" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Both examples raise interesting issues. In the draft of <i>Relevance</i> (chapter IV, 'Implicit</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="631" height="18" font="3">import and implicatures'), we argued that an utterance like ‘I've read the paper</text>
<text top="379" left="738" width="7" height="26" font="8">*</text>
<text top="384" left="745" width="65" height="18" font="3"> or ‘The</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="129" height="18" font="3">stamp was blue</text>
<text top="403" left="236" width="7" height="26" font="8">*</text>
<text top="408" left="243" width="567" height="18" font="3"> is understood as communicating merely that enough of the paper was</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">read (or enough of the stamp was blue) for the fact to be worth mentioning. It is easy to</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">see how this interpretation might follow from considerations of relevance, perhaps</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">combined with the notion of loose use. In (3), 'flowers' might also be treated as strictly</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">defined and loosely used; alternatively, it might be analysed as a case of polysemy. (For</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">further discussion, see Carston 1996; Papafragou 1995, in preparation; Sperber 1996;</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="263" height="18" font="3">Sperber &amp; Wilson forthcoming.)</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="226" height="18" font="4"><b>2.3 Concepts and bridging</b></text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: Bridging assumptions are defined as 'assumptions  which are not directly</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">mentioned in the preceding utterance, but which are constructed by a series of inferences</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">on the basis of what the hearer knows or believes' (Blakemore 1992: 25). How can we</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="442" height="18" font="3">deal with the following case of long-distance bridging?</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="30" height="18" font="3">(4) </text>
<text top="788" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">&#34;I had a sister once,&#34; I say. &#34;She died when she was four. Some sort of  heart</text>
<text top="811" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">disease. I was an infant. I didn't know her. There I was sucking bottles while my</text>
<text top="835" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">parents watched their first born become unable to run, walk. After she died they</text>
<text top="859" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">left her bedroom exactly the same. They didn't put away <i>the toys</i> (= my sister's</text>
<text top="883" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">toys) or clear out <i>the drawers</i> (= my sister's  drawers) or even go into there for</text>
<text top="906" left="162" width="647" height="18" font="3">three and a half years. When I went to a nursery school, they finally made it into</text>
<text top="930" left="162" width="128" height="18" font="3">a laundry room.</text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="311" height="18" font="3">(M. Leimbach, Dying Young, p.129)   </text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">8</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: I don't really see this as a case of long-distance bridging. The antecedent for <i>the</i></text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>toys</i> and <i>the drawers</i> in (4) seems to be the NP <i>her bedroom</i> in the previous utterance</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="546" height="18" font="3">(which is salient enough to be pronominalised later by <i>there</i> and <i>it</i>).</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">  However, (4) does raise an interesting issue about how the NP <i>the toys</i> is mentally</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">represented. One possibility is to treat it as a case of concept narrowing, with <i>the toys</i></text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">being enriched to something like <i>the toys in my sister's bedroom</i>. Another is to treat it as</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">a quantified NP ranging over a pragmatically narrowed domain of discourse, consisting</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">only of objects in the sister's bedroom. Both types of narrowing seem necessary in</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">different circumstances (see Larson &amp; Segal 1995, chapter 9; Rouchota 1994a, 1994b. On</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="560" height="18" font="3">bridging within the relevance-theoretic framework, see Matsui 1995).</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="239" height="18" font="4"><b>3 Stylistic and poetic effects</b></text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="123" height="18" font="4"><b>3.1 Metonymy</b></text>
<text top="573" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: Papafragou (1995: 157) claims that 'in metonymy, the propositional form of the</text>
<text top="597" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">utterance is a literal interpretation of the thought it purports to express. This thought,</text>
<text top="621" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">however, is complex to the extent that it contains an echoic concept.' For example, in (5),</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the expression <i>the sheep</i> can be echoically used to refer to a person who was born in the</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Year of the Sheep, and in (6), the expression <i>the brain</i> can be echoically used to refer to</text>
<text top="692" left="108" width="317" height="18" font="3">someone whose nickname is 'the brain':</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="28" height="18" font="3">(5) </text>
<text top="740" left="162" width="382" height="18" font="3">You should avoid marrying a sheep at all costs.</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(6)</text>
<text top="787" left="162" width="332" height="18" font="3">Where's the brain now that we need him?</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Are all so-called metonymic expressions cases of echoic use, or can they involve concept</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="463" height="18" font="3">loosening or concept widening, as has also been claimed?</text>
<text top="882" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">  </text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Papafragou's suggestion that some cases of metonymy are analysable as varieties</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of echoic (or attributive) use, while others fall together with metaphor as varieties of loose</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="313" height="18" font="3">use, seems to me well worth pursuing. </text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="3">9</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="120" height="18" font="4"><b>3.2 Repetition</b></text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In <i>Relevance</i> (1995: 219), the repetitions in (7) are analysed as requiring extra</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="374" height="18" font="3">processing effort, to be offset by extra effects:</text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="29" height="18" font="3">(7) </text>
<text top="312" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="312" left="216" width="414" height="18" font="3">Here's a red sock, here's red sock, here's a red sock.</text>
<text top="336" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="336" left="216" width="253" height="18" font="3">We went for a long, long, walk.</text>
<text top="360" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">c.</text>
<text top="360" left="216" width="320" height="18" font="3">There were houses, houses everywhere.</text>
<text top="384" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">d.</text>
<text top="384" left="216" width="265" height="18" font="3">I shall never, never smoke again.</text>
<text top="407" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">e.</text>
<text top="407" left="216" width="271" height="18" font="3">There's a fox, a fox in the garden.</text>
<text top="431" left="162" width="12" height="18" font="3">f.</text>
<text top="431" left="216" width="283" height="18" font="3">My childhood days are gone, gone.</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="35" height="18" font="3">       </text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Blass (1986, 1990) argues for a relevance-based account of the repetitions in (8), and</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="284" height="18" font="3">against a coherence-based account:</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="68" height="18" font="3">(8) a.</text>
<text top="550" left="216" width="74" height="18" font="3">Help. </text>
<text top="550" left="265" width="44" height="18" font="3">Help.</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="3">    </text>
<text top="574" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="574" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">Go down Washington Street, Just follow Washington Street three blocks to</text>
<text top="598" left="216" width="114" height="18" font="3">Adams Street.</text>
<text top="621" left="123" width="14" height="18" font="3">  </text>
<text top="621" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">c.</text>
<text top="621" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">?A box of cornflakes, please. A box of cornflakes, please. A box of</text>
<text top="645" left="216" width="149" height="18" font="3">cornflakes, please.</text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">d.</text>
<text top="669" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">?I'd like a box of cornflakes. I'd like a box with cornflakes in it. Just take</text>
<text top="693" left="216" width="477" height="18" font="3">some cornflakes off the shelf and bring them to me, please.</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="35" height="18" font="3">       </text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Is it possible us to explain all the stylistic effects of repetition in terms of a single factor</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="180" height="18" font="3">like processing effort?</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Our analysis of the examples in (7), which illustrate the variety of effects</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">achievable by planned repetitions, still seems to me on the right lines. It has been</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">extended by Furlong (1996), who has looked at a wide range of literary examples, and</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">compared the relevance-theoretic account with stylistic accounts based on a notion of</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">foregrounding. Blass's arguments against the coherence-based approach to repetition also</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">seem to me largely correct. Even if a coherence relation of Repetition (or Elaboration or</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Restatement) could account for the two-clause repetitions in (8), it would shed no light</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="582" height="18" font="3">on the the one-clause repetitions in (7b-f), thus missing a generalisation.</text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="3">10</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="117" height="18" font="4"><b>3.3 Tautology</b></text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: What is the main difference between REPETITION (as shown above) and</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">TAUTOLOGY, as in (9), in which the same encoded concept is repeated in a single</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="79" height="18" font="3">sentence?</text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(9)</text>
<text top="336" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="336" left="216" width="148" height="18" font="3">Boys will be boys.</text>
<text top="360" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="360" left="216" width="197" height="18" font="3">A red sock is a red sock.</text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Ordinary stylistic repetitions, as in (7) and (8), are syntactically superfluous, and</text>
<text top="431" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the processing effort required is gratuitous unless offset by extra effects. By contrast, the</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">repeated phrases in (9) occur in different syntactic positions, with different functions, and</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">could not be eliminated without ungrammaticality. Grice treats the tautologies in (9) as</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">deliberate violations of the Quantity maxims, with resulting implicatures. In the relevance-</text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">theoretic framework, where there are no maxims and hence no maxim-violation, an</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">alternative account must be provided. One possibility would be to treat these cases as</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="528" height="18" font="3">reminders, implicating that an obvious truth has been overlooked.</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="334" height="18" font="4"><b>4 Conceptual and procedural encoding</b></text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="482" height="18" font="4"><b>4.1 Conventional implicatures and procedural meaning</b> </text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: In the Postface (1995, section 2.2), you stress the importance of the distinction</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">between conceptual and procedural encoding. Is there any significant difference between</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Grice's notion of conventional implicature and your notion of procedural meaning when</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it comes to analysing expressions such as <i>actually</i>, <i>oh</i>, <i>well</i>, <i>even</i> and <i>but</i>? (cf. Grundy's</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Gricean analyses of these expressions (1995: 47) versus Higashimori's relevance-theoretic</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="199" height="18" font="3">analyses (1995, 1996b).)</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: As Grice makes clear in his 'Retrospective Epilogue' (Grice 1989), his notion of</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">conventional implicature is quite narrow. It applies to non-truth-conditional 'discourse</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">connectives' such as <i>so, moreover, but</i> and <i>on the other hand</i>, and involves the</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">performance of a non-basic or higher-order speech act of commenting on a more basic</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">speech act. For example, <i>so</i> is associated with a higher-order speech act of explaining, <i>on</i></text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>the other hand</i> with a higher-order speech act of contrasting, <i>moreover</i> with a higher-</text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="790" width="20" height="18" font="3">11</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">order speech act of adding, and so on. It is not clear how <i>actually</i>, <i>oh, even </i>or <i>well</i> would</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="680" height="18" font="3">fit this pattern, since it is not clear what higher-order speech act they might perform.</text>
<text top="242" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Relevance theory offers a richer range of possibilities. For example, <i>actually</i> might be</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">treated as a case of conceptual rather than procedural encoding, along the lines of</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Ifantidou 1993, 1994. If <i>oh</i> is part of the language, it might be treated as encoding a</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">procedural constraint on higher-level explicatures, as suggested in Wilson &amp; Sperber</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">1993, Higashimori 1995. <i>Well</i> has been interestingly analysed as a procedural constraint</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">on implicatures by Jucker 1993; and the behaviour of focus particles such as <i>even</i> and</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="0"><i>only</i> is discussed by Breheny (this volume). More generally, the idea that all meaning, or</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">even all non-truth-conditional meaning, must be cut to a single pattern is no part of the</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance-theoretic framework, and there is little reason to think it is correct (see Sperber</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="312" height="18" font="3">&amp; Wilson 1995: 90-93; Sperber 1996).</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="315" height="18" font="4"><b>4.2 Combining procedural meanings</b></text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: How are we to compute the effects of combining two discourse connectives,</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="654" height="18" font="3">or one discourse connective and another procedural element, as in (10) and (11)?</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="33" height="18" font="3">(10)</text>
<text top="645" left="162" width="74" height="18" font="3">Michiko:</text>
<text top="645" left="270" width="372" height="18" font="3">The weather is usually really good in October.</text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="32" height="18" font="3">Joe:</text>
<text top="669" left="270" width="278" height="18" font="0"><i>Well</i>, I'll try for October, <i>then/*so</i>.</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(11)</text>
<text top="716" left="162" width="467" height="18" font="3">I don't know why I settled on Aberdeen, <i>but anyway</i> I did.</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: The relevance-theoretic framework, which allows for fine-grained differences</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">among types of procedural encoding, should shed some light on these and other cases</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(e.g. <i>but oh, oh but, well after all, so therefore</i>). As noted in Wilson &amp; Sperber 1993,</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">procedural elements do not seem to combine to form more complex units: for example,</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>well </i>and <i>then </i> do not function as a semantic unit in (10).<i> </i>However, it would be interesting</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">to see to what extent procedural elements can interact: whether one can take scope over</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">another, or whether they tend to operate independently. The interaction between</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="571" height="18" font="3">procedural elements and intonation would also be worth investigation. </text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="3">12</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="276" height="18" font="4"><b>5 Explicatures and implicatures</b></text>
<text top="217" left="108" width="25" height="18" font="3">     </text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: What is the relation between Grice's <i>saying/implicating</i> distinction and Sperber</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="321" height="18" font="3">&amp; Wilson's <i>explicit/implicit</i> distinction?</text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: Grice's <i>saying/implicating</i> distinction is not exhaustive. It does not accommodate</text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the sort of speech-act and propositional-attitude information illustrated in (13), which</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="423" height="18" font="3">might be communicated by Mary's utterance in (12):</text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="33" height="18" font="3">(12)</text>
<text top="407" left="162" width="291" height="18" font="3">Mary (sadly): Susan has gone away.</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(13)</text>
<text top="455" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="455" left="216" width="336" height="18" font="3">Mary is saying that Susan has gone away.</text>
<text top="479" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="479" left="216" width="330" height="18" font="3">Mary believes that Susan has gone away.</text>
<text top="503" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">c.</text>
<text top="503" left="216" width="311" height="18" font="3">Mary is sad that Susan has gone away.</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="263" height="18" font="3">It is also not clear whether Grice</text>
<text top="545" left="371" width="7" height="26" font="8">*</text>
<text top="550" left="377" width="432" height="18" font="3">s notion of saying corresponds merely to expressing a</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">proposition, or to <i>communicating</i> a proposition, i.e. committing oneself to its truth (see</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="115" height="18" font="3">Wilson 1995).</text>
<text top="621" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Our notion of explicature (like Grice's notion of implicature) applies only to</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicated propositions. It applies not only to the proposition expressed by an</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">utterance (when this is communicated), but also to the sort of speech-act and</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="688" height="18" font="3">propositional-attitude information in (13), and is thus more comprehensive than Grice</text>
<text top="688" left="796" width="7" height="26" font="8">*</text>
<text top="693" left="802" width="8" height="18" font="3">s</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="135" height="18" font="3">notion of saying.</text>
<text top="740" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Our notion of implicature is modelled quite closely on Grice's, although in several cases</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">we would argue that what he analysed as an implicature is better treated as part of an</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">explicature (see Carston 1988). There is a further difference. For Grice, entailments and</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures were mutually exclusive. We allow for the possibility that entailments and</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="450" height="18" font="3">implicatures may coincide, as in the following example:</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="33" height="18" font="3">(14)</text>
<text top="883" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="883" left="215" width="491" height="18" font="3">Peter:  Would you like to listen to my Rolling Stones record?</text>
<text top="906" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="906" left="216" width="312" height="18" font="3">Mary:  No. I'd rather hear some music.</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="90" height="18" font="3">Here, Mary</text>
<text top="949" left="197" width="7" height="26" font="8">*</text>
<text top="954" left="203" width="607" height="18" font="3">s utterance suggests that Peter's Rolling Stones record is not music, and this</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">suggestion has all the hallmarks of a Gricean implicature. However, it is also an</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">entailment: Mary's statement that she would rather hear some music than hear Peter's</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Rolling Stones record entails that Peter's Rolling Stones record is not music. Thus, what</text>
</page>
<page number="13" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="567" width="164" height="15" font="7"><i>Questions on</i> Relevance</text>
<text top="132" left="790" width="20" height="18" font="3">13</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">is recovered as an implicature may also be an entailment, and our definition of implicature</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="175" height="18" font="3">does not rule this out.</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="306" height="18" font="4"><b>6 Comunication and understanding</b></text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Question</i>: What is the goal of communication and understanding? How can</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicative success and failure be analysed in the light of the following comments?</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="3">  </text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="23" height="18" font="3">(a)</text>
<text top="407" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">Communication alters the mutual cognitive environment of the communicator and</text>
<text top="431" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">audience. Mutual manifestness may be of little cognitive importance, but it is of</text>
<text top="455" left="162" width="448" height="18" font="3">crucial social importance (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995: 61).</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(b)</text>
<text top="479" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">The purpose of communication is not to 'duplicate thoughts' but to 'enlarge mutual</text>
<text top="503" left="162" width="448" height="18" font="3">cognitive environments' (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995: 193).</text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="23" height="18" font="3">(c)</text>
<text top="526" left="162" width="649" height="18" font="3">It (= Mutual knowledge) arises as a result of comprehension rather than as a</text>
<text top="550" left="162" width="321" height="18" font="3">precondition for it (Garman 1990: 366).</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(d)</text>
<text top="574" left="162" width="649" height="18" font="3">The Communicative Principle of Relevance does not generally warrant the</text>
<text top="598" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="3">selection of more than one interpretation for a single ostensive stimulus (Sperber</text>
<text top="621" left="162" width="177" height="18" font="3">&amp; Wilson 1995: 167).</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="23" height="18" font="3">(e)</text>
<text top="645" left="162" width="649" height="18" font="3">The Communicative Principle of Relevance is an exceptionless generalization</text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="454" height="18" font="3">about utterance interpretation (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1995).</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Answer</i>: One important issue raised by the above comments, and more generally by the</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relevance-theoretic account of communication, is whether 'uptake' is essential to</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">successful communication. This and other questions are currently being investigated by</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="604" height="18" font="3">Gary Holden in his University of London PhD on Communication Failure. </text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="94" height="18" font="4"><b>References</b></text>
<text top="929" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Blakemore, D. (1988) The organization of discourse. In F.J. Newmeyer (ed.)<i> Linguistics: The Cambridge</i></text>
<text top="949" left="123" width="299" height="15" font="7"><i>survey</i>, Vol. IV. Cambridge, CUP: 229-250.</text>
<text top="969" left="108" width="687" height="15" font="5">Blakemore, D. (1992)<i> Understanding utterances: An introduction to pragmatics</i>. Oxford, Blackwell.</text>
<text top="989" left="108" width="550" height="15" font="5">Blakemore, D. (1994) Echo question: A pragmatic account. <i>Lingua</i> 94: 197-211.</text>
<text top="1008" left="108" width="584" height="15" font="5">Blass, R. (1986) Cohesion, coherence and relevance. <i>Notes on Linguistics</i>  34: 41-64. </text>
</page>
<page number="14" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="245" height="15" font="7"><i>Isao Higashimori &amp; Deirdre Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="3">14</text>
<text top="193" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Blass, R. (1990) <i>Relevance relations in discourse: A study with    special reference to Sissala</i>. Cambridge,</text>
<text top="213" left="123" width="37" height="15" font="5">CUP.</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Breheny, R. (1996) Pro-active focus. This volume.Carston, R. (1985) Lexical concepts. In G.</text>
<text top="253" left="123" width="541" height="15" font="5">Hoppenbrouwers et al. (eds) <i>Meaning and the lexicon</i>. Dordrecht, Foris: 29-38.</text>
<text top="273" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Carston, R. (1988) Implicature, explicature and truth-theoretic semantics. In R. Kempson (ed.) <i>Mental</i></text>
<text top="292" left="123" width="297" height="15" font="7"><i>representations</i>.  Cambridge, CUP: 155-81.</text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Carston, R. (1996) The proposition expressed by an utterance. Paper delivered to the IPRA conference,</text>
<text top="332" left="123" width="236" height="15" font="5">Mexico City. See also this volume.</text>
<text top="352" left="108" width="476" height="15" font="5">Fodor, J. (1983) <i>The modularity of mind</i>. Cambridge MA: MIT Press.</text>
<text top="372" left="108" width="669" height="15" font="5">Furlong, A. (1996) <i>Relevance theory and literary interpretation</i>. University of London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="391" left="108" width="386" height="15" font="5">Garman, M. (1990)<i> Psycholinguistics</i>. Cambridge, CUP.</text>
<text top="411" left="108" width="472" height="15" font="5">Grice, H.P. <i>Studies in the way of words</i>. Cambridge MA, Harvard UP</text>
<text top="431" left="108" width="432" height="15" font="5">Grundy, P. (1995) <i>Doing pragmatics</i>. London, Edward Arnold.</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Higashimori, I. (1995) Correlation of discourse connectives: A relevance-theoretic account. <i>The English</i></text>
<text top="471" left="123" width="438" height="15" font="7"><i>Literature Review</i> 39: 48-88. Kyoto Women's University, Kyoto.</text>
<text top="490" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Higashimori, I. (1996) Metonymy understanding and relevance theory. <i>Annual Bulletin of Research</i></text>
<text top="510" left="123" width="452" height="15" font="7"><i>Institute for Social</i> <i>Science</i> 26: 61-86. Ryukoku University, Kyoto.</text>
<text top="530" left="108" width="635" height="15" font="5">Higashimori, I. (to appear) EVEN, SAE/SURA/MO as constraints on contextual assumptions.</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Hirschfeld, L. &amp; Gelman, S. (1994)<i> Mapping the mind: Domain specificity in cognition and culture</i>.</text>
<text top="570" left="123" width="121" height="15" font="5">Cambridge, CUP.</text>
<text top="589" left="108" width="595" height="15" font="5">Holden, Gary. (in preparation) <i>Communication failure</i>. Universit of London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="609" left="108" width="493" height="15" font="5">Ifantidou, E. (1993) Sentential adverbs and relevance. <i>Lingua</i> 90: 65-90.</text>
<text top="629" left="108" width="555" height="15" font="5">Ifantidou, E. (1994) <i>Evidentials and relevance</i>. University of  London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="649" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Jucker, A.H. (1993) The discourse marker <i>well</i>: a relevance-theoretic account. <i>Journal of Pragmatics</i> 19:</text>
<text top="669" left="123" width="62" height="15" font="5">435-452.</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="566" height="15" font="5">Larson, R. &amp; Segal, G. (1995) <i>Knowledge of meaning</i>. Cambridge MA, MIT Press.</text>
<text top="708" left="108" width="520" height="15" font="5">Matsui, T. (1995) <i>Bridging and relevance</i>. University of London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="728" left="108" width="486" height="15" font="5">Papafragou, A. (1995) Metonymy and relevance. <i>UCLWPL</i> 7: 141-175.</text>
<text top="748" left="108" width="515" height="15" font="5">Papafragou, A. (in preparation) <i>Polysemy</i>. University of London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="768" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Rouchota, V. (1994a) <i>The semantics and pragmatics of the subjunctive in Modern Greek - a relevance-</i></text>
<text top="787" left="123" width="364" height="15" font="7"><i>theoretic approach</i>. University of London PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="807" left="108" width="574" height="15" font="5">Rouchota, V. (1994b) On indefinite descriptions. <i>Journal of Linguistics</i> 30: 441-75. </text>
<text top="827" left="108" width="559" height="15" font="5">Sperber, D. 1996 <i>Explaining culture: a naturalistic approach</i>. Blackwell, Oxford.</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="427" height="15" font="5">Sperber, D. &amp; Wilson, D. (1983) Draft of <i>Relevance</i>. UCL ms.</text>
<text top="867" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Sperber, D. &amp; Wilson, D. (1995) <i>Relevance: communication and cognition</i> (Second Edition). Oxford,</text>
<text top="886" left="123" width="72" height="15" font="5">Blackwell.</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="578" height="15" font="5">Sperber, D. &amp; Wilson, D. (forthcoming) <i>Relevance and meaning</i>. Oxford, Blackwell.</text>
<text top="926" left="108" width="504" height="15" font="5">Wilson, D. (1995) Is there a maxim of truthfulness? <i>UCLWPL</i> 7: 197-212.</text>
<text top="946" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Wilson, D. (1996a) Truth and relevance in communication and cognition. Paper delivered at Keio</text>
<text top="966" left="123" width="512" height="15" font="5">International Conference on the Interface between Grammar and Cognition.</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="5">Wilson, D. (1996b) Grammar, pragmatics and knowledge. Paper delivered at Keio International</text>
<text top="1005" left="123" width="431" height="15" font="5">Conference on the Interface between Grammar and Cognition.  </text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="553" height="15" font="5">Wilson, D. &amp; Sperber, D. (1993) Linguistic form and relevance. <i>Lingua</i> 90: 1-25.</text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
