<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="0.86.1">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="0" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="23" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="18" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="11" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="136" left="108" width="487" height="32" font="0"><i><b>On interpreting ‘folk psychology’</b></i></text>
<text top="128" left="595" width="12" height="21" font="1"><b>*</b></text>
<text top="220" left="108" width="129" height="18" font="2">MILENA NUTI</text>
<text top="316" left="152" width="73" height="18" font="3"><b>Abstract</b></text>
<text top="361" left="152" width="615" height="16" font="4">‘Folk psychology’ has meant many things to many people. In this paper I consider some of</text>
<text top="381" left="152" width="615" height="16" font="4">the construals and issues surrounding them. My aim is to clear the conceptual ground</text>
<text top="401" left="152" width="615" height="16" font="4">necessary to decide what is ‘folk psychology’ and what is not in a way that is sensitive to</text>
<text top="421" left="152" width="614" height="16" font="4">constraints of methodological naturalism. There is an interesting comparison between the</text>
<text top="441" left="152" width="615" height="16" font="4">notion of ‘folk psychology’ as discussed in different literatures, and the notion of</text>
<text top="461" left="152" width="615" height="16" font="4">‘language’ as it was discussed before Chomsky sharpened the boundaries of empirical</text>
<text top="480" left="152" width="53" height="16" font="4">inquiry.</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="122" height="18" font="3"><b>1 Introduction</b></text>
<text top="594" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">There is now a huge literature on ‘folk psychology’. This paper considers some of the</text>
<text top="617" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">ways in which the term has been understood, with a view to developing a theoretically</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="565" height="18" font="2">adequate conception which will lay the groundwork for future research.</text>
<text top="663" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">The term ‘folk psychology’ is typically introduced in discussing facts of the following</text>
<text top="687" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">sort. If we consider some piece of behaviour, there are (at least) two ways in which we</text>
<text top="710" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">might characterise it. On a purely physical level, we might notice that the detective has</text>
<text top="733" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">put his hand in his raincoat pocket. However, we can also form hypotheses about why he</text>
<text top="757" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">might have done that, and we have expectations about what might happen next for each</text>
<text top="780" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of these hypotheses. For example, we might think that the detective <i>feels</i> cold and he</text>
<text top="803" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5"><i>hopes</i> to warm his hand up in his pocket. In which case he should keep it there a while.</text>
<text top="827" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Or we may notice the unlit cigarette in his mouth and understand that he <i>thinks</i> his</text>
<text top="850" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">lighter is in his pocket and <i>wants</i> a smoke. Or we might notice the gangster just ahead of</text>
<text top="873" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">him and wonder whether the detective is in fact reaching for the gun he <i>knows</i> to be in</text>
<text top="896" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">his pocket while <i>hoping</i> that the gangster, whom he <i>intends</i> to shoot, <i>assumes</i> he is just</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="1004" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="7"><i><b>*</b></i></text>
<text top="1007" left="129" width="681" height="16" font="4"> I am most grateful to Deirdre Wilson for her help, advice and encouragement, and to Robyn Carston</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="545" height="16" font="4">for her comments and suggestions. I am responsible for the views expressed here.</text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="8" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="9" size="13" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="10" size="11" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">82</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">looking for a light. Understanding any of these scenarios involves understanding</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="491" height="18" font="2">behaviour in mental terms: e.g. hoping, wanting, thinking, etc.</text>
<text top="190" left="599" width="7" height="12" font="9">1</text>
<text top="218" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Normal adult humans have this ability, and the term ‘folk psychology’ regularly</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">appears in most discussions of exactly what such abilities humans have and how to</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">account for them. Because these issues are of interest to different disciplines (e.g.</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">philosophy, psychology, primatology) they are approached by theorists from different</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="368" height="18" font="2">backgrounds and from multiple perspectives</text>
<text top="306" left="476" width="7" height="12" font="9">2</text>
<text top="311" left="483" width="327" height="18" font="2">. While interdisciplinarity is a virtue, I</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">think some confusions have arisen partly from lack of clarity in use of terminology. My</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="399" height="18" font="2">main aim in this paper is to clear some of them up.</text>
<text top="381" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">There are three main reasons why the notion of ‘folk psychology’ should be of interest</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to linguists. The first is methodological: the most effective way of sorting out conflicting</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">issues in debates surrounding folk psychology is to adopt a Chomskyan naturalistic</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">approach. In order to evaluate this claim, the emphasis in this paper will be on</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">terminological issues and an overview of existing debate. The second is the inherently</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">interesting possibility of a cognitive module parallel to the language faculty. There is not</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">only a “pre-Chomsky” notion of ‘folk psychology’ at play in the literature, that is</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">comparable to a “pre-Chomsky” notion of ‘language’; also there is probably a faculty of</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">the brain dedicated to some aspects of ‘folk psychology’ in the same way as there is for</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">some aspects of ‘language’. But in order to work out what aspects those might be and</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">how to explain them, the basic parallel will have to be accepted, and its consequences</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">for existing (and future) debate accommodated. The third reason concerns the relation</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">between pragmatics and folk psychology. Understanding communicative behaviour</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">involves recognising and attributing mental states. There is therefore an overlap between</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">the interests of pragmatics and folk psychology. Indeed, it would be desirable to provide</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">an integrated account. However, to do this would require some characterisation of the</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">folk psychology side of the equation and it is therefore useful to get a handle on the</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="283" height="18" font="2">notion that is theoretically tractable.</text>
<text top="865" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="882" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">1</text>
<text top="886" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> In much of the literature on folk psychology, <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> are the most discussed mental states,</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">and the ones that are almost always used to illustrate folk psychology. I have deliberately avoided using</text>
<text top="925" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">them at this point. Reasons for this should become apparent below. Already note, however, that for the</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">purposes of exposition of so-called ‘folk psychological abilities’ <i>think</i> and <i>want</i> do just as well. In fact,</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">they probably do better because they are free from some of the natural-language connotations that <i>belief</i></text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="351" height="16" font="4">and <i>desire</i> carry, which are not relevant at this point.</text>
<text top="1021" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">2</text>
<text top="1025" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> See e.g. Carruthers &amp; Smith (1996), Davies &amp; Stone (1995a&amp;b), Astington et al (1990), Christensen</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="116" height="16" font="4">&amp; Turner (1993).</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">83</text>
<text top="172" left="108" width="353" height="18" font="3"><b>2 Folk psychology (as it is often discussed)</b></text>
<text top="219" left="108" width="238" height="18" font="3"><b>2.1 Problems of terminology</b></text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.1.0 </b>First of all, I would like to draw attention to problems with the term ‘folk</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’. Some problems are stylistic, to do with the connotations the term carries;</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">some are more serious and concern difficulties faced in attempting to identify what the</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">term is used to pick out, and problems that arise when different theorists fail to take this</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="101" height="18" font="2">into account.</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.1.1 Connotations of ‘folk’.  </b>The stylistic problems are mainly to do with ‘folk’ being</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="669" height="18" font="2">part of the label. The following quote illustrates the kind of objection I have in mind:</text>
<text top="474" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="5"><i>Not</i> ‘Folk Psychology’! This is too ‘folksy’; once it is so baptised, it</text>
<text top="497" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">inevitably finds it hard to live down its folksiness. There is an inbuilt</text>
<text top="521" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">temptation to see it as a bit twee, a bit primitive. And that is a very substantial</text>
<text top="544" left="152" width="66" height="18" font="2">mistake.</text>
<text top="567" left="595" width="172" height="18" font="2">(Wilkes, 1993, p.168)</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">I am sympathetic to this point: ‘folk’ does have strong connotations and they may give</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">rise to inferences that lead to us prejudging the nature of what we are trying to</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">investigate. For example, the expectations activated in one’s mind by the word ‘folk’</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">might suggest that whatever folk psychology is, it is a relatively simple matter; they</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">might cast doubt on the reliability of the knowledge associated with it, and further might</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">carry implications about how information about it is learned and passed on, and about</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">how cultural factors and traditions can affect its content. These are open questions, and it</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">is complicated enough to think about them objectively, without the extra burden of an</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="370" height="18" font="2">unfortunate choice of label colouring the issue.</text>
<text top="798" left="478" width="6" height="11" font="10">3</text>
<text top="845" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="863" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">3</text>
<text top="866" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> This problem is particularly salient if the kind of account you expect to move towards is likely to be</text>
<text top="886" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">more ‘technical’ (or sub-personal) than would be compatible with the kind of allusions just mentioned.</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">(“If it is a folk theory, then why can no one state what its principles are in any more than the most</text>
<text top="925" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">rudimentary terms?”, the objection tends to go). The possibility of tacit knowledge accounting for folk</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">psychological abilities is sometimes discarded because it is seen as incompatible with the kind of</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">connotations mentioned above. Maybe this shouldn’t really matter, but since opposers of some kinds of</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">accounts have not refrained from taking cheap shots at them using the connotations carried by ‘folk’ as</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">the basis for their arguments, perhaps it would be a good idea to remove this ammunition if they cannot</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">be mature enough not to play with it. For example Churchland, who wants to construe folk psychology</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">as a theory in order to then argue that it is false, talks of generations of accumulated wisdom and</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">84</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Perhaps similar considerations apply to lend support to my suggestion in footnote 1</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> should not be used as the paradigmatic mental-state terms. These</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">terms often carry connotations that are not relevant to the kind of straightforward</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">reasoning that is generally at issue in the kinds of practices that folk psychology is</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">supposed to account for. Note that it actually seems rather odd to say something like “I</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">went to the fridge because I <i>desired</i> a beer and <i>believed</i> I would find one there”. While</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">these concepts may be the ones of interest to philosophers, that interest should not lead</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to super-imposing them onto ordinary people’s everyday practice. Informants tend to</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">contest the use of <i>belief</i> in sentences like “Certain things follow from my <i>belief</i> that the</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">refrigerator is switched on”. Not only are these concepts philosophically loaded, so that</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">hoping for answers to independently existing questions might easily sway some</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">accounts into hasty conclusions, but also their use in everyday language carries specific</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">contextual effects. At a very crude level, <i>belief</i> is often associated with religious contexts</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">and <i>desire</i> with sexual ones. Explaining to an interested novice what the study of folk</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology is about as ‘understanding behaviour using concepts like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i>’</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">would probably lead them to draw entirely the wrong conclusions about what such a</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="264" height="18" font="2">study is interested in discovering.</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.1.2 ‘Folk’ versus ‘lay’ psychology.  </b>Another worry about the connotations of ‘folk’ in</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">the label of ‘folk psychology’ is the danger of confusing ‘folk psychology’ with what I</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">would call ‘lay’ psychology. In certain parts of the world at least there is a wide body of</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">information that is about psychology in some sense and is available to many individuals.</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">The kind of information I have in mind is the sort of thing that gets reported in the</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">science pages of newspapers, or is the subject for discussion in radio review</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">programmes, or spread by popular science books. For example, Pinker’s “The language</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">instinct” or any of the books about evolutionary psychology (the newspaper plugs and</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">interviews that surround their publication often ensure that a large number of people</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">may be aware of their gist without having to read the books). The results of</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychological experiments are often reported as quirky examples of things that one</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">might never have thought about human nature (e.g. the fact that presented with an array</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of three apparently identical objects subjects tend to pick the right-most one). Tenets of</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychoanalytical theories that now form part of general culture might also fall into this</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="73" height="18" font="2">category.</text>
<text top="962" left="108" width="706" height="18" font="2">                                                                                                                                            </text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">platitudes learnt at the mother’s knee. Such improbable characterizations then become the easy target for</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">those who doubt the status of folk psychology as a theory and point to the difficulties encountered in</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">formulating these alleged platitudes as evidence in favour of a simulation account of folk psychology.</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="695" height="16" font="4">(See the discussions in Davies &amp; Stone 1995a (e.g. Goldman “In defense of simulation theory”, p.195)).</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">85</text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Now, on some occasions, any of these pieces of information might be called upon in</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">some particular instance of predicting or explaining some piece of behaviour (the</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">neighbours have their au pair talking to their small children in Spanish; the shop</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">assistant arranges the display in a special way; I excuse my friend’s behaviour on</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">account of his childhood). Often, to the extent that the information appealed to was</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">reliable and has been accurately reported, the explanation or prediction made on its basis</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">is successful. However, none of this implies that the kind of information I have labelled</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">as ‘lay’ psychology should be considered as part of ‘folk psychology’. Lay psychology</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">is not to do with the individual’s “automatic” understanding of the mind; it is a culturally</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">re-elaborated version of scientific understanding. Indeed, to the extent that lay</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology is included in any characterisation of ‘folk psychology’, I would argue that</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that notion of ‘folk psychology’ is ill-defined with respect to the type of naturalistic</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="181" height="18" font="2">inquiry I have in mind.</text>
<text top="474" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">The fact that folk-psychological practice is often hastily glossed as ‘predicting and</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">explaining behaviour’ should not mean that <i>whatever</i> can be called upon in behaviour</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">prediction or explanation is ‘folk psychology’. What can be called upon in the practices</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of ‘predicting and explaining behaviour’ is of a much wider scope than what can be</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">plausibly assumed to be a universal trait of human beings. This should serve as a</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">warning that the gloss ‘predicting and explaining behaviour’ does not pick out a set of</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">practices that can be given a homogeneous account. As there do seem to be some traits</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to do with mindreading that are universal to humans, those are what I aim to</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="99" height="18" font="2">characterise.</text>
<text top="658" left="207" width="6" height="11" font="10">4</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.1.3  Physics, biology and psychology.  </b>Of course, ‘folk psychology’ is a term that has</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">been around a while, and its shifting reference is something I will discuss shortly. Note</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that one reason the ‘folk’ prefix persists in the case of psychology is because of apparent</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">counterparts to be found in the domains of physics and biology: just as they have a grasp</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of the mental lives of those around them, humans also have an understanding of the</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">movement of objects and of biological categories. This knowledge and the resulting</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">abilities are often referred to as folk physics and folk biology. These three ‘folk’</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">capacities are often considered together in evolutionary psychology. In each case,</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">humans are assumed to have evolved some set of domain-specific abilities (see e.g.</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Hirschfield &amp; Gelman 1994). However, a closer look at the way the ‘folk’ prefix is used</text>
<text top="940" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">in these other cases will show that the parallels we might be tempted to draw, given the</text>
<text top="963" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">shared presence of ‘folk’ in each label, are not always straightforward. It is in fact worth</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">guarding against unqualified comparisons with other ‘folk’ domains, both because of</text>
<text top="1024" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="1041" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">4</text>
<text top="1044" left="130" width="208" height="16" font="4"> See e.g. Avis &amp; Harris (1991).</text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">86</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">differences in how the prefix is used and because of possible differences between</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">domains. I will return to this point after having considered some original uses of ‘folk</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="102" height="18" font="2">psychology’.</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="346" height="18" font="3"><b>2.2 What does ‘folk psychology’ refer to?</b></text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.2.0 </b>‘Folk psychology’ is a very slippery term: it covers many positions and areas of</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">investigation, and in its different guises is tied up in different debates. In this section, I</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">will first rehearse some standard philosophical construals of the term, and the questions</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that surround these construals, and then compare the terminology and interests of more</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">cognitive approaches. What I want to do eventually is to characterise some specific</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">cognitive ability that can be separated out from everything else that gets discussed under</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">the label ‘folk psychology’ and investigated in its own right. As noted above, for</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">linguists, a useful parallel might be with attempts to separate out a language faculty from</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="541" height="18" font="2">everything that goes under the heading ‘language’ or ‘language use’.</text>
<text top="521" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">It is worth noting that alternatives like ‘commonsense psychology’ and ‘belief-desire</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’ are sometimes used instead of ‘folk psychology’. These alternatives do lose</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="471" height="18" font="2">the undesirable ‘folksiness’ connotations mentioned above.</text>
<text top="563" left="579" width="7" height="12" font="9">5</text>
<text top="567" left="586" width="225" height="18" font="2"> However, they do not seem</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to carry any systematic theoretical commitment; they neither mark out a particular</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">standpoint, nor do they delimit a more restricted area of investigation. They are not</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">introduced with the explicit purpose of distinguishing between any particular sets of</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="499" height="18" font="2">data, or circumscribed aspects of ‘folk-psychological-practice’.</text>
<text top="656" left="608" width="7" height="12" font="9">6</text>
<text top="661" left="615" width="196" height="18" font="2"> I will compare the more</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘psychological’ use of the labels ‘theory of mind’, ‘mindreading’, and ‘mentalizing’</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="350" height="18" font="2">after having sketched a ‘philosophical’ map.</text>
<text top="730" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">It is useful to note before proceeding that there are (at least) three different things that</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="407" height="18" font="2">might be at issue in discussions of folk psychology:</text>
<text top="865" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="882" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">5</text>
<text top="886" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> Even though arguably they gain others: for example ‘belief-desire psychology’ to me can lead to</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">presupposing that the concepts of belief and desire will feature in an <i>account of</i> the practices that can be</text>
<text top="925" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="8"><i>described as</i> the attribution of beliefs and desires; in other words it assumes that belief and desire are the</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="483" height="16" font="4">concepts <i>used</i> in the practices, rather than just the concepts talked about.</text>
<text top="982" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">6</text>
<text top="985" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> This ‘elegant variation’ (Fowler 1965, p. 148) certainly is not constructive; and given that more</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">subtle distinctions do need to be introduced in this field it is a shame to pointlessly multiply terminology.</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Instead, the many interchanged alternatives are sometimes used with subtly different intention, but</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="536" height="16" font="4">without having a systematic referent, in spite of the need for refining discussion.</text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">87</text>
<text top="171" left="190" width="342" height="18" font="2">i) <i>Sets of practices</i> that humans engage in;</text>
<text top="195" left="190" width="577" height="18" font="2">ii) <i>Accounts of</i> what it is that enables humans to engage in those</text>
<text top="218" left="216" width="75" height="18" font="2">practices;</text>
<text top="241" left="190" width="577" height="18" font="2">iii) <i>That which</i> (the mechanism, or whatever) underlies the ability to</text>
<text top="265" left="216" width="397" height="18" font="2">engage in i), and what ii) is actually an account of.</text>
<text top="260" left="614" width="7" height="12" font="9">7</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">I think that the words ‘folk psychology’ (and to some extent ‘theory of mind’) have been</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">used at different times to mean all three of these. While some slippage might be</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">acceptable, I suspect that on occasion such slippage actually has the effect of covering</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="149" height="18" font="2">up inconsistencies.</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.2.1 Philosophical issues.  </b>Sometimes when theorists say they want to talk about ‘folk</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’, they mean that they want to talk about the fact that humans understand</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">behaviour in mental terms, often employing a battery of psychological concepts. In this</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">case ‘folk psychology’ seems to denote a practice or set of practices that humans engage</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">in. Such practices seem to involve, for example, attributing mental states on the basis of</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">environmental information; predicting what mental states follow from attributed mental</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">states; selecting and integrating relevant background information in order to predict what</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">action might be taken on the basis of these further attributed mental states; taking some</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">piece of behaviour and forming and testing hypotheses about the mental states that might</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="585" height="18" font="2">have caused it, probably via a process of inference to the best explanation.</text>
<text top="661" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">This appears to be the sense in which Baron-Cohen uses ‘folk psychology’ as an</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="226" height="18" font="2">alternative to ‘mindreading’:</text>
<text top="730" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">Mindreading also goes under the name “folk psychology” – and that may be</text>
<text top="753" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="2">a better term for it, since it reminds us that it is simply our everyday way of</text>
<text top="777" left="152" width="174" height="18" font="2">understanding people.</text>
<text top="800" left="549" width="218" height="18" font="2">(Baron-Cohen, 1995, p. 25)</text>
<text top="885" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="922" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">7</text>
<text top="925" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> To illustrate the spirit of the distinctions between i), ii) and iii) a parallel with linguistics might be</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">useful: i) could be linguistic behaviour; ii) could be particular theories (GB, minimalism, Davidsonian</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">theories, use theories, etc.); iii) could be I-language. Already it is clear that the three categories need to</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">be refined a lot and made more specific as they each encompass some quite different possibilities. But I</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">think it is already useful to distinguish between these three different kinds of thing that might be under</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">discussion; and such distinctions are rarely standardly drawn. In fact, it is not always clear how the</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="424" height="16" font="4">positions sketched in this paper map onto i), ii) and iii), if at all.</text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">88</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">While Baron-Cohen is careful about the scope and level of description of his inquiry, it</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">is still confusing to introduce a term as laden as ‘folk psychology’, which raises more</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="694" height="18" font="2">issues than it resolves, apparently without considering how it might be (mis)understood.</text>
<text top="241" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">When philosophers use ‘folk psychology’ it is not always clear whether what is at</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">issue are the practices that humans engage in, or what mediates those practices. Part of</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">the reason for this, I think, is that these two issues are often run together. ‘Folk</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’ can refer to what philosophers call ‘a commonsense conception of the</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">mind’, according to which beliefs, desires and other propositional attitudes feature in</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">everyday understanding of behaviour (see e.g. Rudder Baker, 1995). On the one hand,</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">however, these ‘practices’ are not very well delimited. What is at issue appears to be</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">how we understand one another’s behaviour. Even when this is restricted, as it</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">sometimes is, to explaining, predicting and describing behaviour, it will still be an area</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of considerable complexity, probably calling upon a wide variety of sub-skills. Bear in</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">mind that huge amounts of information of very different kinds might be brought to bear</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">on this kind of ‘interpretation’ process. On the other hand, not only is a very wide</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">category of behaviours picked out, but also it is picked out in a way that may well be too</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">restrictive. The interest is taken to be ‘understanding behaviour in terms of concepts like</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5"><i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i>’. This is generally understood as ‘in terms of the concepts <i>belief</i> and</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5"><i>desire</i> and other concepts like them’. However, I think it would be more open minded to</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">say instead: ‘in terms of concepts that are like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> (i.e. whatever states they</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">are, they are representational states with semantic properties and causal powers)’,</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">without presupposing that concepts that are theoretically interesting and sophisticated in</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">philosophy (<i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i>) will appear in an account of general human cognitive</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="82" height="18" font="2">capacities.</text>
<text top="702" left="191" width="7" height="12" font="9">8</text>
<text top="707" left="198" width="255" height="18" font="2"> I will return to this point below.</text>
<text top="730" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">When ‘folk psychology’ is talked of as “the commonsense psychology that explains</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">behaviour in terms of beliefs, desires, intentions, etc…” (e.g. Rudder Baker, 1999), it is</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">unclear whether this is supposed to be still a description of practices, or instead refer to</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">whatever is responsible for these practices; to say “<i>the</i> commonsense psychology”</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">makes it sound as if there is some thing that is responsible for the practices, and <i>that</i> is</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">what is being talked about, whatever it is. If this interpretation is the intended one, it</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">makes it sound as if there is a unified explanation for a set of phenomena that are no</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="228" height="18" font="2">more than intuitively related.</text>
<text top="889" left="337" width="7" height="12" font="9">9</text>
<text top="924" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="942" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">8</text>
<text top="945" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> For a proposal that is not guilty of this presupposition, see Grice (1975). For illustration of how</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="593" height="16" font="4">Grice’s proposal relates to a Chomskyan approach to ‘folk psychology’, see Nuti (1998).</text>
<text top="1002" left="124" width="6" height="10" font="10">9</text>
<text top="1005" left="130" width="681" height="16" font="4"> We can compare the variety of issues surrounding ‘language’ in some sense, that have interested</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">different theorists and are relevant to completely different studies. Bilgrami describes Chomsky’s</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">approach to circumscribing a domain of investigation as “…a soberly made critique based on a realistic</text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">89</text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="492" height="18" font="2">Let us use the following quote to consider these issues further:</text>
<text top="218" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="2">It has come to be a standard assumption in philosophy and psychology that</text>
<text top="241" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">normal adult human beings have a rich conceptual repertoire which they</text>
<text top="265" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="2">deploy to explain, predict and describe the actions of one another and,</text>
<text top="288" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">perhaps, members of closely related species also. As is usual, we shall speak</text>
<text top="311" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="2">of this rich conceptual repertoire as ‘folk psychology’ and of its deployment</text>
<text top="334" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">as ‘folk-psychological practice’. The conceptual repertoire constituting folk</text>
<text top="358" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">psychology includes, predominantly, the concepts of belief and desire and</text>
<text top="381" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">their kin – intention, hope, fear and the rest – the so-called propositional</text>
<text top="404" left="152" width="71" height="18" font="2">attitudes.</text>
<text top="428" left="532" width="235" height="18" font="2">(Davies &amp; Stone, 1995a, p. 2)</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">This kind of statement is widely accepted and at first sight relatively uncontroversial.</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="574" height="18" font="2">However, it conceals certain assumptions that I think deserve discussion.</text>
<text top="521" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Here, ‘folk psychology’ is used to refer to precisely the framework of concepts that</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">feature in (verbal) explanations of behaviour. However, we are also told that these</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">concepts are <i>deployed</i> in the prediction, explanation and description of behaviour that is</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">folk-psychological practice. If ‘this rich conceptual repertoire’ is what is supposed to be</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">deployed in these practices, it is presumably (part of) what underlies or accounts for</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">them. So this kind of statement appears to presuppose that the conceptual repertoire that</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">features in verbal reports is in fact what is deployed in explaining and predicting</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="84" height="18" font="2">behaviour.</text>
<text top="707" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="2">Probably one reason these concepts feature so saliently is that they are the ones</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">provided by natural language, which is so often used as a starting point for philosophical</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">discussions. However the conceptual framework provided by natural language is not a</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">reliable indicator of concepts that might be required in a scientific account. Even if it</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">were acceptable to start from the standpoint of natural language, it is not the case that</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">there is a one-to-one mapping between lexical items and concepts. Single words can be</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">used to stand for concepts that humans recognise and readily manipulate in spite of their</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">not being lexicalised (see Sperber &amp; Wilson 1998). Another consideration that might</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">motivate the presence of concepts like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> as basic in some kinds of</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">accounts is that an account of concepts like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> is what many philosophers</text>
<text top="942" left="108" width="706" height="18" font="2">                                                                                                                                            </text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">sense of what is theoretically tractable and identifiable. This has given the impression to many that he is</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">narrowing the subject to leave out interesting social and normative elements. Exactly the opposite is true</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">for he has liberated the study of language from a set of unnecessary and ill-described constraints.”</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">(Bilgrami in Chomsky 1997, p. 60). The same process needs to be undergone in the domain of ‘folk</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="87" height="16" font="4">psychology’.</text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">90</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">are interested in, so that if these concepts do not in fact feature in some explanation of</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">humans’ abilities, then the account will not serve to illuminate independently existing</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="75" height="18" font="2">concerns.</text>
<text top="241" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">For example, ‘folk psychology’ can also refer to versions of ‘theory theory’ (see e.g.</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Fodor 1987, Churchland 1981, Horgan &amp; Woodward 1985). This is a philosophical</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">account of propositional-attitude terms and their relation to behaviour. According to this</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">position, the meaning of terms like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i> is implicitly defined by a network of</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">generalisations containing them; ascribing possession of this theory both justifies</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">ascription of mental-state concepts and accounts for the practices. An instance of such a</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="191" height="18" font="2">generalisation might be:</text>
<text top="428" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="5"><i>If X desires q, and X believes that if p then q, then X will attempt to bring</i></text>
<text top="451" left="152" width="192" height="18" font="5"><i>about p, ceteris paribus.</i></text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">When ‘theory theory’ is understood as an empirical psychological theory that is to</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">underlie the practices, it is sometimes claimed to be largely tacit, as these sorts of</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">generalisations are not always easy to formulate, even if they look familiar once spelt</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">out. Often, analogies with linguistics are drawn. However, the theory is standardly</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">constrained to include the concepts listed above, as it is claimed that those are the</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">concepts that folk psychology practices use. By contrast, I would like to put forward the</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">possibility that while elements from this rich conceptual repertoire may feature in</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">introspection and reports of behaviour, they perhaps do so at no more than the level of</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">descriptive adequacy. The generalisations that are standardly listed as part of ‘folk</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’ may be no more than a phenomenological description of deeper processes.</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">In much the same way, an informant might claim that she knows the sentence is</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">grammatical because the words are in the right order, instead of appealing to features</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="84" height="18" font="2">and traces.</text>
<text top="800" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">I will be examining detailed ways of exploring parallels between the study of folk</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology and linguistics elsewhere. For now, note that in the literature this parallel is</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">always hastily drawn. Before doing linguistics, linguists decide what notion of</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘language’ they are investigating. This basic step does not seem to be taken in the case of</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="145" height="18" font="2">‘folk psychology’.</text>
<text top="940" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3"><b>2.2.2  Debates.  </b>At this point it is worth distinguishing between two philosophical</text>
<text top="963" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">debates that surround the notions of ‘folk psychology’. The first concerns the status of</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">humans’ everyday understanding of psychology as the conceptual framework for</text>
<text top="1010" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">scientific psychology. The second concerns what account to provide of humans’</text>
<text top="1033" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">everyday understanding. The first is about the eliminativist issue of whether the</text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">91</text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">categories of <i>belief</i>, <i>desire</i>, etc. are really what is causing the behaviours that are being</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">understood by, on the one hand scientific psychology, and on the other folk psychology.</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Do beliefs and desires (the categories of folk psychology) really exist? (Presumably the</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">question is whether they exist in the brain of the person who is being understood). The</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">second is about the simulation-theory/theory-theory debate that attempts to illuminate,</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="693" height="18" font="2">often at cross-purposes, how to explain different features of folk-psychological practice.</text>
<text top="311" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">To illustrate how there are two different objects of investigation, and two possible</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="445" height="18" font="2">approaches to each one, consider the following diagram:</text>
<text top="404" left="486" width="213" height="18" font="2">dotted line = folk approach</text>
<text top="428" left="378" width="21" height="18" font="2">P2</text>
<text top="428" left="486" width="246" height="18" font="2">filled line = scientific approach</text>
<text top="451" left="216" width="21" height="18" font="2">S2</text>
<text top="474" left="152" width="21" height="18" font="2">P1</text>
<text top="497" left="486" width="11" height="18" font="2">=</text>
<text top="497" left="540" width="218" height="18" font="2">object of study is behaviour</text>
<text top="521" left="486" width="11" height="18" font="2">=</text>
<text top="521" left="540" width="270" height="18" font="2">object of study is humans’</text>
<text top="544" left="452" width="329" height="18" font="2">(pretheoretic) understanding of behaviour</text>
<text top="591" left="270" width="21" height="18" font="2">S1</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">S1 (subject 1) is just behaving. P1 (psychologist 1) is studying S1’s behaviour using the</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">apparatus of scientific psychology. S2 (subject 2) is understanding S1’s behaviour using</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">her ‘folk’ psychology. P2 (psychologist 2) is attempting to characterise what is actually</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">going on in S2 when she does this. (We could in fact also draw a thick dotted arrow</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">from S2 back onto S2, as S2 has opinions about how she is understanding S1’s</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="90" height="18" font="2">behaviour).</text>
<text top="777" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">It is clearly worth distinguishing between comparing humans’ everyday psychology</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">with scientific psychology, and providing an account of humans’ everyday</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">understanding of psychology, however flawed that understanding might be. However,</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">these issues are not always kept distinct. I will discuss this in section 3, on how</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="525" height="18" font="2">comparisons are drawn between folk psychology and folk physics.</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.2.3 Cognitive issues.  </b>When the domain becomes more interdisciplinary, embracing</text>
<text top="940" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">contributions from developmental psychology, primatology, and other branches of</text>
<text top="963" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">cognitive science, the further label of ‘theory of mind’ appears. This sometimes refers to</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">“the branch of cognitive science that concerns our understanding of the minds of</text>
<text top="1010" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">ourselves and others” (Gopnik, 1999) (which should perhaps strictly be ‘theory of theory</text>
<text top="1033" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of mind’), and sometimes refers to the mechanisms that are responsible for this</text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">92</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">understanding, that can be selectively impaired, as in the ‘theory of mind deficit</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="380" height="18" font="2">hypothesis of autism’ (see e.g. Leslie 1991).</text>
<text top="190" left="489" width="14" height="12" font="9">10</text>
<text top="195" left="503" width="308" height="18" font="2"> Putting to one side the “branch of</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">science” interpretation (to which I will return in my discussion of Atran and folkbiology</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">in section 4), let us concentrate on the “mechanism” interpretation. A note on phrasing.</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="523" height="18" font="2">Consider for discussion the following quote from Scholl &amp; Leslie:</text>
<text top="311" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">A theory of mind refers to the capacity to interpret, predict, and explain the</text>
<text top="334" left="152" width="486" height="18" font="2">behaviour of others in terms of their underlying mental states.</text>
<text top="358" left="542" width="225" height="18" font="2">(Scholl &amp; Leslie, 1998, p. 4)</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">But ‘theory of mind’ itself is not an ability. <i>Having</i> ‘theory of mind’ is <i>having</i> an ability</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to (…), in normal circumstances. Theory of mind is what <i>underlies</i> the ability to (…). So</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="558" height="18" font="2">perhaps we should say: “Theory of mind subserves the ability to (…)”.</text>
<text top="474" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">If we can agree that the term ‘theory of mind’ picks out a mechanism that underwrites</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">some set of abilities, as in the above definition, care needs to be taken in determining</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">what this set of abilities might be. What is it that theory of mind provides one with the</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">ability to do? A fairly neutral characterisation (i.e. one that leaves open both the details</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of which facts we should properly be trying to account for, and what might account for</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="131" height="18" font="2">them), might be:</text>
<text top="637" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">Theory of mind is that in virtue of which humans perform certain cognitive</text>
<text top="661" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">tasks that involve the deployment of mental-state concepts in order to make</text>
<text top="684" left="152" width="345" height="18" font="2">sense of the behaviour of their conspecifics.</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">But notice that ‘theory of mind’ is slipperily used too. This can be seen by trying to</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">substitute for ‘theory of mind’, in the above statement, two other terms which are often</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">used in the same sentence as ‘theory of mind’ as alternatives or synonyms:</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘mindreading’ and ‘mentalizing’. To say “Mindreading is that in virtue of which …”</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">would no longer quite make sense. I happen to quite like both of these terms, and would</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">be happy for them to appear in a scientific account, provided it was clear what they are</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to pick out. It is clear, however, that ‘theory of mind’ is sloppily used if it can appear</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">both in statements like the above, and in the same breath as ‘mentalizing’ and</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="118" height="18" font="2">‘mindreading’.</text>
<text top="964" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="982" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">10</text>
<text top="985" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> ‘Theory’ is also a misnomer in this case according to those who doubt the strictly theoretical status</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">of whatever will end up accounting for the abilities at issue. Perhaps law-like generalizations will not</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">feature. Those who are happy for ‘theory’ to apply loosely to any body of knowledge, including</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="445" height="16" font="4">mechanism-based, process-driven structures, can ignore this point.</text>
</page>
<page number="13" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="11" size="16" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">93</text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">The kind of objections I am raising are against the widespread “metonymic” use of the</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="162" height="18" font="2">current terminology.</text>
<text top="190" left="271" width="14" height="12" font="9">11</text>
<text top="195" left="285" width="526" height="18" font="2"> I object to this metonymic use for the following sorts of reasons.</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">If people say ‘folk psychology’ meaning the practices, and then ‘folk psychology’ gets</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">interchanged with ‘theory of mind’ (loosely speaking), but then theory of mind is</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">understood as e.g. a module, then suddenly a domain-specific mechanism is responsible</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">for explaining folk psychology construed in its widest possible sense. And again, if folk</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology is a ‘rich conceptual repertoire’ and, further, one that is taken to underlie our</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="697" height="18" font="2">practice, then tacit theories get lumbered with personal-level, natural-language concepts.</text>
<text top="382" left="108" width="401" height="18" font="3"><b>2.3 The (lack of) status of the domain of inquiry</b></text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.3.1 What are theorists trying to explain?  </b>My concerns are not merely</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">terminological. I am interested in exploring the fascinating abilities that humans have in</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="530" height="18" font="2">the domain of psychology, and what might account for them.</text>
<text top="470" left="638" width="14" height="12" font="9">12</text>
<text top="474" left="652" width="158" height="18" font="2"> I do believe it is</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">necessary to carry out this kind of pedantic ground clearing in order to make progress</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">and to evaluate existing contributions in the field, without falling into a mesh of cross</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="75" height="18" font="2">purposes.</text>
<text top="567" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">One problem with this field might be that it is possible to latch onto the general area</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that theorists are interested in investigating more or less immediately, and it is an area</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that is easy to think about, intuitive and appealing, where even brief and superficial</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">introspection appears to yield insights worth defending. However, I’m worried about</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">whether people know <i>what</i> they are talking about, because I suspect they don’t, and it</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">concerns me that this doesn’t stop the discussion proceeding as if they did, so the</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">problems about working out what they <i>are</i> talking about are just passed on and</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="314" height="18" font="2">eventually ignored. It is almost as if </text>
<text top="733" left="422" width="160" height="15" font="11">FOLK PSYCHOLOGY</text>
<text top="730" left="581" width="230" height="18" font="2"> has become an incomplete</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="200" height="18" font="2">interpretive concept, like </text>
<text top="756" left="309" width="43" height="15" font="11">LOVE</text>
<text top="753" left="352" width="26" height="18" font="2"> or </text>
<text top="756" left="378" width="55" height="15" font="11">ANGEL</text>
<text top="753" left="433" width="195" height="18" font="2">, (if a less beautiful one).</text>
<text top="777" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">It may be that there is no single thing that people are talking about. It certainly seems</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">as if there is nothing that could possess all the properties and satisfy all the constraints</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">and provide an answer to all the questions that get discussed under the rubric ‘folk</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’ (consider again the comparison introduced above between different notions</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of ‘folk psychology’ and the range of issues associated with ‘language use’). I certainly</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">would not want a theory of how humans explain behaviour to be constrained by</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">philosophical requirements on how to explicate the notion of belief, any more than</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="962" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">11</text>
<text top="965" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> Metonymic because labels slide between referring to sets of practices, accounts of practices, and</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="214" height="16" font="4">mechanisms (i.e. i, ii, iii above).</text>
<text top="1021" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">12</text>
<text top="1025" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> Cognitive ethologists like Allen and Bekoff (1997) also proceed in a similarly naturalistic vein in</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="516" height="16" font="4">investigating the existence and nature of mental states in non human animals.</text>
</page>
<page number="14" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">94</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Chomsky would think a theory about (I)-language should be constrained by, for</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">example, philosophical constraints à la Dummett on how ‘knowledge [of language] is</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="307" height="18" font="2">delivered’ (see Chomsky, 1995, p. 34).</text>
<text top="241" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Consider the basic sense of ‘folk psychology’, described as the framework that is used</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">on a day to day basis to understand behaviour. That is a <i>huge</i> area. Indeed, almost the</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">only way to understand the idea of referring to ‘my commonsense psychology’ is by</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">thinking about examples of the practices I engage in. In other words, my practices are</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">taken to be an implementation of some kind of ‘folk psychology’. But now consider the</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">sheer size and complexity of these practices. And then consider the claim that these</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">practices (all of them, indiscriminately, as far as I can tell) are underwritten by a ‘folk</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’. But if a set of practices is identified as practically anything that involves</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">mental states or psychological reasoning, and then attributed to a “folk psychology”,</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="615" height="18" font="2">what status could this “folk” or “commonsense” “psychology” possibly have?</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3"><b>2.3.2 What might theorists usefully try to explain?  </b>There is some human cognitive</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">ability in the domain of psychology that it would be desirable to provide an account of.</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">In order to find out what it is and how to characterise it, I advocate a Chomskyan</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="77" height="18" font="2">approach.</text>
<text top="591" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Having noted that an extremely wide range of events is standardly associated with folk</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology, it would be useful, although it is rarely done, to provide a list of examples</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">that illustrate as many as possible of the different and interacting skills that theorists try</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="334" height="18" font="2">to explain by appeal to ‘folk psychology’.</text>
<text top="656" left="442" width="14" height="12" font="9">13</text>
<text top="661" left="456" width="355" height="18" font="2"> When one starts to do this, it becomes clear</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that what we have is a range of intuitively related phenomena. Applying the basic</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">principles of a Chomskyan approach involves recognising that, by ‘folk psychology’, if</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">you want ‘folk psychology’ to be a naturalistic category, you cannot mean <i>any old thing</i></text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that humans might call upon in understanding one another. Only some of the phenomena</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that pretheoretically appeared to fall within the domain of investigation will end up</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="203" height="18" font="2">sharing a unified account.</text>
<text top="823" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">In the light of the initial discussion, perhaps it would be better to introduce new</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">terminology, rather than attempt to redefine the old terminology that already has many</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">interpretations and hope that the changes register. I propose for this purpose ‘I-</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology’. Partly for its parallels with the terminology in linguistics, which I would</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">like to underline and endorse, but also because of the relative ease with which the three</text>
<text top="940" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">different senses in which ‘folk psychology’ is often used can be teased out. <i>I-psychology</i></text>
<text top="963" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">clearly refers to the mechanisms in the mind/brain that are responsible for a certain set of</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">human cognitive capacities. There can be different <i>accounts of I-psychology</i> and we can</text>
<text top="1024" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="1041" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">13</text>
<text top="1044" left="135" width="218" height="16" font="4"> I am collecting these elsewhere.</text>
</page>
<page number="15" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">95</text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">also discuss the <i>I-psychology practices</i>, made possible by the deployment of (existence</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of) I-psychology and that the accounts of I-psychology have to capture. Furthermore,</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">given the variety of what can be classed as ‘folk psychology’, there seems to be</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="585" height="18" font="2">counterpart notion of E-psychology, that could also usefully be explored.</text>
<text top="237" left="693" width="14" height="12" font="9">14</text>
<text top="241" left="707" width="103" height="18" font="2">  To sum up,</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="464" height="18" font="2">the kind of statement I would like to move towards is then:</text>
<text top="311" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">I-psychology is that in virtue of which humans perform certain cognitive</text>
<text top="334" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">tasks that involve the deployment of mental state concepts in order to make</text>
<text top="358" left="152" width="345" height="18" font="2">sense of the behaviour of their conspecifics.</text>
<text top="405" left="108" width="478" height="18" font="3"><b>3 Comparisons between folk psychology and folk physics</b></text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">I noted above that comparisons are often drawn between folk psychology, folk biology</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">and folk physics. In the case of folk psychology and folk physics, this comparison is</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">standardly drawn in the following way: folk physics is a false theory (often said to be</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">equivalent to medieval impetus theory) and therefore should be abandoned and replaced</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">by scientific physics. In the same way, folk psychology will turn out to be false, and the</text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="625" height="18" font="2">entities it postulates do not exist. This comparison is, I think, too hastily drawn.</text>
<text top="591" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">If physical facts are what you are interested in, then it does make sense to abandon the</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">categories of folk physics. If, however, you are interested in how humans think about</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">physical facts, then scientific physics is not the right science for you. The object of</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">investigation has shifted from physics to how humans understand physics. It becomes a</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">study of humans’ mental processes rather than of the outside world. So to say that the</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">theory that is our folk physics will be overthrown by scientific physics only makes sense</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">if it is physics that is the object of study. By contrast, the concepts that humans use to</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">understand physics pretheoretically are what they are and cannot be replaced. They can</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="540" height="18" font="2">be studied by some branch of scientific psychology or anthropology.</text>
<text top="800" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">If there is any parallel to be found between folk physics and folk psychology, it needs</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">to be cashed out in this way. Humans have a folk psychology that they use to understand</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychological facts. Scientific psychology might come along and show that ideally there</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">are better ways of understanding psychological facts. So much is true if psychological</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">facts are what is under investigation. However, if the focus of study shifts from</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychological facts to how humans interpret psychological facts, then we are back to the</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="962" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">14</text>
<text top="965" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> Comparisons between linguistics and folk psychology have been drawn before (see e.g. Stich &amp;</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Ravenscroft 1993). However, any comparison tends to be dominated by discussions of tacit knowledge,</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">without much consideration of what other methodological insights linguistics could bring to the field, or</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">which concepts might carry over between domains. I am currently exploring the potential of such further</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="67" height="16" font="4">analogies.</text>
</page>
<page number="16" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">96</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">situation we were in when the focus of study was folk physics. The concepts of folk</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology are what they are. Scientific psychology will not replace them, but might</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">elucidate them with an account that employs theoretical concepts introduced for that</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="67" height="18" font="2">purpose.</text>
<text top="265" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">In order to evaluate whether folk psychology will be vindicated by scientific</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology, we will have to wait for a scientific psychological account of folk</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology and a scientific psychological account of psychological facts, and see</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">whether the two accounts match up. However, if it turns out that humans’ folk</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology (understood as what is inside S2) mistakenly ascribes mental states (to S1)</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">in understanding psychological facts, that would not stop the scientific psychological</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">account of how humans understand psychological facts (P2’s theory) from being real</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology of a particular human competence. Nor will the scientific psychological</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">account of how humans understand psychological facts in any sense replace the concepts</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">that humans are using to do so. Rather, it will provide a scientific account of what the</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="548" height="18" font="2">concepts that humans are using to understand psychological facts are.</text>
<text top="495" left="656" width="12" height="11" font="10">15</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="585" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">15</text>
<text top="588" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> Someone might say that we already know what concepts people use to understand psychological</text>
<text top="608" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">facts: they are concepts like <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i>. But these concepts are just part of (some) people’s</text>
<text top="628" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">pretheoretic understanding of how they are able to do something. The response that <i>that</i> is precisely</text>
<text top="648" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">what folk psychology was supposed to be will not wash. A reminder: I have been using ‘folk</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">psychology’ to mean ‘how humans understand psychological facts’. This was pretty uncontroversial.</text>
<text top="687" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Interest in folk psychology mainly does seem to be about how humans understand the mental lives of</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">those around them. If it turns to how humans <i>think</i> they understand the mental lives of those around</text>
<text top="727" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">them, then the focus of interest has shifted again. We might call it [folk-(folk psychology)]. Note that my</text>
<text top="747" left="108" width="552" height="16" font="4">‘folk theory about how I understand others’ might be wrong in two different ways:</text>
<text top="787" left="124" width="597" height="16" font="4">a) my ‘folk theory’ is wrong about what is inside the ‘how to understand others’ theory;</text>
<text top="807" left="124" width="687" height="16" font="4">b) the ‘how to understand others’ theory, although truly what I use to understand them, isn’t actually</text>
<text top="826" left="152" width="465" height="16" font="4">a realistic characterisation of what causes others to behave as they do.</text>
<text top="866" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">So what was lumped together as ‘my folk theory about how to understand others’, should be ‘[my folk</text>
<text top="886" left="108" width="499" height="16" font="4">theory about][how I understand others]’. It is in fact two different theories:</text>
<text top="925" left="124" width="9" height="16" font="4">1</text>
<text top="925" left="152" width="369" height="16" font="4">whatever underlies the ability to understand others, and</text>
<text top="945" left="124" width="9" height="16" font="4">2</text>
<text top="945" left="152" width="223" height="16" font="4">a folk theory about how I do that.</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Either the eliminativist argument is about b), in which case the counter-argument set out above holds, or</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">it is concerned about a), in which case it is arguably about something different from what psychologists</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">are interested in. Either way, it should certainly be made clear which of 1 and 2 is supposed to be ‘folk</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="364" height="16" font="4">psychology’, or at least which one is under discussion.</text>
</page>
<page number="17" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">97</text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">So, the domain that is at issue is the ability to understand other minds. Normal adult</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">humans seem to possess something that enables them to do this, more or less</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">successfully. Now, it might be that the knowledge that the average human is using in</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">order to perform this task is defective in some important respects. Perhaps a Martian or a</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">cognitive scientist equipped with an exhaustive human psychology handbook could do a</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">better job at understanding other minds than the average human. However, if what you</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">are interested in is how humans understand other minds, for better or for worse, rather</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">than how and why humans behave in the way they do, then it makes little sense to think</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of the concepts and processes of folk psychology as being eventually improved upon or</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">replaced. For even if it turns out that folk psychology is radically mistaken about the</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">behaviour of humans and thus makes false statements about the psychology of humans</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">in general, by characterising successfully the principles that constitute folk psychology,</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">theorists would still be doing real psychology of a particular domain. After all, while an</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">individual may be wrong in attributing a particular mental state <i>x</i>, or may be wrong in</text>
<text top="497" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">attributing mental states at all, she, applying her theory, cannot be mistaken about the</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">fact that she thought that attributing a mental state was the right thing to do, and that <i>x</i></text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="296" height="18" font="2">was the right mental state to attribute.</text>
<text top="567" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">In this respect, the situation for psychological understanding seems similar to the</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="176" height="18" font="2">situation for language.</text>
<text top="637" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">The claims entailed by the speaker’s internalized grammar cannot possibly be</text>
<text top="661" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">wrong about sentences in his own idiolect, since grammatical properties in</text>
<text top="684" left="152" width="562" height="18" font="2">that idiolect are determined by the internalized grammar of the idiolect.</text>
<text top="707" left="615" width="152" height="18" font="2">(Stich, 1996, p. 42)</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">In producing a grammaticality judgement about a particular sentence, the informant</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">cannot be wrong about that judgement, as the theory in virtue of which she is able to</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">make that judgement exhausts all considerations about whether or not the judgement is</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="59" height="18" font="2">correct.</text>
<text top="847" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">In short, you as an individual cannot be wrong in using the analysis of a situation</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">provided by your (behaviour-understanding dedicated) brain mechanisms, any more than</text>
<text top="893" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">you can be wrong to use the analysis provided by your I-language in deciding whether a</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">string is grammatical (for you). However, you can be wrong about how your brain</text>
<text top="940" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">mechanisms understand behaviour (you might think the concepts of <i>belief</i> and <i>desire</i></text>
<text top="963" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">feature in your abilities) in much the same way as you can be wrong about how your</text>
<text top="986" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">brain understands language (you might think the concepts of <i>word</i> or <i>sentence</i> are</text>
<text top="1010" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">important) until you’ve done some serious linguistics. Whether your brain mechanisms</text>
<text top="1033" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">are right about what is in fact causing the behaviour (produced by someone else) that</text>
</page>
<page number="18" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="4">98</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">you (thanks to the mechanisms) are in the process of understanding, is a separate</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="72" height="18" font="2">question.</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="478" height="18" font="3"><b>4 Comparisons between folk psychology and folk biology</b></text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">To further illustrate how comparisons made between domains, on the basis of the prefix</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘folk’, need to be drawn carefully, let us consider the way in which Atran uses</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘folkbiology’. In order to discuss Atran’s use of terminology I have set out some quotes</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="286" height="18" font="2">which appear to introduce his terms.</text>
<text top="353" left="395" width="14" height="12" font="9">16</text>
<text top="358" left="409" width="152" height="18" font="2"> He first states that:</text>
<text top="404" left="152" width="614" height="18" font="2">a) “Folkbiology is the cognitive study of how people classify and reason</text>
<text top="428" left="152" width="202" height="18" font="2">about the organic world”;</text>
<text top="474" left="108" width="470" height="18" font="2">This is then expanded with the following two clarifications:</text>
<text top="521" left="152" width="492" height="18" font="2">b) “Ethnobiology is the anthropological study of folkbiology.”</text>
<text top="544" left="152" width="482" height="18" font="2">c) “Naïve biology is the psychological study of folkbiology.”</text>
<text top="591" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Substituting the definition of folkbiology given in a) into the statements b) and c) gives</text>
<text top="614" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">rise to a rather bizarre understanding of the business of ethno and naïve biology: it</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">suggests that, for example, ethnobiology is something anthropologists do if they look at</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">how cognitive scientists study humans’ knowledge of biological categories. This clearly</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">cannot be what is meant; I am just pointing out that the use of these terms deserves more</text>
<text top="707" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">care and attention. I think that what is meant is that ethnobiology is the anthropological</text>
<text top="730" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">study of <i>the object of study of</i> folkbiology. In other words, the most charitable</text>
<text top="753" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">interpretation of this set of statements is that ‘folkbiology’ is an umbrella term for the</text>
<text top="777" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">science that is concerned with studying humans’ pre-theoretic understanding of the</text>
<text top="800" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">biological world. There are two different branches of this science: ethnobiology, which</text>
<text top="823" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">consists in an anthropological approach to this cognitive domain, and naïve biology,</text>
<text top="847" left="108" width="346" height="18" font="2">which consists in a psychological approach.</text>
<text top="842" left="454" width="14" height="12" font="9">17</text>
<text top="885" left="108" width="217" height="16" font="6">                                                </text>
<text top="902" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">16</text>
<text top="906" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> The following quotes come from MITECS, the MIT encyclopaedia of cognitive science; I have</text>
<text top="925" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">chosen it as a source because it is both a recent publication, that should therefore be aware of</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">developments in the fields it discusses since the terminology at issue was originally introduced, and an</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="628" height="16" font="4">introductory one that presumably should be concerned with strict and clarificatory definitions.</text>
<text top="1002" left="124" width="11" height="10" font="10">17</text>
<text top="1005" left="135" width="675" height="16" font="4"> Using this terminology, I imagine the picture goes something like this. Folkbiologists notice that</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">apparently small children have a way of taxonomising living kinds that is similar across individuals and</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="703" height="16" font="4">develops at a very early stage. This has been called naïve biology. Humans also develop, at a slightly</text>
</page>
<page number="19" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="12" size="20" family="Symbol" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="13" size="20" family="Helvetica" color="#000000"/>
<text top="131" left="605" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="794" width="17" height="16" font="4">99</text>
<text top="171" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">Perhaps I am being picky, but notice that if I am right about the interpretation of a), the</text>
<text top="195" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">label ‘folk-plus-domain-name’, as standardly used in biology, refers to <i>the science</i> that</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">studies human conceptions of the world. If this is the case, then parallels between</text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology and biology should be drawn carefully. On the equivalent reading,</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">‘folkpsychology’ would be not what humans have in their heads, nor some set of</text>
<text top="288" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">abilities, nor any account of these abilities, but rather the label for a branch of scientific</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">psychology that is concerned with the psychological aspect of humans’ intuitive</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">understanding of the world. Furthermore, ‘folk psychology’ on the philosophers’ reading</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="2">appears to translate roughly into ethnopsychology in Atran’s terms, while psychologists’</text>
<text top="381" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">interest in ‘theory of mind is closer to naïve psychology. However, no systematic</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="470" height="18" font="2">distinction of this kind appears to be drawn in the literature.</text>
<text top="428" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="2">To sum up: it seems as if we so far have (at least) the following possible</text>
<text top="451" left="108" width="428" height="18" font="2">understandings of what the ‘folk’ prefix can mark out:</text>
<text top="492" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="498" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="499" left="179" width="480" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is some widely construed set of ‘everyday’ practices;</text>
<text top="517" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="523" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="524" left="179" width="588" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is some ability that humans have universally enough to think that</text>
<text top="547" left="179" width="533" height="18" font="2">it is in virtue of some cognitive ability that they have these abilities;</text>
<text top="565" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="571" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="572" left="179" width="588" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is the science that studies (some aspects of) everyday</text>
<text top="595" left="179" width="117" height="18" font="2">understanding;</text>
<text top="613" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="619" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="620" left="179" width="448" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is an account of practices, i.e. a particular theory;</text>
<text top="638" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="644" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="644" left="179" width="551" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is what enables the practices to be performed, i.e. mechanism;</text>
<text top="663" left="152" width="9" height="26" font="12">•</text>
<text top="668" left="161" width="6" height="19" font="13"> </text>
<text top="669" left="179" width="503" height="18" font="2">Folk-X is how the ‘folk’ <i>think</i> that they perform these practices.</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="109" height="18" font="3"><b>5 Conclusion</b></text>
<text top="762" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">Given that there does seem to be a set of cognitive capacities that humans have in virtue</text>
<text top="785" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">of which they are able to conceptualise the world, and given that we might want to</text>
<text top="809" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">investigate what these are, it would be sensible to have a term that picks out this kind of</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">investigation, and an explicit methodology to apply. ‘Folk’ is a singularly inappropriate</text>
<text top="855" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">term to choose for this purpose (particularly in the case of psychology). What alternative</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="477" height="18" font="2">might we use? Chomsky introduces the term ‘ethnoscience’:</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="706" height="18" font="2">                                                                                                                                            </text>
<text top="925" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">later stage, a more explicit set of characterisations of the living kinds around them that depends to some</text>
<text top="945" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">extent on an ontology provided by social subjects, on categories that may be culture dependent to some</text>
<text top="965" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">extent, and which different individuals may have more or less access to and be more or less familiar</text>
<text top="985" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">with. This kind of information, which may be organised in terms of law-like generalizations, or as</text>
<text top="1005" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">disparate pieces of encyclopaedic information about particular kinds, or some combination thereof, we</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">can call ethnobiology. Perhaps neither of these two kinds of information about biology that humans have</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="421" height="16" font="4">access to pre-theoretically actually corresponds to real biology.</text>
</page>
<page number="20" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="14" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="131" left="108" width="25" height="16" font="4">100</text>
<text top="131" left="152" width="29" height="16" font="8"><i>Nuti</i></text>
<text top="195" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">Ethnoscience is a branch of science that studies humans, seeking to</text>
<text top="218" left="152" width="615" height="18" font="2">understand their modes of interpretation of the world, the diversity of these</text>
<text top="241" left="152" width="206" height="18" font="2">systems, and their origins.</text>
<text top="265" left="580" width="187" height="18" font="2">(Chomsky, 1993, p. 13)</text>
<text top="311" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">This “…study of common sense concepts as a branch of naturalistic inquiry” (ibid.)</text>
<text top="334" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2">needs to be set out with particular care in the case of ‘folk psychology’, where the</text>
<text top="358" left="108" width="613" height="18" font="2">concepts of belief and desire have for so long dominated discussion. After all,</text>
<text top="404" left="153" width="614" height="18" font="2">The ethnoscientist seeks to determine what people take to be constituents of</text>
<text top="428" left="153" width="334" height="18" font="2">the world, however they may talk about it.</text>
<text top="451" left="580" width="187" height="18" font="2">(Chomsky, 1995, p. 30)</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="78" height="16" font="14"><b>References</b></text>
<text top="560" left="108" width="529" height="16" font="4">Allen, C. &amp; M. Bekoff. (1997). <i>Species of Mind</i>. Cambridge Mass.: MIT Press.</text>
<text top="580" left="108" width="573" height="16" font="4">Astington, J. W. et al. (eds.). (1990). <i>Developing Theories of Mind</i>. Cambridge: CUP.</text>
<text top="600" left="108" width="486" height="16" font="4">Atran, S. (1999). Folkbiology. In Wilson &amp; Keil (eds.). (1999). 317-319.</text>
<text top="619" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Avis, J. &amp; P. L. Harris. (1991). Belief-Desire Reasoning among Baka Children: Evidence for a Universal</text>
<text top="639" left="124" width="363" height="16" font="4">Conception of Mind. <i>Child Development</i> 62: 460-467.</text>
<text top="659" left="108" width="477" height="16" font="4">Baron-Cohen, S. (1995). <i>Mindblindness</i>. Cambridge Mass.: MIT Press.</text>
<text top="679" left="108" width="549" height="16" font="4">Carruthers, P. &amp; P. Smith. (1996). <i>Theories of theories of mind</i>. Cambridge: CUP.</text>
<text top="699" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Chomsky, N. (1993). Naturalism and Dualism in the Study of Language and Mind. Agnes Cummins</text>
<text top="719" left="124" width="62" height="16" font="4">Lectures.</text>
<text top="738" left="108" width="406" height="16" font="4">Chomsky, N. (1995). Language and Nature. <i>Mind</i> 104: 1-61.</text>
<text top="758" left="108" width="489" height="16" font="4">Chomsky, N. (1997). <i>Language and Thought</i>. Rhode Island: Moyer Bell.</text>
<text top="778" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Christensen, S. M. &amp; D. R. Turner. (1993). <i>Folk Psychology and the Philosophy of Mind</i>. Hillsdale,</text>
<text top="798" left="124" width="294" height="16" font="4">New Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</text>
<text top="818" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Churchland, P. M. (1981). Eliminative Materialism and Propositional Attitudes. <i>Journal of Philosophy</i></text>
<text top="837" left="124" width="389" height="16" font="4">78: 67-90. Reprinted in Christensen &amp; Turner (eds.) 1993.</text>
<text top="858" left="108" width="469" height="16" font="4">Davies, M. &amp; T. Stone. (1995a). <i>Folk Psychology</i>. Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="877" left="108" width="482" height="16" font="4">Davies, M. &amp; T. Stone. (1995b). <i>Mental Simulation</i>. Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="897" left="108" width="440" height="16" font="4">Fodor, J. (1987). <i>Psychosemantics</i>. Cambridge Mass.: MIT Press.</text>
<text top="917" left="108" width="632" height="16" font="4">Fowler, H. W. (1965). <i>A Dictionary of Modern English Usage (second edition)</i>. Oxford: OUP.</text>
<text top="937" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Grice H. P. (1975). Method in Philosophical Psychology (From the Banal to the Bizarre). <i>Proceedings</i></text>
<text top="957" left="124" width="687" height="16" font="8"><i>and Addresses of the American Philosophical Association </i>48: 23-53. Reprinted in <i>The conception of</i></text>
<text top="976" left="124" width="267" height="16" font="8"><i>value</i>. (1991). Oxford: Clarendon Press.</text>
<text top="996" left="108" width="524" height="16" font="4">Gopnik, A. (1999). Theory of mind. In Wilson &amp; Keil (eds.). (1999). 838-841.</text>
<text top="1016" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Hirschfeld, L. &amp; S. Gelman. (eds.). (1994). <i>Mapping the Mind: Domain Specificity in Cognition and</i></text>
<text top="1036" left="124" width="180" height="16" font="8"><i>Culture</i>. Cambridge: CUP.</text>
</page>
<page number="21" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="131" left="597" width="140" height="16" font="8"><i>On ‘folk psychology’</i></text>
<text top="131" left="785" width="25" height="16" font="4">101</text>
<text top="171" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Horgan, T. &amp; J. Woodward. (1985). Folk psychology is here to stay. <i>The Philosophical Review</i> 94:197-</text>
<text top="191" left="124" width="361" height="16" font="4">226. Reprinted in Christensen &amp; Turner (eds.) (1993).</text>
<text top="211" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Leslie, A. M. (1991). The theory of mind impairment of autism: evidence for a modular mechanism of</text>
<text top="231" left="124" width="531" height="16" font="4">development? In <i>Natural theories of mind</i>. A. Whiten (ed.). Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="250" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Nuti, M. (1998). Grice as an evolutionary philosopher. Paper presented to the Hang Seng Centre for</text>
<text top="270" left="124" width="495" height="16" font="4">Cognitive Studies conference on<i> Evolving the Mind</i>, Sheffield, June 1998.</text>
<text top="290" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Rudder Baker, L. (1995). <i>Explaining Attitudes. A Practical Approach to the Mind</i>. Cambridge: CUP</text>
<text top="310" left="124" width="39" height="16" font="4">Press.</text>
<text top="330" left="108" width="572" height="16" font="4">Rudder Baker, L. (1999). Folk psychology. In Wilson &amp; Keil (eds.). (1999). 319-320.</text>
<text top="350" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Scholl, B. J. &amp; A. Leslie. (1998). Modularity, Development and ToM. Forthcoming in <i>Mind and</i></text>
<text top="369" left="124" width="71" height="16" font="8"><i>Language</i>.</text>
<text top="389" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Sperber, D. &amp; D.Wilson. (1998). The mapping between the mental and the public lexicon. In P.</text>
<text top="409" left="124" width="498" height="16" font="4">Carruthers &amp; J. Boucher (eds.). <i>Language and Thought</i>. Cambridge: CUP.</text>
<text top="429" left="108" width="404" height="16" font="4">Stich, S. (1996). <i>Deconstructing the mind</i>. New York: OUP.</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="565" height="16" font="4">Stich, S. &amp; I. Ravenscroft. (1993). What <i>is</i> folk psychology? <i>Cognition </i>50: 447-468.</text>
<text top="468" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Wilkes, K. V. (1991). The Relationship between scientific psychology and common-sense psychology.</text>
<text top="488" left="124" width="467" height="16" font="8"><i>Synthese</i> 89: 15-39. Reprinted in Christensen &amp; Turner (eds.). (1993).</text>
<text top="508" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="4">Wilson, R. A. &amp; F. C. Keil (eds.). (1999). <i>The MIT Encyclopaedia of the Cognitive Sciences</i>. Cambridge</text>
<text top="528" left="124" width="118" height="16" font="4">Mass: MIT Press.</text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
