<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="0.86.1">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
	<fontspec id="0" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="23" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="18" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="8" size="13" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="169" left="95" width="378" height="18" font="0"><i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics</i> 10 (1998)</text>
<text top="218" left="95" width="703" height="32" font="2"><i><b>The deferred interpretation of indexicals and</b></i></text>
<text top="258" left="95" width="197" height="32" font="2"><i><b>proper names</b></i></text>
<text top="249" left="292" width="12" height="21" font="3">*</text>
<text top="340" left="95" width="168" height="18" font="1">GEORGE POWELL</text>
<text top="435" left="139" width="75" height="18" font="4"><b>Abstract</b></text>
<text top="481" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">One of the central tenets of direct reference theory, that indexicals are semantically</text>
<text top="501" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">marked so as to give rise to singular propositions, has recently been challenged, by</text>
<text top="521" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">Geoffrey Nunberg among others, on the grounds that indexicals can, in fact, be shown to</text>
<text top="541" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">lead to the same range of interpretations as descriptions. In this paper I want to take a look</text>
<text top="561" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">at so-called <i>deferred </i>interpretations of indexicals and proper names from a cognitive</text>
<text top="582" left="139" width="615" height="16" font="5">perspective grounded in Relevance Theory, with the aim of  exploring what rôles semantic</text>
<text top="601" left="139" width="528" height="16" font="5">decoding and pragmatic inference play in the retrieval of these interpretations.</text>
<text top="669" left="95" width="124" height="18" font="4"><b>1 Introduction</b></text>
<text top="715" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">What do indexicals, expressions such as<i>  I</i>,  <i>you</i>,  <i>here</i> and <i>now</i>, contribute to the</text>
<text top="738" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">propositions expressed by utterances in which they appear? What, for instance, does the</text>
<text top="761" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">expression <i>I</i> bring to a proposition? I imagine many of us, without having to give the</text>
<text top="785" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">question too much thought, would probably say something like:<i> I</i> just serves to pick out</text>
<text top="808" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">a particular person, it picks out the person who’s speaking. So if I say <i>I hope I’m not</i></text>
<text top="831" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>boring you yet</i>, my use of <i>I</i> just picks out George Powell, in order that I can say</text>
<text top="854" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something about him/me. And faced with most of the data this intuition seems pretty</text>
<text top="878" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">robust, so robust, in fact, that it provides the bedrock for accounts of the semantics of</text>
<text top="901" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexicals within the direct reference tradition. But is it really as robust as all that? Are</text>
<text top="924" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">there uses of indexicals which don’t fit into this nice clear picture? Over the last few</text>
<text top="947" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">years there has been a growing number of voices claiming just this: that there are, in</text>
<text top="970" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">fact, a range of uses, involving so-called <i>deferred</i> reference, in which indexicals do not</text>
<text top="994" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">introduce particular individuals into the propositions expressed by the utterances in</text>
<text top="1038" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1054" left="111" width="7" height="12" font="8"><i><b>*</b></i></text>
<text top="1061" left="117" width="680" height="16" font="5">I would like to thank Robyn Carston for her encouragement, her support and, above all, for her</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="61" height="16" font="5">patience.</text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
	<fontspec id="9" size="20" family="Helvetica" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="10" size="20" family="ZapfDingbats" color="#000000"/>
<text top="169" left="95" width="9" height="16" font="5">2</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="657" height="18" font="1">which they appear. Consider the following examples, taken from Nunberg (1993):</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(1)</text>
<text top="255" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="256" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Condemned prisoner</i>: I am traditionally allowed to order whatever I like for my</text>
<text top="279" left="139" width="76" height="18" font="1">last meal.</text>
<text top="306" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(2)</text>
<text top="305" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="306" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Chess teacher giving an introductory lesson to a student who has just played 4. N</i></text>
<text top="321" left="139" width="15" height="20" font="10">✕</text>
<text top="328" left="154" width="618" height="18" font="0"><i> P …</i>: According to all the textbooks, you often get in trouble with that move.</text>
<text top="374" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(3)</text>
<text top="373" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="374" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Medical pathologist pointing to a spot on his own chest</i>: When a person is shot</text>
<text top="397" left="139" width="418" height="18" font="1">here we can usually conclude that it was not suicide.</text>
<text top="444" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">In each of these examples it seems that, on at least one reading, an indexical is being</text>
<text top="467" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">used to introduce something other than an individual. Have a look at (1), for example.</text>
<text top="490" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">The claim is that it has two readings: a (nonsensical) reading on which <i>I</i> does indeed</text>
<text top="514" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">introduce an individual, and a preferred reading on which <i>I</i> introduces a definite</text>
<text top="537" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">description something like <i>the condemned prisoner</i>, used attributively in the sense of</text>
<text top="560" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Donnellan (1966). In much the same way, <i>you</i> in (2) is taken to introduce a description</text>
<text top="585" left="95" width="335" height="18" font="1">something like <i>the player who plays 4. N </i></text>
<text top="579" left="431" width="15" height="20" font="10">✕</text>
<text top="585" left="446" width="352" height="18" font="0"><i> P…</i>, again attributively used. In (3) it’s not</text>
<text top="608" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">entirely clear how we’d want to paraphrase the contribution <i>here</i> makes to the</text>
<text top="632" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">proposition expressed, but all we need be clear about is that it doesn’t serve to introduce</text>
<text top="655" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the particular spot on his own chest which the pathologist is pointing at, as our original</text>
<text top="678" left="95" width="263" height="18" font="1">intuition might suggest it should.</text>
<text top="701" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">So where do these observations leave us? Should we abandon our original intuition</text>
<text top="725" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">entirely in the face of irreconcilable evidence? But if we do that how do we explain the</text>
<text top="748" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">undoubted strength of the intuition, or the fact that it can account for the majority of the</text>
<text top="771" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">data? It would surely be ill advised to ditch out of hand a theory which can do so much</text>
<text top="794" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">good work for us. Perhaps, then, we should just stick to our guns and assume that uses</text>
<text top="817" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">like those in (1), (2) and (3) are somehow deviant? It seems to me that this smacks of</text>
<text top="841" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">sticking our head in the sand; if our theory of indexicals is to be worth its salt it better</text>
<text top="864" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">have some kind of account for uses which, although perhaps rare, are certainly</text>
<text top="887" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">intelligible and attested. As I imagine the foregoing may have hinted, I hope to steer a</text>
<text top="910" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">middle course between these two approaches: I don’t want to turn my back entirely on</text>
<text top="934" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">direct reference, but direct reference cannot hide from the data if it is to provide a</text>
<text top="957" left="95" width="560" height="18" font="1">satisfactory account of indexicals as they are used in natural language.</text>
<text top="980" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">So far, then, I’ve introduced the notion of the deferred use of indexicals; how about</text>
<text top="1003" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the proper names I promised in the title? I don’t want to say too much about the</text>
<text top="1026" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">deferred use of proper names yet: I hope that, as we go on, it will become clear why the</text>
<text top="1050" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">availability or unavailability of deferred readings for proper names is of central</text>
<text top="1073" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">significance. As a rough first approximation, the issue looks like this: if indexicals are</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="601" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="789" width="9" height="16" font="5">3</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">alone among referring expressions in their capacity to give rise to deferred readings,</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">then that seems like pretty good evidence that that capacity has something to do with</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the semantics of indexicals i.e. with their linguistically encoded meaning; if, on the</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">other hand, proper names can give rise to deferred readings just as indexicals can, then</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="672" height="18" font="1">we might well be looking towards pragmatics for an overall account of deferred use.</text>
<text top="326" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Before getting on to the meat of this paper, let me say a couple of words about how I</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">propose to proceed. In the first half of the paper, I want to look at the competing camps</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">in rather more detail, starting with direct reference-flavoured accounts and then turning</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">to the challenges that those accounts have had to face. Then I want, essentially, to turn</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the question around: rather than approaching the issues raised by deferred reference</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">from a philosophical perspective grounded in truth-conditional semantics, I want to see</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">whether any interesting results fall out from adopting a cognition-based approach. My</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">aim is to see whether looking at things from a new perspective might allow us to ask</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">different (and perhaps more interesting) questions and so reach different (and perhaps</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="211" height="18" font="1">more interesting) answers.</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="406" height="18" font="4"><b>2 Indexicals, proper names and direct reference</b></text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">At the heart of the theory of direct reference is the notion that there is a lexically</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encoded distinction between, on the one hand, definite descriptions and, on the other</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">hand, directly referential terms such as indexicals and proper names. There are various</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">ways of looking at this distinction but whichever way you look at it, it comes down to</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something like this: what descriptions contribute to a proposition is some version of a</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Fregean sense; what directly referential expressions contribute to a proposition just is</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">their referent. Kaplan (1977) is careful to distinguish this from the claim that directly</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referential expressions lack descriptive content; it’s just that what descriptive content</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">they do have plays a fundamentally different role in the interpretation process. Instead</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of forming part of the proposition expressed, it simply serves to indicate a referent and</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">then falls away. To put this another way, utterances containing descriptions give rise to</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">general truth conditions, utterances containing directly referential expressions give rise</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="220" height="18" font="1">to singular truth conditions.</text>
<text top="953" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">To capture this insight, Kaplan (1977) introduces a distinction between two different</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">types of meaning: character and content. I don’t want to go into this no doubt familiar</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">distinction in any great depth, but as a rough rule of thumb an expression’s character</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">can be equated with its linguistic meaning and its content with what it contributes to the</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">proposition expressed. In Kaplan’s terms, then, the key thing about directly referential</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">expressions is that their content just is their referent. So what <i>I</i> or <i>John</i>, for instance,</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="9" height="16" font="5">4</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">contribute to a proposition just is whoever they’re being used to refer to. The content of</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a description, by contrast, is some kind of conceptual complex, some kind of Fregean</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">sense. And the character of directly referential expressions? For Kaplan, the feature that</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">distinguishes indexicals from other expressions is that their character and content differ.</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Let’s take <i>I</i> again: we’ve just seen that the content of <i>I</i> will be an individual; what is its</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">character? Well it’s going to be something like <i>the speaker of this utterance</i>. So the</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning of <i>I</i> on this analysis just serves to pick out the speaker of the particular</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="331" height="18" font="1">utterance and then falls out of the picture.</text>
<text top="396" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">There’s some debate about the character of proper names: for Kaplan proper names</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">have identical character and content. For others, such as Recanati (1993), proper names</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">have differing character and content; they are, in other words, a form of indexical. We</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">need not, however, be too concerned here with the character of directly referential</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">expressions; it is, rather, their content, what they contribute to propositions, that lies at</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="372" height="18" font="1">the heart of the debate over deferred reference.</text>
<text top="582" left="95" width="509" height="18" font="4"><b>3 Geoffrey Nunberg and the challenge of deferred reference</b></text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">In a series of papers (e.g. Nunberg (1990) and Nunberg (1993)), Geoffrey Nunberg has</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">raised objections to the approach outlined above which one of its leading proponents</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">has called ‘the most serious which the theory of direct reference has ever faced’</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">(Recanati (1993, p301)). The main thrust of Nunberg’s argument is simple: at the heart</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of direct reference is the claim that there is a semantically encoded distinction between</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">directly referential expressions and descriptions which leads to a difference in truth</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conditions; if, therefore, it can be shown that indexicals are capable of giving rise to the</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">same range of interpretations as descriptions, then the theory of direct reference will be</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">seriously weakened, at least so far as indexicals are concerned. And, for Nunberg,</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="381" height="18" font="1">examples such as (1), (2) and (3) show just this.</text>
<text top="860" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">But what lessons does he draw from these data? Let’s just remind ourselves of the</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">two main planks of the direct reference account of indexicals: the meaning (character)</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of indexicals does not enter into the proposition expressed, in other words the meaning</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of indexicals is indicative; and what indexicals contribute to propositions (their content)</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">just is an individual. Where do these claims stand in the face of Nunberg’s examples?</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Well the first claim remains unaffected: Nunberg sees no reason to dispute the notion</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that the linguistic meaning of indexicals is indicative. There is, after all, abundant</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">evidence to illustrate this point. To take just one example, Kaplan (1977) points out</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">that, if <i>the speaker of this utterance</i> were the content as well as the character of <i>I</i>, then</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="288" height="18" font="1">(4) would express a necessary truth:</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
	<fontspec id="11" size="13" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="12" size="11" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="169" left="601" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="789" width="9" height="16" font="5">5</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(4)</text>
<text top="232" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="233" left="139" width="409" height="18" font="1">If no one were to utter this token, I would not exist.</text>
<text top="256" left="631" width="167" height="18" font="1">Kaplan (1977, p520)</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="596" height="18" font="1">‘Beliefs such as [(4)]’, says Kaplan, ‘could make one a compulsive talker’.</text>
<text top="326" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The second claim of direct reference, on the other hand (the claim, that is, that</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexicals are semantically marked so as to give rise to singular propositions), seems</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">seriously threatened by Nunberg’s examples, if we accept that the propositions</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="328" height="18" font="1">expressed by those examples are general</text>
<text top="390" left="423" width="7" height="12" font="11">1</text>
<text top="396" left="429" width="368" height="18" font="1">. The insight that underlies this is that there is</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">no necessary link between the two claims of direct reference: just because the meaning</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of an expression is indicative, that doesn’t necessarily mean that what that expression</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">contributes to a proposition just is an individual. It might contribute a property other</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">than that encoded by its linguistic meaning. And it’s this insight that leads Nunberg to</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">propose an alternative account of the semantics of indexicals, an account grounded in</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="257" height="18" font="1">the notion of deferred reference.</text>
<text top="558" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">The question Nunberg sets out to answer is, essentially, this: if indexicals can</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">contribute properties other than those encoded by their linguistic meaning, through</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">what mechanism do these properties get into propositions? And, in rough terms, the</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">answer he gives is that they get in because indexicals have the semantics they do.</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg starts by looking at the meaning of <i>we</i>: he observes that, although it may be so</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="86" height="18" font="1">interpreted</text>
<text top="669" left="182" width="7" height="12" font="11">2</text>
<text top="674" left="188" width="609" height="18" font="1">, <i>we</i> is not standardly used as the plural form of <i>I</i>. It is, rather, used to mean</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something like<i> the group of people instantiated by the speaker or speakers of the</i></text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>utterance</i> (Nunberg (1993, p7)). Now as Nunberg points out, what this really comes</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">down to is the idea that the interpretation of <i>we</i> involves a two-stage (i.e. deferred)</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">process: first the hearer has to find out who the speaker of the utterance is and secondly</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">he must decide which group instantiated by the speaker is being picked out by this use</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">of  <i>we</i>. With this in mind, Nunberg divides the meaning of <i>we</i> into three separate</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">components: a deictic component, which picks out a particular element of the context of</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">utterance (an <i>index</i>, in Nunberg’s terms): in the case of <i>we</i>, the deictic component will</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pick out the speaker; a classificatory component, which serves to lay constraints on the</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">eventual interpretation: for <i>we</i>, the classificatory component will contain the features</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">plural and animate, on Nunberg’s analysis; and a relational component which</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">determines what relation must hold between the index and the interpretation: for <i>we</i> this</text>
<text top="980" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="996" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">1</text>
<text top="1001" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> As we shall see there are good reasons to believe that, contrary to appearances, at least some of</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="420" height="16" font="5">Nunberg’s examples do, in fact, express singular propositions.</text>
<text top="1057" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">2</text>
<text top="1062" left="116" width="681" height="16" font="5"> As, for instance, when a group of authors jointly drafting a document start with the phrase <i>we the</i></text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="88" height="16" font="6"><i>undersigned</i>.</text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="9" height="16" font="5">6</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">will be something like <i>the index must instantiate the interpretation</i>. The key point is</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that, for Nunberg, the semantics of <i>we</i> is such that all three components must be</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">resolved in the interpretation process: a hearer must go from the expression to its</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">speaker and then from the speaker to a plural, animate interpretation instantiated by the</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">speaker. Now that’s not to say that there is no rôle for pragmatics in this process:</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">clearly working out which plural, animate group is being referred to on a given use of</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>we</i> involves pragmatic inferencing. That pragmatic inferencing, in fact, is mandatory</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="407" height="18" font="1">given what, for Nunberg, <i>we</i> semantically encodes.</text>
<text top="396" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">The interpretation of <i>we</i>, then, standardly involves deferred reference. But it’s not at</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">all clear that direct reference theorists would have much trouble with the outline of this</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">account of <i>we</i>: so long as the ultimate interpretation is singular rather than general, then</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">all’s well. They would, and in the case of Recanati do, however, have a problem with</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s next move. Nunberg’s claim is that the interpretation of indexicals</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">standardly involves a process of deferred reference; in other words, indexicals in</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">general work just like <i>we</i>. Let’s have a look at <i>I</i> to see how this might work. Nunberg’s</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">proposal looks something like this: <i>I</i> has a deictic component identical to that of <i>we</i>, i.e.</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the deictic component of <i>I</i> picks out the speaker as index; it has a classificatory</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component which requires that the interpretation should be ‘an individual or an</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">individual property, which moreover can only apply to an animate’ (Nunberg (1993,</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">p20)); and it has a relational component which, again, determines that the index should</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">instantiate the interpretation. With this in mind let’s have another look at (1), repeated</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="90" height="18" font="1">here as (5):</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(5)</text>
<text top="743" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="744" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Condemned prisoner</i>: I am traditionally allowed to order whatever I like for my</text>
<text top="767" left="139" width="76" height="18" font="1">last meal.</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">On Nunberg’s analysis, the deictic component of <i>I </i>will, in this case as in every case,</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pick out the speaker as index. The hearer will then look for an animate individual, or</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">‘individual property’, instantiated by the speaker. Clearly, so long as the interpretation</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of <i>I</i> is an individual, the predictions of Nunberg’s account will coincide with those of</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the direct reference account; after all, there’s only one individual which is identical to</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">any speaker, and that is the speaker herself. But in this case it is an individual property,</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that of being a condemned prisoner, which enters into the interpretation. As we’ve</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">already observed, whether it will be an individual or an individual property which</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">enters into the interpretation, and, if the latter, which individual property, will be down</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="187" height="18" font="1">to pragmatic inference</text>
<text top="1017" left="281" width="7" height="12" font="11">3</text>
<text top="1022" left="288" width="510" height="18" font="1">, but that pragmatic inference is mandatory given Nunberg’s</text>
<text top="1061" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1077" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">3</text>
<text top="1082" left="116" width="681" height="16" font="5"> In an earlier analysis (Nunberg, 1978), Nunberg saw this process in terms of the selection of a</text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="601" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="789" width="9" height="16" font="5">7</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="197" height="18" font="1">semantics for indexicals.</text>
<text top="233" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">To summarise, for Nunberg the direct reference account of indexicals must be wrong,</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">given the evidence that indexicals can give rise to the same range of interpretations as</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">descriptions. He thus proposes a semantics for indexicals which accounts for the</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">transfer from individual to property evident in some of his examples as the upshot of a</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">mandatory  step of the interpretation process. For Nunberg, an indexical leads to its</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation by pointing out an object, the index, which relates to that interpretation.</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Looking at it from the other end, deferred reference depends on the availability of an</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">index: ‘in the absence of deixis, deferred interpretation is not possible’ (Nunberg (1993,</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="49" height="18" font="1">p35)).</text>
<text top="442" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">But why, given that there’s so much pragmatics going on in the step between index</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">and interpretation, does Nunberg want to develop a semantic machinery to account for</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">this step, rather than just leaving the whole thing to pragmatics? Well he has two</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">answers to this question. Firstly, if these interpretations were just the product of some</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pragmatic tinkering with a literal meaning, you’d expect the same effect to crop up in</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the same contexts with other referring expressions, such as proper names. But there are</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">at least some contexts in which a deferred reading is available for indexicals but</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="543" height="18" font="1">unavailable for proper names. Compare (6) and (7) with (8) and (9):</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(6)</text>
<text top="650" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="651" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken by Justice O’Connor, a member of the US Supreme Court</i>: We might have</text>
<text top="674" left="139" width="106" height="18" font="1">been liberals.</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(7)</text>
<text top="720" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="721" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken by Bill Clinton</i>: The Founders invested me with sole responsibility for</text>
<text top="744" left="139" width="281" height="18" font="1">appointing Supreme Court justices.</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(8)</text>
<text top="789" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="790" left="139" width="484" height="18" font="1">O’Connor, Rehnquist, Thomas etc. might have been liberals.</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="24" height="18" font="1">(9)</text>
<text top="836" left="119" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="837" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">The Founders invested Bill Clinton with sole responsibility for appointing</text>
<text top="860" left="139" width="191" height="18" font="1">Supreme Court justices.</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">For Nunberg (6) and (7) have general readings on which the indexicals introduce</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">attributive descriptions; <i>we</i> in (6) would be equivalent to something like <i>the Supreme</i></text>
<text top="958" left="95" width="706" height="18" font="1">                                                                                                                                            </text>
<text top="981" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">referring function. In broad terms the idea is that in any act of indexical reference the index and</text>
<text top="1001" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">interpretation are linked by a referring function; for communication to succeed the intended referring</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">function must be that with highest ‘cue validity’ in the context. For those examples in which indexicals</text>
<text top="1042" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">do, in fact, turn out to refer to what Nunberg would call their index (such as most uses of <i>I</i>), the</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">referring function with highest cue validity simply is the identity function (see also Berckmans (1990)</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="164" height="16" font="5">and Fauconnier (1994)).</text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="9" height="16" font="5">8</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>Court justices</i>, and <i>me</i> in (7) to <i>the President of the US</i>. (8) and (9), by contrast, appear</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="220" height="18" font="1">to have only de re readings.</text>
<text top="256" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The second reason Nunberg gives for rejecting a pragmatic account is that, if these</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">general readings are pragmatically derived, then there must be some coherent literal</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation for them to be derived from; but, in at least some of the examples, there is</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="600" height="18" font="1">no coherent literal interpretation. Consider another of Nunberg’s examples:</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(10)</text>
<text top="371" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="372" left="139" width="443" height="18" font="1">Tomorrow is always the biggest party night of the year.</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>Always</i> must quantify over instances, therefore, Nunberg argues, this utterance has no</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">coherent interpretation on which <i>tomorrow</i> is taken to refer to a particular day, as direct</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference would have it do. Rather, the only coherent interpretation has <i>tomorrow</i></text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">standing in for some description such as <i>the Saturday before classes begin</i>. Given the</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">lack of a coherent literal interpretation this general reading cannot, for Nunberg, be</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pragmatically derived. If, then, we want to argue for a pragmatic account of any of</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s general interpretations, we’re going to have to overcome these two</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="78" height="18" font="1">obstacles.</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="357" height="18" font="4"><b>4 Some problems with Nunberg’s account</b></text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Before I come on to that, however, I just want to highlight a couple of problems which</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">might make us think twice before accepting Nunberg’s account wholesale. Let’s just</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">briefly remind ourselves of the core of Nunberg’s claim. Essentially what he is arguing</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">amounts to this: an indexical receives its interpretation through a process of deferred</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference. It can do this due to a tripartite semantic structure consisting of a deictic</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component, a classificatory component and a relational component. The deictic</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component points to an object, the index, and the combination of index, classificatory</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component and relational component lead to an interpretation. On this analysis, as we</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="651" height="18" font="1">have seen, deixis is crucial to deferred reference: no deixis, no deferred reference.</text>
<text top="906" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The first problem with Nunberg’s account is that it involves a great deal of</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">redundancy. As we have seen, Nunberg analyses the meaning of <i>we</i> as: deictic</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component picking out the speaker; classificatory component constraining the</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation to plural and animate; and relational component requiring that the index</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">instantiate the interpretation. But how would we want to flesh out the semantics of other</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexicals,  <i>they</i> for instance? Let’s look at one of Nunberg’s examples of deferred</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="199" height="18" font="1">reference involving <i>they</i>:</text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="601" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="789" width="9" height="16" font="5">9</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(11)</text>
<text top="209" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="210" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken by a teacher pointing at a little girl</i>: They haven’t signed the permission</text>
<text top="233" left="139" width="73" height="18" font="1">form yet.</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">The idea is that <i>they</i> in this utterance is interpreted as something like <i>her parents</i>. But</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">how does this interpretation proceed? Firstly, what is the deictic component of <i>they</i></text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">which leads us to the index, in this case to the little girl? The answer Nunberg gives is,</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">essentially, that there is no encoded deictic component, or, at least, no deictic</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">component which alone identifies an index: <i>they</i> relies for deixis on an associated</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">demonstration. And what of the relational component? As Nunberg himself points out,</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">there seems to be no particular relation that need hold between the index and the</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="276" height="18" font="1">interpretation in cases such as this.</text>
<text top="465" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Now Nunberg is entirely aware of these differences; they in fact form the basis of his</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">distinction between two classes of indexicals: <i>participant terms</i> and <i>non-participant</i></text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>terms</i>. Participant terms are those nominal indexicals which, in Nunberg’s terms, have</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">as their index a participant in the exchange; that is <i>I</i> and <i>we</i>, which both have the</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">speaker as index, and <i>you</i>, which has the addressee as index. Non-participant terms are,</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">essentially, all other nominal indexicals: <i>he</i>, <i>she</i>,<i> they, this</i>, <i>that</i> etc. For Nunberg the</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation of participant terms involves the cashing out of all three semantic</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">components, whereas non-participant terms ‘have no explicit relational component’</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">(Nunberg (1993, p9)). In addition, ‘with demonstratively used pronouns, the deictic</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component is provided entirely by demonstration’ (Nunberg (1993, p23)), so for the</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">majority of non-participant terms there is neither a semantically encoded deictic</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component nor a semantically encoded relational component. It seems, then, that much</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of the semantic machinery Nunberg has developed is actually redundant in many of the</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="268" height="18" font="1">examples he seeks to account for.</text>
<text top="790" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">The second problem with Nunberg’s account is pointed out by Recanati (1993).</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Recanati argues that, in his distinction between index and interpretation, Nunberg has</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conflated two separate distinctions: that between index and referent, a distinction which</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Recanati grants is crucial to the interpretation of <i>we</i>, and the distinction between trigger</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">and target in the terminology of Fauconnier (e.g. Fauconnier (1994)). Have a look at the</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="156" height="18" font="1">following example:</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(12)</text>
<text top="952" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="953" left="139" width="159" height="18" font="1">We are in red brick.</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="498" height="18" font="1">Now the interpretation of (12) will, Recanati claims, look like:</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(13)</text>
<text top="1045" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="1046" left="139" width="286" height="18" font="1">The house we live in is in red brick.</text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">10</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">But, Recanati asks, what is the process which underlies this interpretation? The answer</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">seems to be something like: from <i>we</i> to the speaker, from the speaker to the group of</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">people living in the house and from the group of people living in the house to the house</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">itself. In Fauconnier’s terms, the trigger is the group of people living in the house and</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the target is the house itself. As Recanati points out, the distinction between index and</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referent must be separate from that between trigger and target ‘for the obvious reason</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that the index is neither the trigger nor the target’ (Recanati (1993, p312)). It seems to</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">me that this objection is crucial. However Recanati has allowed Nunberg an easy</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">escape: example (12) is of a type which Nunberg expressly excludes from his analysis</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="168" height="18" font="1">of deferred reference</text>
<text top="414" left="263" width="7" height="12" font="11">4</text>
<text top="419" left="270" width="528" height="18" font="1">. We can, however, see the same phenomenon at work in some of</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="318" height="18" font="1">the examples cited by Nunberg himself:</text>
<text top="488" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">There was an even clearer example of this type [the type of example (6)] in a</text>
<text top="512" left="139" width="616" height="18" font="1">recent cartoon by William Hamilton, which showed a group of conservative</text>
<text top="535" left="139" width="616" height="18" font="1">middle aged businessmen sitting around a boardroom table as one of them</text>
<text top="558" left="139" width="457" height="18" font="1">says: “in a couple of years we’ll probably all be women.”</text>
<text top="581" left="543" width="211" height="18" font="1">Nunberg (1993, p14 fn20)</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">As Grimberg (1996) points out, the index in this example cannot be intending to</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">include himself in the interpretation, since the interpretation is an all-female group.</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Grimberg takes this as evidence that there is no relational component encoded by <i>we</i>; as</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">I shall argue later I believe this conclusion to be a bit hasty. It does, however, illustrate</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">just the situation Recanati claims for (12): the index, here, is, as always, the speaker, the</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">trigger is the group of businessmen around the boardroom table and the target will be</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something like <i>the board members</i> attributively used. What this shows, I shall be</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">arguing, is that there are two entirely separate processes of deferral at work in</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="616" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s examples, one semantically motivated and one entirely pragmatic.</text>
<text top="813" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Finally, before launching into the second half of this paper, I’d like to mention</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">another issue raised by Nunberg’s account. As I’ve stressed, one of Nunberg’s key</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">claims is that ‘in the absence of deixis, deferred interpretation is not possible’: the</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">process of deferral relies, for Nunberg, on the identification of an index, and that can</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">only be achieved through deixis, either in the form of an encoded deictic component or</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a demonstration. In the light of this, consider these two examples, both from Nunberg</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="59" height="18" font="1">(1993):</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1037" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">4</text>
<text top="1042" left="116" width="681" height="16" font="5"> Nunberg actually accounts for uses such as this in terms of property transfer e.g. for (12) the</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">property of being in red brick would transfer from house to inhabitants. For more on predicate transfer,</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="138" height="16" font="5">see Nunberg (1995).</text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">11</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(14)</text>
<text top="209" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="210" left="139" width="563" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken while pointing at a painting</i>: Now <i>he</i> knew how to paint goats.</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(15)</text>
<text top="255" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="256" left="139" width="613" height="18" font="0"><i>We are walking through the Taj Mahal</i>: Gee, he certainly spared no expense.</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">(14) has, <i>ex hypothesi</i>, an associated demonstration; (15), on the other hand, has neither</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">an associated demonstration nor an encoded deictic component (since <i>he</i> is a non-</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">participant term and so lacks deixis). As we already know, no deixis, no deferred</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference; so, if Nunberg is right, there must be a different kind of interpretation process</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">at work in (14) and (15). Nunberg concludes that (14) and (15) contain examples of</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">different uses of <i>he</i>: in (14) <i>he</i> is <i>deictic</i>, in (15) it is <i>contextual</i>. In a good discussion of</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s distinction between deictics and contextuals, Grimberg (1996) points out</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">that this result is highly counterintuitive: there seems little intuitive basis for assuming</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that the Taj Mahal is playing a fundamentally different role in the interpretation of (15)</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">from that played by the painting in the interpretation of (14). Grimberg also observes</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that the use of <i>he</i> in (15) carries the hallmark of deferred reference: it can give rise to an</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation on which the indexical appears to stand in for an attributively used</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">definite description, just as it can in (14). In (14) <i>he</i> can either be interpreted as Chagall,</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">say, or as <i>the man who painted that painting</i>; in (15) it can be interpreted either as Shah</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Jahan or as <i>the man who built this building</i>. There seems little more evidence to support</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">a distinction between these two uses than that Nunberg’s account begins to look a bit</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">shaky without it. Nunberg himself, in fact, appears to realise that this is, to say the least,</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a murky area: he concedes that ‘it is not always easy to tell when the context provides</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="401" height="18" font="1">an implicit demonstration (Nunberg (1993, p 34)).</text>
<text top="791" left="95" width="370" height="18" font="4"><b>5 Deferred reference - a cognitive approach</b></text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="19" font="4"><b>5.0.  </b>At the start of this paper I suggested that by approaching questions of deferred</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference from a cognitive perspective, interesting results might fall out. The cognitive</text>
<text top="884" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">perspective I intend to adopt is grounded in Relevance Theory, providing, as it does,</text>
<text top="907" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">useful insights into the semantics-pragmatics distinction, a distinction which will prove</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">central to the following discussion. It seems to me that, looking at deferred reference</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">from a relevance theoretic perspective, we’re likely to find the question we’re asking</text>
<text top="977" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">more or less entirely reversed: rather than asking, as Nunberg does, why deferred</text>
<text top="1000" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">readings <i>are</i> available for indexicals, the key question from within a relevance theoretic</text>
<text top="1023" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">framework, as I hope to show, is likely to be why deferred readings <i>aren’t</i> available for</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">other referring expressions, such as proper names, where they are available for</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexicals. But before looking at that question we need to do a bit of preliminary scene-</text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">12</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="58" height="18" font="1">setting.</text>
<text top="280" left="95" width="302" height="18" font="4"><b>5.1 Individual and general concepts</b></text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">What kind of thing are we talking about when we talk about the interpretations of</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexicals or, for that matter, of any referring expressions? I hope I’m saying nothing</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">too controversial when I claim that, from a cognitive perspective, there can be only one</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">general answer to this question: we’re talking about concepts. Concepts, after all, must,</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">in one form or another, be the building blocks of propositions on any representational</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">account. It might seem, however, that, in accepting this notion, I’ve prejudged the entire</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">issue against the direct reference camp; after all, it is, as we’ve seen, one of the central</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">claims of direct reference that what directly referential terms contribute to propositions</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">is nothing but their referent. I don’t believe that I have: direct reference, as originally</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">formulated by Kaplan, is a semantic theory, not a cognitive one; Kaplan is not</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">attempting to discover what goes on in the mind, but rather what goes into the truth</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="88" height="18" font="1">conditions.</text>
<text top="605" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">The direct reference account, however, is not incompatible with a cognitive approach,</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">as has been demonstrated, for instance, by Recanati (1993). Recanati draws a</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">distinction between <i>descriptive</i> concepts and <i>de re</i> concepts. Descriptive concepts are</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the sort of thing that go to make up Fregean senses; de re concepts, by contrast, are, for</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Recanati, the cognitive corollary of directly referential terms. Their defining</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">characteristic is that their content is truth conditionally irrelevant, leaving only their</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referent to appear in the truth conditions. Recanati envisages de re concepts as being of</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">two types: <i>egocentric</i> and <i>encyclopaedic</i>. Egocentric concepts are the sort of thing we</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">standardly entertain when we understand indexicals; they are temporary dossiers</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">dominated by non-descriptive (perceptual) information. Encyclopaedic concepts, by</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">contrast, are stable, long-term dossiers of predominantly descriptive information, the</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="483" height="18" font="1">sort of thing we entertain when we understand proper names</text>
<text top="855" left="578" width="7" height="12" font="11">5</text>
<text top="860" left="584" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="883" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Having explained (albeit very sketchily) Recanati’s distinction between de re and</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">descriptive concepts, I now propose to replace it or, rather, to modify it. Recanati’s</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">distinction is firmly grounded within semantic notions of propositional singularity,</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">direct referentiality and so on; it seems to me, however, to cross-cut the key cognitive</text>
<text top="1000" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1016" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">5</text>
<text top="1021" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> That is not to say that egocentric concepts cannot contain descriptive information or that</text>
<text top="1042" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">encyclopaedic concepts cannot contain perceptual information; it is rather a claim about which type of</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">information predominates in each type of concept. For a more detailed account, see Recanati (1993,</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="76" height="16" font="5">Chapter 7).</text>
</page>
<page number="13" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
	<fontspec id="13" size="20" family="Symbol" color="#000000"/>
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">13</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">distinction. The question we need to ask ourselves is this: when can we think of an</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">individual under a de re concept? In what relation do we have to stand to something in</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">order to open a de re concept corresponding to it? Clearly to open an egocentric concept</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">we need direct epistemic contact of some variety. But is the same true of encyclopaedic</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="278" height="18" font="1">concepts? Recanati’s answer is no:</text>
<text top="349" left="139" width="616" height="18" font="1">For the referent to be thought of non-descriptively, it seems to be sufficient</text>
<text top="372" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">that the thinker acquire what Grice calls a ‘dossier’ for the definite</text>
<text top="396" left="139" width="291" height="18" font="1">description used to fix the reference.</text>
<text top="419" left="139" width="525" height="18" font="1">In Grice’s framework, ‘X has a dossier for a definite description </text>
<text top="414" left="662" width="10" height="27" font="13">δ</text>
<text top="419" left="672" width="82" height="18" font="1"> if there is</text>
<text top="443" left="139" width="364" height="18" font="1">a set of definite descriptions which includes </text>
<text top="438" left="503" width="10" height="27" font="13">δ</text>
<text top="443" left="513" width="241" height="18" font="1">, all the members of which X</text>
<text top="466" left="139" width="585" height="18" font="1">supposes…to be satisfied by one and the same item’ (Grice, 1969, p.139)</text>
<text top="489" left="571" width="183" height="18" font="1">Recanati (1993, p 109)</text>
<text top="536" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Now what does this criterion actually mean? Well it means something like: to have a de</text>
<text top="559" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">re thought all you need is enough information all of which you believe applies to a</text>
<text top="582" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">unique individual. But how much information is enough? Where between one and one</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">million pieces of information can we safely draw the line between de re and descriptive</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">concepts? From the perspective of direct reference, concerned as it is with truth</text>
<text top="652" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conditions, there’s a very good reason for drawing the line, wherever it may be that you</text>
<text top="675" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">decide to draw it; but from a cognitive perspective, concerned only with what’s going</text>
<text top="698" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">on in the minds of speaker and hearer, there seems to me to be no good reason to draw</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="567" height="18" font="1">what must in the end be an arbitrary line somewhere on this continuum</text>
<text top="716" left="661" width="7" height="12" font="11">6</text>
<text top="721" left="668" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="745" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">If that’s right, then, where does it leave us? Let me propose the outline of an answer</text>
<text top="768" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">to that question: in cognitive terms the crucial difference between concepts is whether</text>
<text top="791" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">or not we believe they are representations of an individual, not how much uniquely</text>
<text top="814" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">identifying information they contain. What do I mean by that? Essentially I mean that</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">there are two distinct types of concept: first there are those which, whether they contain</text>
<text top="861" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">one piece of information or a million, we believe correspond to an individual in the</text>
<text top="884" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">world (from now on I propose to call these<i> individual</i> concepts); and there are those</text>
<text top="907" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">which, again regardless of how much information they may contain, we believe do not</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">uniquely represent any individual (henceforth <i>general</i> concepts). I would, for instance,</text>
<text top="954" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">have an individual concept of Robyn Carston, which will include a bunch of</text>
<text top="977" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">information gained through direct epistemic contact as well as otherwise; another of the</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1057" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">6</text>
<text top="1062" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> Recanati does, to an extent, accommodate this insight through his notion of provisional de re</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="614" height="16" font="5">concepts. A provisional de re concept is, essentially, a de re concept in search of a referent.</text>
</page>
<page number="14" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">14</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">current president of Indonesia, containing information gained, I guess, through indirect</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">epistemic contact as well as otherwise; and yet another of the oldest person in the</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">world, which will, as far as I can see, contain very little information other than <i>is the</i></text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>oldest person in the world</i>. The crucial thing is that it is my belief that each of these</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">concepts relates to a single individual. On the other hand each of these three individual</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">concepts will contain general concepts: my concept of the current president of</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Indonesia, for instance, will contain the general concepts <i>president</i> and <i>Indonesian</i>; it</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">will, in fact, contain the general concept <i>president of Indonesia</i>. Equally my individual</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">concept of the oldest person in the world will contain general concepts such as <i>old</i>,</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="144" height="18" font="0"><i>person</i>, <i>world </i>etc.</text>
<text top="442" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">This distinction between individual and general concepts is little more than a</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">suggestion; I haven’t, as you will have noticed, offered much in the way of supporting</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">argument. On the other hand, when we come to look at Nunberg’s examples of deferred</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">reference from a cognitive perspective later in this paper, I hope to persuade you that</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="232" height="18" font="1">the distinction is a useful one</text>
<text top="530" left="327" width="7" height="12" font="11">7</text>
<text top="535" left="334" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="558" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">While reformulating Recanati’s distinction between descriptive and de re concepts, I</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">want to maintain, within the class of individual concepts, his distinction between</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">egocentric and encyclopaedic concepts, or something very like it. Recanati (1993)</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">provides extensive and, as far as I can see, very convincing arguments for such a</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">distinction and, when we come to look at contexts in which deferred readings are</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">apparently available for indexicals but not for names, the egocentric-encyclopaedic</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="410" height="18" font="1">distinction is, I hope, going to do good work for us.</text>
<text top="768" left="95" width="478" height="18" font="4"><b>5.2 Indexicals and the conceptual-procedural distinction</b></text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Since Blakemore (1987) proposed that the meaning encoded by non-truth conditional</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">expressions such as discourse connectives might be of a fundamentally different kind</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">from that encoded by other expressions, there has been a great deal of research</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conducted within the relevance theoretic framework into the distinction between</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>conceptual</i> meaning and <i>procedural</i> meaning. Blakemore’s original insight was,</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">roughly, this: that, since utterance interpretation involves two radically different kinds</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of process, first the retrieval of a logical form and then the manipulation of that logical</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">form through pragmatic inference, we might well expect to find two distinct kinds of</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1037" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">7</text>
<text top="1042" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> Of course, if this is right, it may have interesting consequences for Donnellan’s referential-</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">attributive distinction. For lack of space, I shall have to leave an examination of those consequences for</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="89" height="16" font="5">another time.</text>
</page>
<page number="15" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">15</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning corresponding to these processes. And this, for Blakemore, is just what we do</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">find. The kind of meaning encoded by descriptions, for instance, is representational: it</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encodes concepts. The kind of meaning encoded by discourse connectives is, by</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">contrast, computational: it encodes procedures which lay constraints on the retrieval of</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="103" height="18" font="1">implicatures.</text>
<text top="326" left="111" width="689" height="18" font="1">For Blakemore, then, procedural meaning constrains the retrieval of implicitly</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">communicated meaning. Wilson and Sperber (1993) and others have extended</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Blakemore’s original notion to the retrieval of explicitly communicated information;</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">specifically, Wilson and Sperber suggest that pronouns, while contributing to truth</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conditions, might encode procedures. On the face of it, as Wilson and Sperber admit,</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">this is little more than a reformulation of Kaplan’s distinction between character and</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">content: for Kaplan the character of <i>I</i> is something like <i>the speaker of this utterance</i>; for</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Wilson and Sperber <i>I</i> encodes ‘an instruction to identify its referent by first identifying</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the speaker’ (Wilson and Sperber (1993, p20)). The conceptual-procedural distinction</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">does, however, have a cognitive grounding which the character-content distinction</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">lacks. For Kaplan, character and content are, at least in one sense, the same <i>kind</i> of</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning: they are both descriptive. The failure of the character of indexicals to show up</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">in truth conditions, then, must be accounted for by an extra (and ad hoc) piece of</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encoding, something like the REF feature of Recanati (1993). By contrast there is a</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">fundamental difference between conceptual meaning and procedural meaning</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">corresponding to the cognitive difference between representation and computation. The</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">upshot of this is that procedural meaning is not excluded from truth conditions by an ad</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">hoc encoding, it is excluded because it’s simply not the sort of thing that appears in</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="347" height="18" font="1">truth conditions i.e. it’s not representational</text>
<text top="739" left="442" width="7" height="12" font="11">8</text>
<text top="744" left="449" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="767" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">It seems to me, then, that there may well be good reasons to suppose that indexicals</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encode something like procedures, although I’m not sure that a great deal of what</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">follows will hang on this. But, if indexicals do encode procedures, which procedures do</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">they encode? Let’s take Sperber and Wilson’s suggestion for the procedure encoded by</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>I</i> as a starting point: <i>identify its referent by first identifying the speaker</i>. In other words,</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">the semantics of <i>I</i> takes the hearer as far as the speaker (or, in the light of the discussion</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">above, as far as an individual concept of the speaker) and then leaves the rest to</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pragmatics. I imagine we’d want to say much the same about the encoded meaning of</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>you</i>: something like <i>identify its referent by first identifying the hearer</i>. In other words,</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>you</i> takes the hearer to his own concept of himself and then leaves him to work the rest</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1037" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">8</text>
<text top="1042" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> This is clearly no criticism of Kaplan’s approach, since providing a cognitive account of the</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="324" height="16" font="5">interpretation of indexicals is no part of his aim.</text>
</page>
<page number="16" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">16</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="145" height="18" font="1">out pragmatically.</text>
<text top="233" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">So much for Nunberg’s two singular participant terms; how about the plural</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">participant terms? As we’ve seen, Nunberg (1993) launches his proposal off the back of</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a discussion of the semantics of <i>we</i>. The reason he gives for doing so is that the</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">interpretation of <i>we</i> uncontroversially involves deferred reference. And intuitively this</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">seems right; the interpretation of <i>we</i> does seem to involve finding the speaker and then</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">finding a group of which the speaker is a member. In procedural terms, it looks like <i>we</i></text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encodes a two-part procedure, the first part leading to the speaker and the second</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="369" height="18" font="1">leading to a group instantiated by the speaker</text>
<text top="390" left="464" width="7" height="12" font="11">9</text>
<text top="396" left="470" width="327" height="18" font="1">. But maybe this analysis of <i>we</i> is not as</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">uncontroversial as it seems. Grimberg (1996) has argued that, for all indexicals,</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s relational component should be regarded not as semantically encoded but,</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">rather, as a metaphor for the operation of pragmatic processes. In other words for</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Grimberg the semantics of indexicals consists of a deictic component leading to an</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">index, a classificatory component constraining the interpretation and no more. So the</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning of <i>we</i> would simply lead a hearer to the speaker and then determine that the</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation should be plural and animate. Grimberg takes as evidence for this the fact</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">that <i>we</i> can give rise to interpretations which are not instantiated by the speaker. Have a</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="323" height="18" font="1">look again at (12), repeated here as (16):</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(16)</text>
<text top="650" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="651" left="139" width="159" height="18" font="1">We are in red brick.</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Now, as we’ve already seen, for Recanati, (16) shows that there must be a difference</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">between Nunberg’s distinction between index and interpretation and Fauconnier’s</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">between trigger and target: the group of people living in the house, while neither index</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">nor interpretation, is the trigger in Fauconnier’s terms. Recanati’s view, then, is that <i>we</i></text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">may well encode something like Nunberg’s relational component, but that this</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">semantics cannot account for deferred uses of <i>we</i>, which are the result of sub-</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="487" height="18" font="1">propositional pragmatic processes. Grimberg, however, says:</text>
<text top="883" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">It seems to me that the inferencing process from index to interpretation is</text>
<text top="906" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">essentially the same as that from trigger to target, with the ‘trigger’ in</text>
<text top="930" left="139" width="616" height="18" font="1">Recanati’s example representing no more than an intermediate stage in that</text>
<text top="953" left="139" width="65" height="18" font="1">process.</text>
<text top="980" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="996" left="111" width="6" height="10" font="12">9</text>
<text top="1001" left="116" width="682" height="16" font="5"> On this analysis, the use of <i>we</i> to refer to a group of speakers/writers arises where the optimally</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">relevant group associated with the speakers simply is the speakers themselves. In other words, once the</text>
<text top="1042" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">hearer has found the speaker(s), he has already found a plural group instantiated by the speaker(s), i.e.</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">the speakers themselves. He should accept this interpretation in the absence of good pragmatic reasons</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="83" height="16" font="5">not to do so.</text>
</page>
<page number="17" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">17</text>
<text top="210" left="573" width="181" height="18" font="1">Grimberg (1996, p 80)</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">As I understand it, then, Grimberg sees the process of interpretation that leads from this</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">utterance of <i>we</i> to the interpretation <i>the house we live in</i> as essentially seamless: the</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">same processes take us all the way, guided by the deictic and classificatory components</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">and by general pragmatic principles. But surely there is a problem here? What’s</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">happened to the classificatory component? The ultimate interpretation in this example is</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a house, i.e. it is neither plural nor animate. As we’ve already seen, however, Nunberg</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">might well not account for this example in terms of deferred reference. Perhaps, then,</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">we might want to say something like: the standard interpretation of <i>we</i>, rather than</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">those cases involving phenomena such as predicate transfer, involves deferred reference</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">guided by a deictic component and a classificatory component but no relational</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">component. Now there seem to me to be good reasons to suppose that this is wrong.</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="399" height="18" font="1">Grimberg conducts her discussion off the back of:</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(17)</text>
<text top="534" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="535" left="139" width="396" height="18" font="1">In a couple of years we’ll probably all be women.</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">in which the interpretation of <i>we </i>does indeed comply with her analysis; interpretation,</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that is, goes via the speaker to a plural animate group but, apparently, to one not</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">instantiated by the speaker. But consider a parallel example. Imagine a discussion</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="580" height="18" font="1">between a group of print workers in Fleet Street some time around 1982:</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(18)</text>
<text top="696" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="697" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">In ten years time we’ll probably be one man and a computer working out of an</text>
<text top="721" left="139" width="150" height="18" font="1">office in Wapping.</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Following Grimberg’s argument, the speaker of (18) is, presumably, not intending to</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">include himself in the interpretation of <i>we</i>, therefore the interpretation does not appear</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">to be constrained by Nunberg’s relational component. But, then, the interpretation</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">doesn’t seem to be constrained by Nunberg’s (or Grimberg’s) classificatory component</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">either: you might, I suppose, want to say that <i>one man and his computer</i> denotes a</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">plural entity, but it surely doesn’t denote a plural animate entity. The only way that I</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">can see out of this, arguing that (17) and (18) involve different types of interpretation</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="323" height="18" font="1">process, seems to me to be a non-starter.</text>
<text top="953" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The picture that seems to be emerging here is, as Recanati has argued, of two distinct</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">processes at work: on the one hand the interpretation of <i>we </i>standardly involves deferred</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference, and it is at the level of the output of this process of deferral that the</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation conforms with both the classificatory and relational components posited</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">by Nunberg. This type of deferral is <i>semantic</i>, by which I mean that it is the result of a</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">semantically mandatory phase of the interpretation process. On the other hand, once</text>
</page>
<page number="18" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">18</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">this mandatory process has taken place, there is then a separate<i> pragmatic</i> deferral,</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">constrained by general pragmatic principles, which leads from the output of semantic</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="452" height="18" font="1">deferral as trigger to the eventual interpretation as target.</text>
<text top="279" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">In passing, I just want to mention one more piece of evidence which seems to me to</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">support a pragmatic deferral account of examples such as (17) and (18). Such examples</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">typically have, if not a humorous feel ((17) is, after all, taken from the caption of a</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">cartoon), at least a slightly anomalous feel. And that, it seems to me, is, in relevance</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">theoretic terms, pretty well the hallmark of extra effort yielding extra effects. If, on the</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">other hand, this interpretation were simply the upshot of standard, semantically guided</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="444" height="18" font="1">processes, we’d be hard pushed to explain the anomaly.</text>
<text top="442" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">On this analysis, then, <i>we</i> encodes a two-step procedure something like <i>first find the</i></text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>speaker(s) and then find a group instantiated by the speaker(s)</i>. And it seems inevitable</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">that much the same analysis must apply to plural <i>you</i>, i.e. plural <i>you</i> must encode</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something like <i>first find the addressee(s) and then find a group instantiated by the</i></text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="101" height="18" font="0"><i>addressee(s)</i></text>
<text top="530" left="196" width="14" height="12" font="11">10</text>
<text top="535" left="210" width="588" height="18" font="1">. I don’t propose to provide any arguments for this analysis over and</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="332" height="18" font="1">above those I’ve already provided for <i>we</i>.</text>
<text top="581" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">That deals, then, albeit fleetingly, with Nunberg’s participant terms; how about non-</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">participant terms? Let’s start with <i>he </i>and <i>she</i>. It seems to me that there is no need to</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">propose anything like a deictic component for <i>he</i> and <i>she</i>; after all, even for Nunberg</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">these are not semantically encoded but supplied by an associated demonstration.</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg also agrees that <i>he</i> and <i>she </i>lack relational components, so what does that leave</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">us with? In Nunberg’s terms it leaves us with a classificatory component consisting of</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the features male and singular in the case of <i>he</i>, and female and singular in the case of</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>she</i>; in procedural terms, it leaves <i>he</i> encoding something like <i>find an individual</i></text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>concept with a male referent</i>, and <i>she</i> encoding <i>find an individual concept with a female</i></text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="342" height="18" font="0"><i>referent</i>. The rest can be left to pragmatics.</text>
<text top="813" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">I’ll come on to <i>they</i> in a moment, but first I want to have a look at <i>this</i>, <i>these, that </i>and</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>those</i>. It seems to me that <i>this</i> and <i>that </i>must, at least in some sense, encode a two-step</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">procedure. Take <i>this</i>; in intuitive terms <i>this</i> is used to refer to an object relatively near to</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the speaker, so the hearer must find the speaker before he can find the object referred to.</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">In procedural terms, <i>this</i> must encode something like <i>find the speaker and then find an</i></text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>object near the speaker</i>. The same goes, <i>mutatis mutandis</i>, for <i>that</i>. How about <i>these</i></text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">and <i>those</i>? There might, at first, be a temptation to suggest that <i>these</i> just encodes</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">something like <i>find a group relatively near the speaker</i> and <i>those</i>, <i>find a group</i></text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1037" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">10</text>
<text top="1042" left="122" width="675" height="16" font="5"> This is, of course, only inevitable if we assume a homonymy account for <i>you</i>; i.e. if we assume that</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">singular  <i>you  </i>and plural <i>you </i>are separate lexical items. I don’t have the space here to go into an</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="173" height="16" font="5">examination of this issue.</text>
</page>
<page number="19" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">19</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>relatively distant from the speaker</i>. But Nunberg produces good reasons why this can’t</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">be right or, rather, why this can’t be the whole picture. Consider the following example</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="178" height="18" font="1">from Nunberg (1993):</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(19)</text>
<text top="302" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="303" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>I point in sequence at two sample plates in my china shop, the first sitting in front</i></text>
<text top="326" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>of me, the second on a table across the room</i>: These are over at the warehouse, but</text>
<text top="349" left="139" width="208" height="18" font="1">those I have in stock here.</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">As Nunberg points out, in (19) the referent of <i>these</i> is further from the speaker than the</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referent of <i>those</i>, whereas the index of <i>these</i> is nearer the speaker than the index of</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>those</i>. What this comes down to is that the interpretation of <i>these</i> and <i>those</i> standardly</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">involves deferral just as for <i>we</i>. In procedural terms, <i>these</i>, for instance, must encode</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something like <i>find an object near the speaker and then find a plural referent relating</i></text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="31" height="18" font="0"><i>to it</i></text>
<text top="506" left="126" width="14" height="12" font="11">11</text>
<text top="512" left="140" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="535" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">How about <i>they</i>? Well, <i>they </i>is a little problematic. The problem comes down to this:</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">does  <i>they</i> encode a plural, genderless equivalent of <i>he</i> or <i>she</i> (i.e. <i>find something</i></text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>plural</i>), or does it encode something more like <i>we</i> (i.e. <i>find a he or she and then find a</i></text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>group relating to it</i>)? There is no way that I can see to decide this: since <i>they</i> doesn’t</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">encode anything like the proximality/distality of <i>these</i> and <i>those</i>, both analyses lead to</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the same results. Given this, I don’t propose to spend too much time worrying about the</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="72" height="18" font="1">problem.</text>
<text top="697" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Finally I want to look at indexicals of time and place i.e. things like <i>here</i>, <i>now</i>,</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="0"><i>tomorrow</i> etc. I don’t want to suggest anything particularly revolutionary; in fact,</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">standard accounts of these expressions seem to translate well into procedural terms. On</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">a straightforward analysis, <i>here</i> would encode <i>find the place of utterance</i> (or, more</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">accurately,  <i>find an egocentric concept of the place of utterance</i>); <i>now</i>, <i>find an</i></text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>egocentric concept of the time of utterance</i> and <i>tomorrow</i>, <i>find a concept of the day</i></text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>after the day of utterance</i>. This is all very rough and ready but, as I stressed earlier, it</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="691" height="18" font="1">does not seem to me that a great deal hangs on the minutiae of this procedural account.</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="314" height="18" font="4"><b>5.3 Deferred reference and relevance</b></text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">I have suggested, then, that there may be two separate processes of deferral at work in</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s examples: what I have been calling semantic deferral and pragmatic deferral.</text>
<text top="1041" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1057" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">11</text>
<text top="1062" left="122" width="675" height="16" font="5"> Again, in the cases where <i>these</i> is used to refer to an ostended group, that group will satisfy the full</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="643" height="16" font="5">encoding and will thus be accepted as the intended interpretation unless pragmatically blocked.</text>
</page>
<page number="20" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">20</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Now I want to persuade you that the availability of pragmatically deferred readings is to</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">be expected within a relevance theoretic approach. Why should this be so? Relevance</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Theory embodies a particular conception of the nature of communication: the task</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">facing a hearer is not that of decoding an encoded message, but rather that of inferring</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">speaker intentions. Under this conception of communication the role of linguistic</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning is restricted to providing inputs to the inferential process which will ultimately</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">deliver hypotheses about speaker intentions; or, in other words, linguistic meaning</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">provides evidence for speaker intentions and no more. One upshot of this insight is that</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">so long as the linguistic meaning of an utterance provides sufficient evidence for a</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">hearer to infer the speaker’s intention, it should have served its purpose; the linguistic</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning of an utterance can be as minimal as you like so long as it places adequate</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">constraints on the interpretation process. Now what does this mean in practice? At the</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">heart of Relevance Theory is the notion that interpretation is constrained by a</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="557" height="18" font="1">presumption of optimal relevance; the hearer, that is, can assume that:</text>
<text top="558" left="111" width="16" height="18" font="1">a)</text>
<text top="557" left="126" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="558" left="139" width="660" height="18" font="1">The ostensive stimulus is relevant enough for it to be worth his effort to process it;</text>
<text top="581" left="139" width="29" height="18" font="1">and</text>
<text top="605" left="111" width="17" height="18" font="1">b)</text>
<text top="603" left="127" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="605" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">The ostensive stimulus is the most relevant one compatible with the</text>
<text top="628" left="139" width="327" height="18" font="1">communicator’s abilities and preferences</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">and can conduct the process of interpretation on the strength of these assumptions. If a</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">speaker wants communication to be successful, she had better make sure that the</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">content of her informative intention coincides with the optimally relevant interpretation</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of her utterance. If it does, communication should succeed, if it doesn’t communication</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="90" height="18" font="1">should fail.</text>
<text top="790" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Now how do these observations tie in with deferred reference? Well, so long as the</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">deferred interpretation of a referring expression is the optimally relevant one, then it</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">should be the accepted interpretation. It seems to me that this condition involves two</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">separate requirements: firstly, that the intermediate stage in the interpretation, the</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">trigger, should not, itself, be optimally relevant; and secondly that there should not be</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">any more relevant stimulus which the speaker could have produced (compatible with</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">her abilities and preferences). So long as these conditions are met, however, pragmatic</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="668" height="18" font="1">deferral is to be expected under a relevance theoretic conception of communication.</text>
<text top="1023" left="95" width="319" height="18" font="4"><b>5.4 Pragmatic deferral and indexicals</b></text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Let’s briefly summarise what we’ve seen in the last three sections. Firstly we’ve</text>
</page>
<page number="21" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">21</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">proposed a rough and ready semantics for indexicals on which indexicals encode</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">procedures which lead to individual concepts; and secondly we’ve argued that some</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">kind of pragmatic deferral is no more nor less than we’d expect within a relevance</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">theoretic framework. But what do we get when we put these two ideas together? Well,</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">if the procedures proposed above are anything like right, many of the examples</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg seeks to account for with his tripartite semantics for indexicals must, on our</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">account, be the product of pragmatic deferral. And on the face of it, this has a pretty</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">plausible feel to it. To convince ourselves of this, let’s return to a couple of Nunberg’s</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="614" height="18" font="1">examples; let’s look at examples (7) and (10), repeated here as (20) and (21):</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(20)</text>
<text top="441" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="442" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken by Bill Clinton</i>: The Founders invested me with sole responsibility for</text>
<text top="465" left="139" width="281" height="18" font="1">appointing Supreme Court justices.</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(21)</text>
<text top="511" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="512" left="139" width="443" height="18" font="1">Tomorrow is always the biggest party night of the year.</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">On the semantics for indexicals proposed above, <i>me</i> in (20) will initially lead the hearer</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">to an individual (egocentric) concept of the speaker, i.e. to an individual concept of Bill</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Clinton. Why, then, is this individual concept not accepted as the eventual</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation? We’d like to be able to say that it’s not accepted because it’s not</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">optimally relevant. And why might that be? One possibility is this: put in pretheoretical</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">terms, there’s something bizarre about the idea that the Founders of the United States,</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">in the 18th century, could have made a decision concerning an individual born in the</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">20th century. Finding a context in which this interpretation will have sufficient</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">contextual effects will put the hearer to a great deal of processing effort; the</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation cannot, therefore, be optimally relevant. With this interpretation</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pragmatically blocked, the hearer should, as always, try out the next most accessible</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation. He will, in this case, look within his individual concept of the speaker</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">where he will find the general concept <i>the President of the United States</i>. Finding that</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">an interpretation on which <i>me</i> is interpreted as equivalent to <i>the President of the US</i></text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">provides enough effects for not too much effort, he will accept this interpretation as</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">optimally relevant. The hearer can thus arrive at the deferred interpretation through</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="253" height="18" font="1">standard pragmatic inferencing.</text>
<text top="953" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">Much the same line of argument can be used to account for the interpretation of (21):</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="544" height="18" font="0"><i>tomorrow</i> leads to the hearer’s concept of a particular day </text>
<text top="972" left="639" width="10" height="27" font="13">δ</text>
<text top="976" left="649" width="149" height="18" font="1">; that concept is</text>
<text top="1000" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">pragmatically blocked as the eventual interpretation since <i>always</i> must quantify over</text>
<text top="1023" left="95" width="662" height="18" font="1">instances; the hearer thus hunts through information stored with his concept of </text>
<text top="1018" left="757" width="10" height="27" font="13">δ</text>
<text top="1023" left="767" width="31" height="18" font="1"> for</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">another interpretation and comes up with something like <i>the Saturday before classes</i></text>
<text top="1070" left="95" width="50" height="18" font="0"><i>begin</i>.</text>
</page>
<page number="22" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">22</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">It therefore seems that, on the face of it, we might be able to account for some of</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg’s examples in terms of pragmatic deferral, i.e. in terms of the free operation of</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">pragmatic processes. But, as we already know, things are not that straightforward: if we</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">want to argue for a pragmatic account we’re going to have to tackle Nunberg’s two</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">objections. I imagine that it may already be clear how I intend to deal with Nunberg’s</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">second objection, that deferred readings cannot be pragmatically derived because there</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">is often no coherent literal interpretation for them to be derived from. Recanati (1993)</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">has mounted what seems to me an entirely convincing defence against this objection.</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Nunberg appears to be working on the assumption that any pragmatic account must be</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">based on the retrieval of implicatures; that is, the pragmatic inferencing involved must</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="521" height="18" font="1">operate once a global utterance interpretation has been achieved</text>
<text top="437" left="616" width="14" height="12" font="11">12</text>
<text top="442" left="630" width="168" height="18" font="1">. But why would we</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">necessarily want to assume this? There is, after all, abundant evidence to suggest that</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">pragmatic inferencing is not restricted to the retrieval of implicatures but plays a crucial</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="382" height="18" font="1">role in retrieving the proposition expressed</text>
<text top="506" left="477" width="14" height="12" font="11">13</text>
<text top="512" left="490" width="308" height="18" font="1">. As soon as we assume that the</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">inferencing involved in pragmatic deferral takes place locally rather than globally, as</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Recanati explicitly does, there’s no need for any global interpretation to be retrieved</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">before deferral takes place: it is, in fact, precisely because no ‘literal’ global</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="547" height="18" font="1">interpretation is available, for Recanati, that deferral does take place.</text>
<text top="628" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">What of Nunberg’s first objection, then? If I’m right, and examples such as (20) and</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">(21) really do involve pragmatic deferral, why can we not get the same readings in the</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">same contexts with proper names, if that is the case? Now it seems to me that there may</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">well be no one standard answer to this question, but a whole range of factors which</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">together may prevent deferred readings of proper names from achieving optimal</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">relevance in particular contexts. There are, however, a couple of general patterns which</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">I’d like to draw out, in order to show that we don’t necessarily need to resort to a</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="401" height="18" font="1">semantic account of the type adopted by Nunberg.</text>
<text top="813" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">First, however, we need to establish in which contexts deferred readings really are</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">available for indexicals but blocked for proper names. I want to start by weeding out</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">one group of Nunberg’s examples which seem to me to involve no deferral in any</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="519" height="18" font="1">useful sense. Consider (22), (14), repeated here as (23), and (24):</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(22)</text>
<text top="928" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="930" left="139" width="621" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken while pointing at a girl child to identify her father</i>: He is in real estate.</text>
<text top="980" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="996" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">12</text>
<text top="1001" left="122" width="676" height="16" font="5"> Nunberg does grant that, for Recanati, the pragmatic processes involved in deferral contribute to</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="703" height="16" font="5">the proposition expressed, but he does not seem to have appreciated the significance of this to</text>
<text top="1042" left="95" width="133" height="16" font="5">Recanati’s account.</text>
<text top="1077" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">13</text>
<text top="1082" left="122" width="272" height="16" font="5"> See, for instance, Carston (1988, 1996).</text>
</page>
<page number="23" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">23</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(23)</text>
<text top="209" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="210" left="139" width="563" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken while pointing at a painting</i>: Now <i>he</i> knew how to paint goats.</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(24)</text>
<text top="255" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="256" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken while pointing at a book to identify its author</i>: She was my chemistry</text>
<text top="279" left="139" width="63" height="18" font="1">teacher.</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">On Nunberg’s analysis, the interpretation of each of these examples involves finding an</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">index, as indicated by the demonstration, and then finding an interpretation suitably</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">associated with that index. As we’ve already seen, this forces Nunberg to the</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">conclusion that (22)-(24) involve a different type of interpretation process from (15),</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="172" height="18" font="1">repeated here as (25):</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(25)</text>
<text top="464" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="465" left="139" width="613" height="18" font="0"><i>We are walking through the Taj Mahal</i>: Gee, he certainly spared no expense.</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Now on the face of it that seems a pretty counterintuitive result; as I suggested earlier,</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the Taj Mahal in (25) seems to be playing much the same role in interpretation as, for</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">instance, the painting in (23). Moreover, we could, without any problem, rework (23)</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">so that the painting in question was the only one in the room and (23) was uttered</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="308" height="18" font="1">without any associated demonstration</text>
<text top="599" left="403" width="14" height="12" font="11">14</text>
<text top="605" left="416" width="381" height="18" font="1">. Evidence such as this has led Kaplan (1989)</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">and Bach (1992) to conclude that the role of demonstrations is no more than context</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">shuffling in order to reveal speaker intentions: a speaker, intending to refer to</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something which is not already maximally contextually salient, performs a</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">demonstration; since demonstrations are intentional acts, the hearer will ask himself</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">what the demonstration is for, and will come up with the answer that it is to make</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">something in the context more salient. Interpretation will then proceed according to this</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">new hierarchy of contextual salience. Now if Kaplan and Bach are right, there is no</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">need for the speaker to point at the actual referent; after all, in (22)-(24) this wouldn’t</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">be possible. All the speaker need do is point at something which makes the intended</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation optimally relevant in the revised context. On this analysis, the</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation processes involved in (22)-(24) are no different from that involved in</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="607" height="18" font="1">(25): each involves assigning reference to an indexical according to context.</text>
<text top="906" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Ah, says Grimberg (1996), but there must be some deferral, because there is an</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">obvious way in which these examples can give rise to general interpretations, the very</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">hallmark of deferral. Consider, for instance, if the speaker of (23) has no idea who the</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">goat-painter is, or the speaker of (25), who built the Taj Mahal. The interpretation in</text>
<text top="1021" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1037" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">14</text>
<text top="1042" left="122" width="676" height="16" font="5"> Nunberg might argue that there was an implicit demonstration in such a case but, given that, as</text>
<text top="1062" left="95" width="702" height="16" font="5">we’ve seen, Nunberg himself admits that it’s sometimes hard to tell when there is an implicit</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="562" height="16" font="5">demonstration and when not, I can’t see that this would be a very fruitful approach.</text>
</page>
<page number="24" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">24</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">each case must, then, be equivalent to a definite description attributively used. Now it</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">seems to me that the distinction drawn earlier between individual and general concepts</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">can help us to overcome this objection: in each case the hearer simply retrieves an</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">individual concept, as required by the semantics of the indexical. So the hearer of (23)</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">will simply retrieve, or open, an individual concept containing the information <i>is the</i></text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>painter of that painting</i>,  and insert that concept into his interpretation; in much the</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">same way the hearer of (25) will retrieve or open a concept containing the information</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>is the person who built the Taj Mahal</i>. The key point is that, in each case, the hearer is</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">accessing a concept which he believes to correspond to a unique individual in the</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="635" height="18" font="1">world, albeit an individual with whom he may have no direct epistemic contact.</text>
<text top="442" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">Finally, before addressing Nunberg’s second objection to pragmatic accounts, there</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">are a couple of pitfalls we would do well to be wary of. Recanati (1993) argues that</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">many of the general interpretations that Nunberg cites for indexicals are simply illusory.</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="675" height="18" font="1">Let’s just have a look at one of the examples he tackles, taken from Nunberg (1990):</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(26)</text>
<text top="557" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="558" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">In the movie <i>The Year of Living Dangerously</i>, Mel Gibson plays a reporter in</text>
<text top="581" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">Sukarno’s Indonesia who is looking for a shipment of arms destined for the local</text>
<text top="605" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">communists; who will kill him if they find out he is on to them. He is interviewing</text>
<text top="628" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">a warehouse manager, who tells him, ‘I have seen no such shipment. And you</text>
<text top="651" left="139" width="410" height="18" font="1">should be careful; I might have been a communist’.</text>
<text top="674" left="615" width="183" height="18" font="1">Recanati (1993, p 301)</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Nunberg points out that there are two possible readings of <i>I might have been a</i></text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>communist</i> in (30): on one reading the warehouse manager is saying, of himself, that he</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">might have been a communist (given a different upbringing, say); on the other, the</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">preferred reading in the context, he is saying something like <i>The person you are talking</i></text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="0"><i>to might have been a communist</i>. For Nunberg the first reading is singular, since <i>I</i></text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">contributes an individual, and the second is general, since <i>I</i> contributes a concept (or</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>property</i> in Nunberg’s terms). Recanati starts by asking the following question: what</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">thought is it that a hearer must think in order to have understood an utterance of (26)?</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">And the answer he comes up with is that the hearer must think something like <i>That man</i></text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>might have been a communist</i>, with <i>that man</i> corresponding to an egocentric concept of</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the warehouse manager. But surely that leads us straight back to our first interpretation,</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">i.e. to the interpretation on which the speaker is saying of himself that he might have</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">been a communist? No, says Recanati, and this becomes clear as soon as we understand</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the distinction between metaphysically possible worlds and epistemically possible</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">worlds. For Recanati, the speaker of (26) is not saying that there is a metaphysically</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">possible world at which he is a communist; rather, he is saying that there is an</text>
</page>
<page number="25" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">25</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">epistemically possible world at which this is the case. To put this another way, in order</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="648" height="18" font="1">to understand (26), a hearer must entertain a thought which looks something like:</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(27)</text>
<text top="278" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="279" left="139" width="441" height="18" font="1">For all I know, that man might have been a communist.</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">The proposition the hearer entertains in understanding (26), then, does, just as Nunberg</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">claims, contain a concept, but, crucially, it is a de re concept and thus contributes</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">nothing to truth conditions beyond its referent. Translating this argument into the terms</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">we’ve been developing in this paper, the interpretation of (26) just involves retrieving</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">an individual concept of the speaker, as determined by the semantics of <i>I</i> and goes no</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">further. For Recanati, many of Nunberg’s examples are just such sheep in wolves’</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="70" height="18" font="1">clothing.</text>
<text top="488" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The second potential pitfall which we should be aware of is illustrated by (1). In his</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">analysis of (1), Nunberg assumes an interpretation of <i>traditionally</i> which requires that it</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">should quantify over instances; and, given this assumption, it follows naturally that <i>I</i></text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">cannot have a de re interpretation. But are we sure that Nunberg is right about</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="444" height="18" font="0"><i>traditionally</i>? Consider the following paraphrase of (1):</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(28)</text>
<text top="627" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="628" left="139" width="533" height="18" font="1">By tradition, I’m allowed to order whatever I like for my last meal.</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Now I hope you agree that, in (28), there is no reason to assume that <i>by tradition</i></text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">quantifies over instances. Given this, how can we be sure that <i>traditionally</i> in (1) is not</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpreted as equivalent to <i>by tradition</i> in (28)? And, if that’s right, there’s no reason to</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">suppose that <i>I</i> receives anything other than a perfectly straightforward de re</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation in (1). Moreover, Nunberg himself seems to have doubts about the</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation of <i>traditionally</i> in this example. In a discussion of (1) he, apparently</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">inadvertently, slips from using <i>traditionally</i> to using <i>usually</i>, the semantics of which</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">seem much clearer (see Nunberg (1993, p 32)). It’s interesting to note, however, that</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the claimed deferred reading of (1) becomes markedly less accessible when we replace</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="208" height="18" font="0"><i>traditionally </i>with<i> usually</i>:</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(29)</text>
<text top="928" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="930" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Condemned prisoner</i>: I am usually allowed to order whatever I like for my last</text>
<text top="953" left="139" width="44" height="18" font="1">meal.</text>
<text top="1023" left="95" width="353" height="18" font="4"><b>5.5 Pragmatic deferral and proper names</b></text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">With those caveats under our belt, the time has come to look at Nunberg’s second</text>
</page>
<page number="26" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">26</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">objection to pragmatic accounts: that deferred readings are unavailable for proper</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">names in the same contexts in which they are available for indexicals. The first question</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">we’re going to need to ask is whether Nunberg is right; whether it is always the case</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that deferred interpretations are unavailable for proper names. It would, after all, be</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">quite surprising if deferred readings of proper names were never available, given that,</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">as we’ve seen, pragmatically deferred readings are to be expected under a relevance</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">theoretic conception of communication. And there do, indeed, seem to be cases in</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">which proper names can give rise to deferred interpretations just as indexicals can.</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Imagine yourself in Allied Command Headquarters, some time around May 1944; you</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="209" height="18" font="1">overhear someone saying:</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(30)</text>
<text top="464" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="465" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">I’ve looked through the meteorological charts and D-Day has been the hottest day</text>
<text top="488" left="139" width="324" height="18" font="1">of the year every year for the last decade</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">How are you going to interpret the expression <i>D-Day</i> in this utterance? It seems to me</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">you’ll probably interpret it as <i>June 6th</i>. The interpretation process, that is, will go via an</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="645" height="18" font="1">individual concept of June 6th 1944 to a general, or generic, concept of June 6th.</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">There do seem, however, to be certain contexts in which, as Nunberg argues, deferred</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretations are available for indexicals but blocked for proper names, and these</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="704" height="18" font="1">examples provide Nunberg with the core of his argument against pragmatic accounts of</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">deferred reference. Consider the following examples, some of which we’ve already</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="41" height="18" font="1">seen:</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(31)</text>
<text top="743" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="744" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="0"><i>Spoken by Justice O’Connor, a member of the US Supreme Court</i>: We might have</text>
<text top="767" left="139" width="106" height="18" font="1">been liberals.</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(32)</text>
<text top="812" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="813" left="139" width="484" height="18" font="1">O’Connor, Rehnquist, Thomas etc. might have been liberals.</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(33)</text>
<text top="859" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="860" left="139" width="660" height="18" font="1">The Founders invested me with sole responsibility for appointing Supreme Court</text>
<text top="883" left="139" width="64" height="18" font="1">justices.</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(34)</text>
<text top="928" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="930" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">The Founders invested Bill Clinton with sole responsibility for appointing</text>
<text top="953" left="139" width="191" height="18" font="1">Supreme Court justices.</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Now Nunberg’s claim is that (31) and (33) have two readings each whereas (32) and</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">(34) have just one each. Whether or not he is right that deferred readings of (32) and</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">(34) are entirely unavailable, there does seem to be a marked disparity in the availability</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">of such readings between the examples using indexicals and those using proper names.</text>
</page>
<page number="27" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">27</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">And, on the face of it, this looks like strong evidence in favour of Nunberg’s account,</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">or something like it; after all, the examples are set up so that the different referring</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="400" height="18" font="1">expressions appear in precisely the same contexts.</text>
<text top="279" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">Perhaps, then, Nunberg is right and the procedures proposed above are far too simple;</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">perhaps we do need to build into the semantics of many more indexicals elements of</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning leading to an index and other elements of meaning leading from index to</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation. But before we give so much away, could there be any other reasons for</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the unavailability of deferred readings of proper names in these contexts? It seems to</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="158" height="18" font="1">me that there could.</text>
<text top="419" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Let’s first consider (31) and (32). Now, to be honest, I’m not entirely sure whether or</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">not (32) does have only a de re reading as Nunberg claims; it seems to me that in certain</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">lights I can get an attributive reading. But if Nunberg is right and there is no attributive</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reading, there may well be a good reason for it without having to resort to a semantic</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">deferral account. As we’ve already seen above, the interpretation of <i>we</i> does standardly</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">involve a two-stage process: from expression to speaker and from speaker to group</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">instantiated by speaker. As part of the mandatory interpretation process, therefore, the</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">hearer must retrieve some kind of property delimiting the group which, in Fauconnier’s</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">terms, provides the trigger for the pragmatic deferral in these cases. This property (in</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the case of (31) the property of being Supreme Court justices) is, therefore, made highly</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">contextually salient and it is a small (and, in processing terms, uncostly) leap from this</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">property <i>indicatively</i> used to the same property <i>attributively </i>used. In (32), by contrast,</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation does not involve the retrieval of any joint property: the proper names in</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">(32) present their referents individually, not jointly. It must therefore be a more costly</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">step, in processing terms, to retrieve the intended property in (32) than in (31); (32),</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">therefore, cannot be the most relevant stimulus the speaker could have produced, given</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that (31) (or the equivalent using <i>they</i>, <i>you</i> etc) offers the same effects for less</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="128" height="18" font="1">processing cost.</text>
<text top="837" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">How about (33) and (34) then? I want to suggest a possible account for these two</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">examples which I hope might well shed light on a wide range of the cases in which</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">there truly does appear to be a disparity between indexicals and proper names.</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Indexicals and proper names differ in two significant (although non-semantic) ways.</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Firstly the linguistic meaning of indexicals, the procedures they encode, are, in obvious</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">ways, bound to the context of utterance. This has the by-product that the link between</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">an indexical and its referent is typically short-term: I can only refer to here as <i>here</i></text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">while I am actually here, I can only refer to you as <i>you</i> while I am addressing you. This</text>
<text top="1022" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">is simply a result of the fact that the kind of properties encoded by the meaning of</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">indexicals, properties such as being the speaker or the addressee, are temporary. The</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">link between a name and its referent, by contrast, remains stable across contexts: I can</text>
</page>
<page number="28" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">28</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">refer to Tony Blair by uttering <i>Tony Blair</i> regardless of where or when I am speaking</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">(so long as my addressee knows who <i>Tony Blair</i> names or, rather, so long as he has an</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">individual concept relating to Tony Blair which contains the information<i> is called Tony</i></text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>Blair</i>). Moreover, any number of other people can also refer to Tony Blair by uttering</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>Tony Blair</i>. The other difference between indexicals and proper names we’ve already</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">seen: understanding an indexical standardly involves retrieving an egocentric concept,</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">whereas understanding a proper name standardly involves retrieving an encyclopaedic</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">concept. And, as we know, egocentric concepts tend to be repositories of short-term,</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">perceptual information, whereas encyclopaedic concepts generally store long-term,</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="204" height="18" font="1">propositional information</text>
<text top="414" left="299" width="14" height="12" font="11">15</text>
<text top="419" left="313" width="5" height="18" font="1">.</text>
<text top="442" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">Now how might these differences help us explain the data we’re trying to explain?</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Consider (33) and (34) again: why can <i>Bill Clinton</i> in (34) not lead to the same general</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reading as <i>me</i> in (33)? Saul (1997) points out that failure of substitutivity of co-</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referential names (or something that looks very much like it) is not limited to those</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="682" height="18" font="1">contexts usually thought of as referentially opaque. Consider the following examples:</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(35)</text>
<text top="580" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="581" left="139" width="509" height="18" font="1">Clark Kent went into the phone booth, and Superman came out.</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(36)</text>
<text top="627" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="628" left="139" width="511" height="18" font="1">Clark Kent went into the phone booth and Clark Kent came out.</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">Although <i>Clark Kent</i> and <i>Superman</i> are co-referential, there nevertheless appears to be</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a difference between what is expressed by (35) and (36). Much the same effect can be</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="607" height="18" font="1">shown to arise in the linguistic context of examples (33) and (34). Consider:</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(37)</text>
<text top="766" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="767" left="139" width="639" height="18" font="1">The Mayor of Metropolis invested Superman with the power to arrest criminals.</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(38)</text>
<text top="812" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="813" left="139" width="645" height="18" font="1">The Mayor of Metropolis invested Clark Kent with the power to arrest criminals.</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Again there seems to be a difference: the most accessible interpretation of (37) seems to</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">involve the Mayor investing Superman, as Superman, with the power to arrest</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">criminals, and the most accessible interpretation of (38) involves him investing Clark</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Kent, as Clark Kent, with this power. In other words, the mode of presentation seems to</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">be getting into the proposition expressed somehow. With this in mind, let’s return to</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">(34): the most accessible interpretation of (34) is going to involve the Founders</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">investing Bill Clinton, as Bill Clinton, with responsibility for appointing Supreme Court</text>
<text top="1041" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1057" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">15</text>
<text top="1062" left="122" width="676" height="16" font="5"> Again, for more extensive argument in favour of the egocentric-encyclopaedic distinction, see</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="184" height="16" font="5">Recanati (1993, chapter 7).</text>
</page>
<page number="29" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">29</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">justices. A hearer who wants to reach a deferred interpretation of (34), therefore, will</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">have to go to the effort of eliminating the extra information provided by the mode of</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">presentation. This extra effort, it seems to me, may bar (34) from being the optimally</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">relevant stimulus for a speaker who wishes to communicate the deferred interpretation;</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="240" height="18" font="1">he could, after all, simply say:</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="34" height="18" font="1">(39)</text>
<text top="348" left="129" width="6" height="19" font="9"> </text>
<text top="349" left="139" width="659" height="18" font="1">The Founders invested the President with sole responsibility for appointing</text>
<text top="372" left="139" width="191" height="18" font="1">Supreme Court justices.</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">requiring no such extra processing effort from the hearer. Why, then, is there no such</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">effect in the case of (33)? The answer to this seems to come in two parts: firstly, since</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the linguistic modes of presentation associated with indexicals are context-bound, there</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">can be no implication that the Founders made their decision about Bill Clinton under</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the mode of presentation encoded by <i>I</i>; that is, the Founders cannot have decided to</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">give the responsibility to Bill Clinton, under the mode of presentation <i>speaker of this</i></text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="0"><i>utterance</i>. A hearer thus has to expend no extra processing effort, as he does for (34).</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">But secondly, we must ask ourselves why (39), in which there is no deferral, is not a</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">more relevant stimulus than (33), given that it would seem to require less processing</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">effort. I guess the answer may look something like this: there is an expectation that a</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">speaker, talking of a group or property which she instantiates, will use a first-person</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">indexical; a failure to do so will raise expectations of extra effects for extra effort, for</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">instance that the speaker is trying to distance herself from the group or property. Now</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">I’m not suggesting that this is a hard and fast rule, but rather that it is one factor that</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="535" height="18" font="1">may affect the relevance of particular stimuli in particular contexts.</text>
<text top="767" left="111" width="687" height="18" font="1">The disparity between examples such as (33) and those such as (34) may, then, be the</text>
<text top="790" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">result of a parallel disparity between the stability across contexts of the modes of</text>
<text top="813" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">presentation linguistically encoded by indexicals and proper names. There seems to me</text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">to be another possibility, however: that this difference is not (or not only) down to the</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">linguistic modes of presentation of indexicals and proper names but (also) to what</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Recanati (1993) calls their psychological modes of presentation, i.e. to the different</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">types of concept they correspond to. Why might this be so? The linguistically encoded</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">meaning of proper names is such that understanding a proper name consists in</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">retrieving an encyclopaedic concept; that is, in retrieving a store of propositional</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="365" height="18" font="1">information all relating to a single individual</text>
<text top="971" left="460" width="14" height="12" font="11">16</text>
<text top="976" left="474" width="324" height="18" font="1">. Now consider what that means for the</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">interpretation of an utterance such as (34): if the speaker of (34) intends his addressee to</text>
<text top="1041" left="95" width="216" height="16" font="7">                                                </text>
<text top="1057" left="111" width="11" height="10" font="12">16</text>
<text top="1062" left="122" width="676" height="16" font="5"> For a more detailed account of the relation between names and encyclopaedic concepts, see</text>
<text top="1082" left="95" width="242" height="16" font="5">Recanati (1993) and Powell (1997).</text>
</page>
<page number="30" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">30</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">retrieve a deferred interpretation parallel to that available for (33), he is putting his</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">addressee to gratuitous processing effort. The addressee must first access a body of</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">propositional information all pointing at a single individual and then throw that body of</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">information out again in order to retrieve the intended interpretation. A rational</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">addressee will be left asking: why did the speaker use a proper name, and thus get me to</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="701" height="18" font="1">retrieve all this information, if she didn’t want me to use any of it? There are, after all,</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">utterances such as (39) which would have required me to go to no such effort for the</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">same effects. However, a speaker who utters (33), intending his addressee to retrieve a</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">deferred reading, is putting his addressee to no such effort: as we’ve already seen</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">egocentric concepts don’t contain large amounts of propositional information, as</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">encyclopaedic concepts do, but, rather, short-term perceptual information. The hearer</text>
<text top="465" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">doesn’t, therefore, have to filter out lots of unnecessary information in order to retrieve</text>
<text top="488" left="95" width="215" height="18" font="1">the intended interpretation.</text>
<text top="512" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">These two lines of argument are clearly closely allied but it seems to me that they are,</text>
<text top="535" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">nonetheless, distinct. As I hope I have made clear, one relies on the relative stability of</text>
<text top="558" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">the expression-referent link across contexts, while the other relies on the kind of</text>
<text top="581" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">information stored in psychological modes of presentation. It seems to me entirely</text>
<text top="605" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">possible that both of these factors may kick in to bar deferred readings of proper names</text>
<text top="628" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">in contexts such as (34). My only aim here is to demonstrate that there may well be</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">good explanations for this data which do not require a semantics for indexicals such as</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">that proposed by Nunberg; in other words, to show that deferred reference in these</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">examples may well be the product of free pragmatic processes operating at a sub-</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="154" height="18" font="1">propositional level.</text>
<text top="791" left="95" width="116" height="18" font="4"><b>6. Conclusion</b></text>
<text top="837" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">I hope, then, that I have managed to convince you of the following: that deferred</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">reference may well not be the single phenomenon Nunberg would have us believe; that</text>
<text top="883" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">there may well be two entirely distinct types of deferral, what I have been calling</text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">semantic deferral and pragmatic deferral, at work in Nunberg’s examples; and that the</text>
<text top="930" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">arguments Nunberg uses in support of a semantic account for the entire range of his</text>
<text top="953" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">examples may not be quite so robust as they at first seem. There may, in fact, be</text>
<text top="976" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">perfectly good pragmatic accounts of deferral, grounded in a proper understanding of</text>
<text top="999" left="95" width="419" height="18" font="1">the cognitive background which underlies reference.</text>
<text top="1022" left="111" width="688" height="18" font="1">But we started this whole discussion with the idea that Nunberg’s deferred uses pose</text>
<text top="1046" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">a grave threat to the tenets of direct reference theory, at least so far as indexicals are</text>
<text top="1069" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">concerned. Where, then, does direct reference stand at the end of our discussion?</text>
</page>
<page number="31" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="592" width="163" height="16" font="6"><i>Deferred interpretation</i></text>
<text top="169" left="780" width="17" height="16" font="5">31</text>
<text top="210" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">Surprisingly, this seems to be the subject of considerable agreement between the</text>
<text top="233" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">opposing camps. Recanati (1993) argues that Nunberg’s examples are only a threat to</text>
<text top="256" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">direct reference on a strong reading, a reading on which the distinction between directly</text>
<text top="279" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referential expressions and descriptions is taken to be, essentially, that directly</text>
<text top="303" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referential expressions lead to singular propositions while descriptions lead to general</text>
<text top="326" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">propositions. For Recanati, however, a weaker reading of direct reference remains</text>
<text top="349" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">unchallenged by Nunberg’s data; on that reading, the difference resides not in directly</text>
<text top="372" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">referential expressions leading to singular propositions but rather in the fact that the</text>
<text top="396" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">process of interpretation of directly referential expressions must, mandatorily, pass via</text>
<text top="419" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">an individual, even if interpretation then continues, guided by general pragmatic</text>
<text top="442" left="95" width="254" height="18" font="1">constraints, past that individual.</text>
<text top="465" left="111" width="372" height="18" font="1">And Nunberg finds much to agree with in this:</text>
<text top="512" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">I think Recanati is right to insist that the central claim of direct-reference</text>
<text top="535" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">theories - “the thesis of the <i>asymmetry</i> between referential and nonreferential</text>
<text top="558" left="139" width="615" height="18" font="1">terms” - survives the challenges posed by the observations I have offered</text>
<text top="581" left="139" width="39" height="18" font="1">here.</text>
<text top="605" left="543" width="211" height="18" font="1">Nunberg (1993, pp 32-33)</text>
<text top="651" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">The effect of Nunberg’s objections, then, has been this: to highlight that direct reference</text>
<text top="674" left="95" width="702" height="18" font="1">cannot be a theory of propositional content; but, after all, once we understand the</text>
<text top="697" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">integral role that pragmatic inference plays in retrieving the proposition expressed, we</text>
<text top="721" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">could never have expected direct reference to be any such thing. Direct reference</text>
<text top="744" left="95" width="703" height="18" font="1">should, rather, be taken as a theory about differences in encoded meaning and, as such,</text>
<text top="767" left="95" width="490" height="18" font="1">it remains, as far as I can see, unscathed by Nunberg’s attack.</text>
<text top="860" left="95" width="93" height="18" font="4"><b>References</b></text>
<text top="906" left="95" width="465" height="16" font="5">Bach, K. 1992. Intentions and demonstrations. <i>Analysis</i> 52, 140-146.</text>
<text top="926" left="95" width="562" height="16" font="5">Berckmans, P. 1990. Demonstrative utterances. <i>Philosophical Studies</i> 60, 281-295.</text>
<text top="946" left="95" width="524" height="16" font="5">Blakemore, D. 1987. <i>Semantic Constraints on Relevance</i>. Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="967" left="95" width="658" height="16" font="5">Carston, R. 1988. Implicature, explicature, and truth-theoretic semantics. In R. Kempson (ed)</text>
<text top="987" left="111" width="643" height="16" font="6"><i>Mental representations: the interface between language and reality</i>, 155-181. Cambridge:</text>
<text top="1007" left="111" width="194" height="16" font="5">Cambridge University Press.</text>
<text top="1027" left="95" width="658" height="16" font="5">Carston, R. 1996. Enrichment and loosening: complementary processes in deriving the</text>
<text top="1047" left="111" width="463" height="16" font="5">proposition expressed. <i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics</i> 8, 61-88.</text>
<text top="1067" left="95" width="649" height="16" font="5">Donnellan, K. 1966. Reference and definite description. <i>The Philosophical Review</i> 75, 281-304.</text>
</page>
<page number="32" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1263" width="892">
<text top="169" left="95" width="17" height="16" font="5">32</text>
<text top="169" left="153" width="104" height="16" font="6"><i>George Powell</i></text>
<text top="209" left="95" width="533" height="16" font="5">Fauconnier, G. 1994. <i>Mental Spaces</i>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</text>
<text top="230" left="95" width="659" height="16" font="5">Grice, P. 1969. Vacuous names. In D. Davidson and J. Hintikka (eds) <i>Words and Objections</i>,</text>
<text top="250" left="111" width="182" height="16" font="5">118-45. Dordrecht: Reidel.</text>
<text top="270" left="95" width="658" height="16" font="5">Grimberg. M. L. 1996. <i>Against rigidity: an investigation of the semantics and pragmatics of</i></text>
<text top="290" left="111" width="477" height="16" font="6"><i>indexicality</i>. Ph.D. thesis, UCL. Page references are to revised version.</text>
<text top="310" left="95" width="659" height="16" font="5">Kaplan, D. 1977. Demonstratives. In J. Almog, J. Perry and H. Wettstein (eds.)<i> Themes from</i></text>
<text top="330" left="111" width="370" height="16" font="6"><i>Kaplan</i>, 481-563. New York: Oxford University Press.</text>
<text top="351" left="95" width="659" height="16" font="5">Kaplan, D. 1989. Afterthoughts. In J. Almog, J. Perry and H. Wettstein (eds.)<i> Themes from</i></text>
<text top="371" left="111" width="370" height="16" font="6"><i>Kaplan</i>, 565-614. New York: Oxford University Press.</text>
<text top="391" left="95" width="659" height="16" font="5">Nunberg, G. 1978. <i>The Pragmatics of Reference</i>. Bloomington: Indiana University Linguistics</text>
<text top="411" left="111" width="37" height="16" font="5">Club.</text>
<text top="431" left="95" width="658" height="16" font="5">Nunberg, G. 1990. Indexicality in contexts. Paper delivered at the conference on philosophy and</text>
<text top="451" left="111" width="362" height="16" font="5">cognitive science, Cerisy-la-Salle, France, June 1990.</text>
<text top="472" left="95" width="540" height="16" font="5">Nunberg, G. 1993. Indexicality and deixis. <i>Linguistics and Philosophy</i> 16, 1-43.</text>
<text top="492" left="95" width="515" height="16" font="5">Nunberg, G. 1995. Transfers of meaning. <i>Journal of Semantics</i> 12, 109-132.</text>
<text top="512" left="95" width="485" height="16" font="5">Powell, G. 1997. Names. UCL MA Dissertation. Unpublished ms UCL.</text>
<text top="532" left="95" width="559" height="16" font="5">Recanati, F. 1993. <i>Direct reference: from language to thought</i>. Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="552" left="95" width="492" height="16" font="5">Saul, J. 1997. Substitution and simple sentences. <i>Analysis </i>57.2, 102-108.</text>
<text top="572" left="95" width="584" height="16" font="5">Wilson, D. and D. Sperber. 1993. Linguistic form and Relevance. <i>Lingua </i>90.1/2, 1-25.</text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
