<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="0.86.1">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="0" size="16" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="11" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="21" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="7" size="16" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="1005" left="129" width="682" height="15" font="0">I would like to thank Deirdre Wilson for her useful suggestions, the participants in the Relevance</text>
<text top="1001" left="123" width="6" height="11" font="1">*</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Reading Group who acted as my informants, and Hans van de Koot for many enjoyable discussions</text>
<text top="1045" left="108" width="390" height="15" font="0">about connectives. Needless to say, all mistakes are mine.</text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="364" height="18" font="2"><i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics 8 (1996)</i></text>
<text top="184" left="108" width="623" height="32" font="3"><i><b>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</b></i></text>
<text top="180" left="731" width="11" height="19" font="4"><i><b>*</b></i></text>
<text top="269" left="108" width="175" height="18" font="5">VILLY ROUCHOTA</text>
<text top="341" left="162" width="75" height="18" font="6"><b>Abstract</b></text>
<text top="387" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="0">Discourse connectives (eg. <i>but</i>, <i>moreover</i>, <i>therefore</i>, <i>so</i>, etc.) have been analysed within</text>
<text top="407" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="0">the coherence theory framework as linking units of discourse; within the relevance-</text>
<text top="427" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="0">theoretic framework they are seen as linking a unit of discourse and a context, which may</text>
<text top="446" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="0">be consisting of prior discourse but often is not. These two approaches are discussed and</text>
<text top="466" left="162" width="594" height="15" font="0">evidence, drawing on the syntactic and semantic properties of connectives as well as tests</text>
<text top="486" left="162" width="547" height="15" font="0">on conditions of usage, is provided in support of the relevance-theoretic analysis.</text>
<text top="566" left="108" width="125" height="18" font="6"><b>1 Introduction</b></text>
<text top="613" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">In this paper I will discuss the semantics of connectives, i.e. little words like <i>whereas</i>, <i>but</i>,</text>
<text top="637" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>moreover</i>, etc, and investigate the way they contribute to utterance interpretation. I will</text>
<text top="661" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">briefly review and compare the relevance-theoretic approach to connectives and, what I</text>
<text top="684" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">will call, the coherence-based approach. There are, as we will see, important differences</text>
<text top="708" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">as well as some striking similarities between the two accounts. The discussion here will</text>
<text top="732" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">focus on a question which receives quite different answers in the two accounts: What do</text>
<text top="756" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives link? Do they link the utterance they introduce with previous discourse units,</text>
<text top="779" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">as coherence theorists believe, or do they link that utterance with a context, which may</text>
<text top="803" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">be verbal but often is not, as relevance theorists argue? And what are the implications of</text>
<text top="827" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">taking one or the other view for building an adequate account of the role of connectives</text>
<text top="851" left="108" width="164" height="18" font="5">in communication?  </text>
<text top="874" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">I will often be referring to 'the relevance-theoretic appoach' to connectives and the</text>
<text top="898" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">'coherence-based approach' to connectives, without mentioning specific works. So, let me</text>
<text top="922" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">start by explaining which people and what kind of work I have in mind in each case.</text>
<text top="946" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Within relevance theory the most influential work on connectives is Diane Blakemore's</text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="5">2</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">book <i>Semantic Constraints on Relevance</i>, published in 1987 and followed by a series of</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">articles, where she puts forward an account of connectives based on relevance-theoretic</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">assumptions about communication and, crucially, introduces the idea, about which more</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">shortly, that connectives encode procedural, rather than conceptual information. This line</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">of investigation has since been very fruitful (for references see Wilson and Sperber 1993</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="251" height="18" font="5">and Sperber and Wilson 1995).</text>
<text top="337" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Within coherence theory, on the other hand, people discuss the role of connectives from</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">rather different angles; what brings their work together is a number of background</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">assumptions: that texts are coherent, that there is a definable set of coherence relations,</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">and that the recovery of such coherence relations are essential for comprehension. The</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">set of connectives I will be considering here are among the so-called 'cue words' whose</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">function is to make such coherence relations explicit. Here I want to mention in particular</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the work by Mann and Thompson (1986), Knott &amp; Dale (1994), Sanders, Spooren and</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="417" height="18" font="5">Noordman (1993), Fraser (1990), and Hovy (1994).</text>
<text top="575" left="108" width="462" height="18" font="6"><b>2 Relevance theory, coherence theory and connectives</b></text>
<text top="621" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Relevance theory and coherence theory take very different views on communication and</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">that has consequences for the analysis of connectives suggested by each of these</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">frameworks. I will not give here a detailed review of each position but rather I will focus</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">on one similarity in the way the two accounts analyse connectives and one important</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="87" height="18" font="5">difference.</text>
<text top="740" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="5">Coherence theorists assume that the most important property of texts, crucially involved</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">both in text generation and in text comprehension, is that texts are coherent. Coherence</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">is analysable in terms of a set of coherence relations, i.e. a set of implicit relations that</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">bind/hold the text together. Examples of coherence relations are CAUSE, SEQUENCE,</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">CONDITION, EVIDENCE, ELABORATION, etc. Now, text comprehension crucially</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">hinges on the recovery of such relations. So, to take a famous example from Mann and</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Thompson (1986: 60), a coherence-based analysis of the discourse in (1) would go</text>
<text top="906" left="108" width="136" height="18" font="5">roughly like this:</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(1)</text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="320" height="18" font="5">I'm hungry. Let's go to the Fuji Gardens</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">(1) is a coherent piece of discourse. The two utterances are somehow held together. To</text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">understand this discourse the hearer has to, among other things, recover the coherence</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="5">3</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">relation between the two discourse units. Mann and Thompson propose that the relation</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">in question here is SOLUTIONHOOD. So, to interpret (1) the hearer has to recover a</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="242" height="18" font="5">relational proposition like (2):</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(2)</text>
<text top="289" left="162" width="648" height="18" font="5">Our going to the Fuji Gardens is a partial solution to my problem of being hungry</text>
<text top="337" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Where do connectives come in in this account of utterance interpretation? For</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">coherence theorists connectives may be used to make the implicit coherence relations</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">explicit — hence, the term 'cue words/ phrases'. For example, <i>but</i> in (3) makes explicit</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="520" height="18" font="5">the relation of CONTRADICTION (Ivir et al. from Hovy 1994):</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(3)</text>
<text top="455" left="162" width="235" height="18" font="5">He votes Tory but I trust him</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">where CONTRADICTION is defined in the following way: 'The discourse structure</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="506" height="18" font="5">relation implies that S2 is not an expected consequence of S1'. </text>
<text top="550" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Let me now turn to the relevance-theoretic account. I will not here outline the basic</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">assumptions of relevance theory. I will only briefly mention two issues that have a</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">prominent role in the relevance-theoretic account of utterance interpretation and which</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">are crucial for the relevance-theoretic account of connectives. The first one has to do with</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">the selection and role of context, the second one has to do with the importance of</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="487" height="18" font="5">processing effort considerations in interpreting an utterance.</text>
<text top="693" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Usually a speaker has a specific interpretation of her utterance in mind and expects the</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">hearer to arrive at that interpretation. To arrive at the intended interpretation of an</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">utterance the hearer must process that utterance in the right, i.e. the intended context. The</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">selection of context is governed by considerations of optimal relevance. Now, the speaker</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">may have reason to believe that the hearer will choose the appropriate contextual</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">assumptions and draw the appropriate conclusions without any extra help from her, or she</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">may decide to direct the hearer towards the intended interpretation by making a certain</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">set of assumptions immediately accessible. Connectives is one of the linguistic devices</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="645" height="18" font="5">the speaker may use to that effect. According to Blakemore (1987:77, 1989:21) </text>
<text top="931" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">Their sole function is to guide the interpretation process by specifying</text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="593" height="18" font="5">certain properties of context and contextual effects. In a relevance-based</text>
<text top="978" left="162" width="595" height="18" font="5">framework, where the aim is to minimise processing costs, the use of such</text>
<text top="1002" left="162" width="240" height="18" font="5">expressions is to be expected.</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="5">4</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Recall that accessing the context in which an utterance is to be interpreted involves a cost,</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">and that the greater the processing effort required to arrive at an interpretation the less</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">relevant that interpretation is. The presence of one connective or another guides the</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hearer towards the intended contextual assumptions and effects; in other words the</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">speaker gives a clear indication as to how she intends her utterance to achieve relevance</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">and thus she saves the hearer some processing effort in arriving at the intended</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="114" height="18" font="5">interpretation.</text>
<text top="360" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">On Blakemore's account the analysis of (3) would go like this:The speaker uses <i>but</i> to</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">indicate that the proposition it introduces is relevant as a denial of an expectation created</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">by the proposition expressed by the first clause. She utters the <i>but</i>-clause because she</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">believes that the first utterance has given rise to a contextual implication, namely that the</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">speaker does not trust 'him', which she wants to deny. Note that if <i>but</i> was not there the</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hearer could construe the second proposition in a different way: possibly, as evidence or</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">an explanation for the first one. The speaker uses <i>but</i> in order to exclude these ways of</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="411" height="18" font="5">establishing the relevance of the second utterance. </text>
<text top="550" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Having looked at the two accounts briefly what is interesting to note is that there is a</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">striking similarity in the way the relevance-theoretic and the coherence-based approach</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">analyse the role of connectives in utterance interpretation. On both accounts connectives</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">have a constraining function. For coherence theorists connectives constrain the relational</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">propositions which express the coherence relations the hearer needs to recover in order</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">to intepret a discourse. For relevance theorists connectives constrain the interpretation</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">process by guiding the hearer towards the intended context and contextual effects. On</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">both accounts connectives play a facilitating role. However, the facilitating role of</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives is very well integrated in the relevance-theoretic account, following naturally</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">from the basic relevance-theoretic assumption that the speaker aims to ensure the</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">intended interpretation, making the hearer's job as easy as possible. On the other hand,</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">there is nothing in coherence theory that might provide any motivation for the existence</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">of such linguistic devices like discourse connectives. There is no psychological</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">explanation, in other words, why a speaker would try to indicate the right coherence</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="280" height="18" font="5">relation by choosing a connective. </text>
<text top="907" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">The most important difference between the relevance-theoretic and the coherence-based</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">approach to connectives is this. For coherence theorists, as we saw, connectives indicate</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">specific coherence relations (or sets of them). Now, coherence relations are expressed by</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">relational conceptual representations, like the one in (2). It follows that the meaning of</text>
<text top="1002" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives is representational. According to relevance theorists, on the other hand,</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="5">5</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives encode procedural meaning. According to Blakemore (1987:144), the theory</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="303" height="18" font="5">of linguistic semantics is non-unitary:</text>
<text top="265" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">On the one hand, there is the essentially conceptual theory that deals with</text>
<text top="289" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">the way in which elements of linguistic structure map onto concepts, i.e.</text>
<text top="313" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">onto constituents of propositional representations that undergo</text>
<text top="337" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">computations. On the other, there is the essentially procedural theory that</text>
<text top="360" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">deals with the way in which elements of linguistic structure map directly</text>
<text top="384" left="162" width="467" height="18" font="5">onto computations themselves, i.e. onto mental processes.</text>
<text top="432" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">The distinction between conceptual and procedural meaning, two different types of</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">linguistically encoded meaning, has been explored further in recent writings and lectures</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">by Deirdre Wilson and Dan Sperber (Wilson and Sperber 1993, Wilson 1990, 1991,</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">1994a,b). This distinction echoes earlier philosophical distinctions: Austin's distinction</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">between describing and indicating and Grice's distinction between saying and</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">conventionally implicating, but is designed to reflect a more fundamental cognitive</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">distinction between representation and computation. Roughly, words with conceptual</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">meaning contribute to the content of assertions and are analysed as encoding elements of</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">conceptual representations. Words with procedural meaning, on the other hand, encode</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">information about how these representations are to be used in inference, they tell you how</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">to 'take' these representations. So, in the case of connectives, the claim is that connectives</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">do not contribute to the proposition expressed by an utterance or to any other conceptual</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">representation the utterance may communicate; rather they point the hearer to the context</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">in which he is expected to process the utterance and the conclusions he should be drawing</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="60" height="18" font="5">from it.</text>
<text top="788" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Note that the recognition of two types of encoded meaning, conceptual and procedural,</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">fits very well with the relevance-theoretic view of communication, i.e. that</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">communication is an essentially inferential process. Linguistic decoding provides the</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">input for this process which surely involves the construction and manipulation of mental</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">representations. It is, therefore, to be expected that linguistic expressions may encode two</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">types of information: information which contributes directly to the construction of</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">conceptual representations, i.e. concepts, and information on how to manipulate these</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">representations, i.e. procedures. I will return to the conceptual-procedural distinction later.</text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="5">6</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="242" height="18" font="6"><b>3 What do connectives link?</b></text>
<text top="241" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Let me now turn to the issue I want to discuss in more detail in this paper. For coherence</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">theorists connectives link two discourse units, usually understood as two consecutive</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">clauses. (I will for now leave out the issue of global coherence). For relevance theorists,</text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">on the other hand, connectives link an utterance and a context or contextual effects. The</text>
<text top="336" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">context that a particular connective suggests may be verbal (for instance, the previous</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="258" height="18" font="5">utterance) but it doesn't have to.</text>
<text top="384" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">To evaluate these claims, we need to look at connectives introducing utterances which</text>
<text top="407" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">initiate discourse. When I say that the utterance introduced by a connective occurs</text>
<text top="431" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">discourse initially, I mean that there is no prior deliberate stimulus (say another utterance</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">or a gesture or a facial expression) intended to attract the speaker's attention and that</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">might cause a reaction on her part; so I am talking about the outset of an instance of</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">intentional communication. In Sperber &amp; Wilson's terms, there is no prior ostensive</text>
<text top="526" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">stimulus. Unfortunately for coherence theorists, most connectives seem to occur happily</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="148" height="18" font="5">discourse initially:</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(4)</text>
<text top="598" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="598" left="216" width="385" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is weighing a portion of muesli)</text>
<text top="621" left="216" width="394" height="18" font="5">Mary: I should pay some attention to my diet <i>too</i></text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="669" left="216" width="301" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is back from jogging)</text>
<text top="693" left="216" width="268" height="18" font="5">Mary:<i> So</i> you're trying to keep fit</text>
<text top="740" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="740" left="216" width="386" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter comes home from work at 3.00)</text>
<text top="764" left="216" width="343" height="18" font="5">Mary: <i>But</i> you had to work late shift today</text>
<text top="811" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="811" left="216" width="422" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is browsing through a PC magazine)</text>
<text top="835" left="216" width="472" height="18" font="5">Mary: We should be thinking of buying a computer <i>indeed</i></text>
<text top="883" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">e.</text>
<text top="883" left="216" width="300" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter has his leg in plaster)</text>
<text top="906" left="216" width="450" height="18" font="5">Mary: <i>Even</i> a small child would have seen that manhole</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Such examples suggest that the fact that <i>but</i>, <i>also</i>, <i>too</i>, etc. often connect two utterances</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">is in some sense accidental; what is crucial, say for <i>but</i>, is that it indicates that the</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">proposition it introduces dnies some other contextually manifest proposition, which may</text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="5">7</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">have been verbally expressed but does not have to. So, such examples provide good</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="474" height="18" font="5">support for the relevance-theoretic account of connectives.</text>
<text top="242" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">On the other hand, there is no way, as far as I can see, that the coherence-based</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">approach could account for these examples. Remember that what it says is that</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives connect two discourse units/segments — well, there is only one here. In fact</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">I've never seen such examples being discussed in the coherence-based literature and yet</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">these are the most common uses of connectives. Notice that in none of these contexts</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">does Peter intend Mary to react at his weighing muesli, returning from jogging, entering</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the house, etc. So, there is no way you could argue that Peter's sentence is simply omitted</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">here. You may perhaps try to argue that Mary's utterance in each case is the continuation</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">of another sentence she could have uttered but did not. But then, you need an account of</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">the conditions under which speakers may felicitously do this and I've never seen one in</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the coherence theoretic literature. Moreover, it will not be simple to provide one given the</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">fact, to which we are now turning, that certain connectives cannot occur discourse intially:</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(5)</text>
<text top="550" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="550" left="216" width="274" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is eating a burger)</text>
<text top="574" left="216" width="422" height="18" font="5">Mary: *Whereas your wife only eats salads and fruit</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="5" height="18" font="5"> </text>
<text top="622" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="622" left="216" width="334" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is cleaning the bathroom)</text>
<text top="645" left="216" width="340" height="18" font="5">Mary: *Moreover, you did the washing up</text>
<text top="693" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="693" left="216" width="377" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is checking the tires of the car)</text>
<text top="717" left="216" width="453" height="18" font="5">Mary: *However/*Nevertheless, you never check the oil</text>
<text top="764" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="764" left="216" width="358" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter comes in laden with parcels)</text>
<text top="788" left="216" width="380" height="18" font="5">Mary: *Therefore, you've spent all your money</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">The coherence-based approach can explain the infelicity of these examples: connectives</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">link two discourse units and here there is only one. Within the relevance-theoretic</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">account, however, which so far seems more promising, some explanation has to be given</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">for such examples. And this is what I will aim to do in the rest of this paper. The</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hypothesis I want to investigate is that whether a connective may occur discourse intially</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="417" height="18" font="5">depends on its syntactic and/or semantic properties.</text>
<text top="978" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">One of the things that is not usually discussed in accounts of discourse connectives is</text>
<text top="1002" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">their syntactic status. There is little doubt that the study of pragmatic markers in general</text>
<text top="1026" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">would profit significantly if we had a better understanding of their syntactic properties.</text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="10" height="18" font="5">8</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">With respect to the problem I am discussing here I will show that syntactic considerations</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="423" height="18" font="5">do provide us often with (at least) a partial solution. </text>
<text top="242" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Some of the connectives under discussion here are conjunctions, i.e. they can only occur</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">at the beginning of the clause they introduce: <i>but</i> is the prototypical example in this</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">category. Other connectives have more of an adverbial nature, for instance <i>after all</i>,</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>indeed</i>, <i>also</i>. Among the connectives that cannot occur discourse initially <i>whereas</i> is a</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">conjunction;  <i>therefore</i>,  <i>moreover</i>,  <i>however</i>,  <i>nevertheless</i>, on the other hand, are</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">adverbials, behaving a lot like parentheticals: they may occur utterance initially, finally</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="225" height="18" font="5">or in mid-sentence position:</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(6)</text>
<text top="432" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="432" left="216" width="418" height="18" font="5">The house is beautiful. However, it is too expensive</text>
<text top="455" left="405" width="226" height="18" font="5">It is too expensive, however</text>
<text top="479" left="405" width="231" height="18" font="5">It is, however, too expensive</text>
<text top="527" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="527" left="216" width="458" height="18" font="5">The house is not beautiful. Moreover, it is too expensive</text>
<text top="550" left="439" width="240" height="18" font="5">It is, moreover, too expensive</text>
<text top="574" left="439" width="235" height="18" font="5">It is too expensive, moreover</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Now, conjunctions may link two clauses paratactically, for instance the coordinator <i>and</i>;</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">or, they may be subordinators, i.e. subordinating the clause they introduce to another</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">clause, for instance <i>because</i>. The hypothesis I am going to investigate with respect to</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>whereas</i> is that it is a subordinating conjunction and as such cannot introduce a clause</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">discourse initially (where there is no main clause): its syntactic nature requires that the</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">sentence it introduces is embedded. This hypothesis finds some initial support in the fact</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">that clearly subordinating conjunctions like <i>because</i>,<i> after</i>, <i>in order to</i>, etc cannot occur</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="143" height="18" font="5">discourse intially:</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(7)</text>
<text top="836" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="836" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="5">(Context: Mary knows that Jane's boyfriend beats her and that she wants to</text>
<text top="859" left="216" width="337" height="18" font="5">split up; Jane walks in covered in bruises)</text>
<text top="883" left="216" width="360" height="18" font="5">Mary: *Because you threatened to leave him</text>
<text top="931" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="931" left="216" width="337" height="18" font="5">(Context:Jane walks in in her black dress)</text>
<text top="954" left="216" width="300" height="18" font="5">Mary: *In order to go to Peter's party</text>
<text top="1002" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="1002" left="216" width="592" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is sitting on the couch watching the news. Mary walks in)</text>
<text top="1026" left="216" width="281" height="18" font="5">Mary: *After you watched football</text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="800" width="10" height="18" font="5">9</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">This suggests the following way of determining whether <i>whereas</i> is a subordinator: In</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">the following dialogues consider whether the second utterance has to be understood as a</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">continuation/completion of the first one (i.e. no other interpretation is possible). A</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">positive answer suggests that the utterance under consideration is introduced by a</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="216" height="18" font="5">subordinating conjunction:</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(8)</text>
<text top="337" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="337" left="216" width="552" height="18" font="5">Peter: I'm not going to return any of the money I borrowed from you</text>
<text top="360" left="216" width="433" height="18" font="5">Mary: Because I don't want to live with you any more</text>
<text top="408" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="408" left="216" width="333" height="18" font="5">Peter: Lucy eventually found her suitcase</text>
<text top="432" left="216" width="372" height="18" font="5">Mary: After she spent two hours looking for it</text>
<text top="479" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="479" left="216" width="249" height="18" font="5">Peter: I'll be home this evening</text>
<text top="503" left="216" width="218" height="18" font="5">Mary: And I'll cook supper</text>
<text top="550" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="550" left="216" width="512" height="18" font="5">Peter: Sound investments like mine never endager the company</text>
<text top="574" left="216" width="405" height="18" font="5">Mary: Whereas unsound ones like mine always do</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">The utterances introduced by <i>because</i>, <i>after</i> and <i>whereas</i> have to be understood as</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">continuing the previous utterance; this suggests that <i>whereas</i> is a subordinator like</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>because</i> and <i>after</i>. By contrast, Mary's utterance in (8c) introduced by the coordinator <i>and</i></text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">may be understood either as completion of the previous utterance or as Mary's</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="181" height="18" font="5">independent assertion.</text>
<text top="740" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Also, there are syntactic tests to determine whether an utterance introduced by a certain</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connective is subordinate to the previous utterance or not (Warner 1979, Green 1976,</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Hoeksema and Napoli 1993). The most convincing of these tests is the one based on</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">binding considerations: If the second clause is syntactically subordinated to the first, then</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">a quantifier or quantified NP including <i>any</i> in the first clause can bind a pronoun in the</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="671" height="18" font="5">second clause (but not vice versa). In paratactic structures binding is not permitted.</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="5">(9)</text>
<text top="907" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="907" left="216" width="307" height="18" font="5">Anyone  would say that he  likes Mary</text>
<text top="917" left="279" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="917" left="428" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="931" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="931" left="216" width="454" height="18" font="5">Paul didn't hire any ballerina  because he liked her  looks</text>
<text top="941" left="447" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="941" left="619" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="954" left="216" width="288" height="18" font="5">*Everybody  left and he  went home</text>
<text top="964" left="313" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="964" left="407" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="978" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="978" left="216" width="553" height="18" font="5">Every ballerina  got pregnant whereas she  should have chosen not to</text>
<text top="988" left="339" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="988" left="551" width="3" height="11" font="1">i</text>
<text top="1026" left="108" width="579" height="18" font="5">On the basis of this test <i>whereas</i> is clearly a subordinating conjunction. </text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="5">10</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="654" height="18" font="5">Another test is this: negative NP preposing is not possible in subordinate clauses:</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(10)</text>
<text top="242" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="242" left="216" width="287" height="18" font="5">*I knew that not a bite had he eaten</text>
<text top="265" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="265" left="216" width="416" height="18" font="5">*We'll have to leave because not a bite has he eaten</text>
<text top="289" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="289" left="216" width="368" height="18" font="5">*John ate a lot whereas not a bite did Jane eat</text>
<text top="313" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="313" left="216" width="380" height="18" font="5">He was terribly hungry but not a bite did he eat</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="540" height="18" font="5">Again, the clause introduced by <i>whereas</i> comes out as subordinate.</text>
<text top="384" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Another test has to do with the possibility of a connective to cooccur with <i>and</i>: in a</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">conjunction 'P and Q' P and Q must be the same sort of constituents, i.e. main clauses. So,</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="498" height="18" font="5">if there is a connective in Q it must enforce paratactic linking.</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(11)</text>
<text top="479" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="479" left="216" width="401" height="18" font="5">*Mary resigned and because her boss insulted her</text>
<text top="503" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="503" left="216" width="415" height="18" font="5">*Mary would resign and unless her boss apologised</text>
<text top="527" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="527" left="216" width="409" height="18" font="5">*John ate a lot and whereas Mary didn't eat a thing</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="531" height="18" font="5">Again, <i>whereas</i> seems to pattern with subordinating conjunctions.</text>
<text top="598" left="123" width="392" height="18" font="5">Finally, embedded truncations are generally bad:</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="33" height="18" font="5">(12)</text>
<text top="645" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="645" left="216" width="209" height="18" font="5">? *I know that I wanna go</text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="669" left="216" width="418" height="18" font="5">? *I'd better get my coat because I wanna leave now</text>
<text top="693" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="693" left="216" width="399" height="18" font="5">Suzie got a hampster and/but I wanna get a rabbit</text>
<text top="717" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">d.</text>
<text top="717" left="216" width="434" height="18" font="5">? Mary wants to go skiing whereas I wanna go fishing</text>
<text top="764" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">The conclusion is that <i>whereas</i> is a subordinating conjunction. It is not surprising then</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">that an utterance introduced by <i>whereas</i> cannot occur discourse initially by itself: the</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="687" height="18" font="5">subordinating nature of <i>whereas</i> requires that the sentence it introduces is embedded.</text>
<text top="836" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Next, I will consider <i>therefore</i>. In contrast to <i>so</i>, <i>therefore</i> cannot occur discourse-</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">intially. According to Blakemore, the reason is the particular semantic properties of</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>therefore</i>: it marks the proposition it introduces as the conclusion of a proof — premises</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="239" height="18" font="5">are always explicit in a proof:</text>
<text top="954" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="5">a speaker can't be said to be proving something if he doesn't present the</text>
<text top="978" left="162" width="144" height="18" font="5">proof  (1992:139)</text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="790" width="20" height="18" font="5">11</text>
<text top="194" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Another consideration is this. In addition to its inferential use discussed by Blakemore</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="552" height="18" font="5">and exemplified in (13), <i>therefore</i> has a causal use as shown in (14):</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(13)</text>
<text top="265" left="162" width="352" height="18" font="5"> He is a philosopher; he is, therefore, brave </text>
<text top="289" left="162" width="148" height="18" font="5">(from Grice 1975)</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(14)</text>
<text top="337" left="162" width="446" height="18" font="5">Bill hit Mary and therefore she was covered in bruises  </text>
<text top="360" left="162" width="216" height="18" font="5">(from Kempson 1975:214)</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">When <i>therefore</i> expresses a causal connection, it is best paraphrased as 'as a result of this'</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">and it makes a contribution to the truth-conditions of the utterance. The fact that the</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">inferential <i>therefore</i> cannot occur discourse initially suggests that <i>therefore</i> retains its</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="455" height="18" font="5">anaphoric nature in its non-truth-conditional use as well.</text>
<text top="503" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Let's turn to <i>moreover</i> now. The first thing to notice here is that the situation with</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">respect to <i>moreover</i> is not clear: some of my informants accept it discourse initially,</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">others find it somewhat odd (they would have preferred <i>also</i> or <i>too</i>), and others find it</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">unacceptable (and this is the largest group). It would be nice if this could be reflected in</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="371" height="18" font="5">the explanation one offers for this connective.</text>
<text top="622" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">There are two basic differences between <i>also</i> and <i>too</i>, on the one hand, and <i>moreover</i>,</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">on the other. First, <i>moreover</i> can only be used for parallel confirmation, i.e. it indicates</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">that the proposition it introduces should be processed in parallel with some other</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">contextually manifest assumption leading to the confirmation of the same conclusion; <i>also</i></text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">and <i>too</i>, by contrast can be used in a variety of other ways as well, as Blass (1990: 134-</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">156) has shown in detail. More important for my purposes is that <i>moreover</i> does not</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="630" height="18" font="5">interact with focus the way <i>too</i> and <i>also</i> do. Compare the following examples:</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(15)</text>
<text top="812" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">a.</text>
<text top="812" left="216" width="291" height="18" font="5">PETER also/*moreover drives a car</text>
<text top="836" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="5">b.</text>
<text top="836" left="216" width="293" height="18" font="5">Peter also/*moreover DRIVES a car</text>
<text top="859" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="5">c.</text>
<text top="859" left="216" width="286" height="18" font="5">Peter drives a CAR also/*moreover</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">As Blakemore has already discussed in her book, the interaction of <i>also</i> with focus</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">simplifies the hearer's task of finding the contextually manifest assumption which the</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hearer is intended to process in parallel with the proposition introduced by <i>also</i>. The idea,</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">which originates from Sperber and Wilson's work on focus (Wilson and Sperber 1979,</text>
<text top="1002" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Sperber and WIlson 1986), is this: the stress on 'Peter' in (15a) indicates that the</text>
<text top="1026" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">proposition in (15a) achieves relevance by providing a value for the variable 'someone'</text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="5">12</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">in the proposition in (16) (in addition to being an entailment, (16) is one of the</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="523" height="18" font="5">background propositions against which (15a) is to be processed):</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(16)</text>
<text top="265" left="162" width="173" height="18" font="5">Someone drives a car</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>Also</i> indicates to the hearer that the proposition it accompanies should be processed in</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">parallel with some other proposition; the interaction of <i>also</i> and focus constrains the</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hearer's search by instructing him to process the proposition in (15a) in parallel with a</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">proposition similar to (16) , in which, however, the value for the variable 'someone' is</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="140" height="18" font="5">other than 'Peter'.</text>
<text top="432" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Parallel processing is a relatively difficult inferential task to perform: in any given</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">instance there will be a variety of assumptions that could be processed in parallel with the</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">one in which <i>also</i> or <i>moreover</i> occurs yielding similar conclusions. Interaction of say <i>also</i></text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">with focus simplifies this task by suggesting what the proposition the hearer is searching</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">for looks like. Where there is no such interaction, as in the case of <i>moreover</i>, the hearer's</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="653" height="18" font="5">task seems to be far too difficult, and therefore a previous utterance is necessary.</text>
<text top="574" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Unfortunately, this is not a full explanation given examples like (17) where <i>also</i> and <i>too</i></text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">are used parenthetically, i.e. without interacting with focus, at the beginning of a</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="82" height="18" font="5">discourse:</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="5">(17)</text>
<text top="669" left="162" width="373" height="18" font="5">(Context: Peter is having only salad for lunch)</text>
<text top="693" left="162" width="472" height="18" font="5">Mary: You went jogging this morning, <i>also</i>/<i>too</i>/?<i>moreover</i></text>
<text top="740" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Another consideration to take into account here is that <i>moreover</i> is somewhat archaic,</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">and given that there are at least two other connectives which can be used for parallel</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">confirmation and are stylistically unmarked, the speaker will, everything else being equal,</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">prefer to use one of those. A similar (partial) explanation hinging on stylistic</text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">considerations can be given for the fact that <i>however</i> and<i> nevertheless</i> cannot occur</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="551" height="18" font="5">discourse initially in contrast to <i>but</i> in the denial of expectation use. </text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="337" height="18" font="6"><b>4 Connectives and procedural meaning</b></text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">I have proposed an explanation for why <i>whereas</i> and <i>therefore</i> cannot occur discourse</text>
<text top="1001" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">initially and we have the beginnings of an account for the similar behaviour of <i>moreover,</i></text>
<text top="1025" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>however</i> and <i>nevertheless</i>. On the basis of the evidence we have got so far, it is clear that</text>
</page>
<page number="13" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="790" width="20" height="18" font="5">13</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the relevance-theoretic approach to connectives is more adequate than the coherence-</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">based approach, on which it is impossible to explain in any principled way the fact that</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="387" height="18" font="5">most connectives may occur discourse initially. </text>
<text top="265" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">In fact, there is a slightly different way of constructing the relevance-theoretic answer</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">to the question 'what do connectives link?' which suggests that the fact that certain</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives may not occur discourse initially, although interesting and worth of an</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">explanation in its own right, does not really bear on the essence of the relevance-theoretic</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="190" height="18" font="5">account of connectives.</text>
<text top="384" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">Remember that the claim which distinguishes the relevance-theoretic account from the</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">coherence-based account is that connectives encode procedural meaning. In Deirdre</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Wilson's lectures on Semantic Theory since around 1990 and in many works on</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">connectives since then, for instance Blass's book <i>Relevance Relations in Discourse</i>, and</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">Blakemore's recent book (1992), and definitely since Wilson and Sperber (1993), it has</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">been stressed that the essential property of connectives is to indicate the inferential</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">process the hearer is expected to go through. Taking this into account, connectives should</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">be seen as linking not so much an utterance and a context but rather an utterance and a</text>
<text top="574" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">specific inferential process: very simply put, <i>but</i> is linked to the inferential process of</text>
<text top="598" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">contradicting and eliminating an assumption, <i>so</i> is linked to the inferential process of</text>
<text top="622" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">drawing a conclusion, <i>whereas</i> is linked to the inferential process of parallel processing</text>
<text top="645" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">leading to contrasting conclusions, <i>moreover</i> is linked to the inferential process of parallel</text>
<text top="669" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">processing leading to the confirmation of the same conclusion, etc. This way of answering</text>
<text top="693" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the question addressed in this paper shows that the fact that certain connectives cannot</text>
<text top="717" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">occur discourse initially is in some sense arbitrary (as the syntactically motivated</text>
<text top="740" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">explanations also suggest), and in any case of no consequence for the relevance-theoretic</text>
<text top="764" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">approach to connectives. What is essential in this approach is that connectives constrain</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the inferential phase of communication by pointing to the particular inferential process</text>
<text top="812" left="108" width="328" height="18" font="5">that the hearer is intended to go through.</text>
<text top="836" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="5">There is further motivation for claiming that connectives link an utterance with the</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">inferential process the hearer is expected to go through: it is in general more in line with</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">the way procedural encoding is understood. Wilson and Sperber (1993) show that the</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">distinction between conceptual and procedural meaning is a fundamental distinction in</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">linguistic semantics which cross-cuts the distinction between the implicitly and the</text>
<text top="954" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">explicitly communicated content of an utterance. Connectives are only one of the various</text>
<text top="978" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">linguistic devices which encode procedural meaning. Pronouns (<i>I</i>,  <i>he</i>, etc.), mood</text>
<text top="1002" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">indicators (interrogative and imperative mood), and attitudinal and illocutionary particles</text>
<text top="1026" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">(<i>huh</i>,<i> eh</i>, etc.) may also be analysed in procedural terms. Whereas connectives are seen</text>
</page>
<page number="14" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="102" height="15" font="7"><i>Villy Rouchota</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="20" height="18" font="5">14</text>
<text top="194" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">as constraints on the implicatures of an utterance, pronouns are argued to be constraints</text>
<text top="218" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">on the proposition expressed by an utterance, and mood indicators, attitudinal and</text>
<text top="242" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">illocutionary particles are best analysed as constraints on the higher level explicatures of</text>
<text top="265" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">an utterance. Neither in the case of pronouns nor in the case of atitude and illocutionary</text>
<text top="289" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">force indicating devices does it make sense to argue that they guide the hearer towards a</text>
<text top="313" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">particular set of contextual assumptions and effects. A pronoun like<i> he</i> guides the search</text>
<text top="337" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="5">for the intended referent by narrowing down the class of candidates that the hearer need</text>
<text top="360" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">consider: he need only consider males. A mood indicator guides the search for the</text>
<text top="384" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">intended interpretation by narrowing down the propositional attitude descriptions the</text>
<text top="408" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">hearer need consider. Moreover, not all connectives can be analysed as constraints on the</text>
<text top="432" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">implicatures of an utterance. For instance, <i>therefore</i> when it expresses a causal connection</text>
<text top="455" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="5">contributes to the proposition expressed by an utterance. If a procedural account of the</text>
<text top="479" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">causal  <i>therefore</i> is viable, then it could not be claimed that it indicates the intended</text>
<text top="503" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">context and contextual effects of an utterance; it is more plausible to argue that in this use</text>
<text top="527" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="5">too <i>therefore</i> links the utterance to the inferential process of reaching a conclusion, only</text>
<text top="550" left="108" width="329" height="18" font="5">this time on the basis of causal evidence.</text>
<text top="646" left="108" width="94" height="18" font="6"><b>References</b></text>
<text top="692" left="108" width="538" height="15" font="0">Blakemore, D. (1987). <i>Semantic Constraints on Relevance</i>. Blackwell: Oxford.</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Blakemore, D. (1989). Denial and contrast: a relevance theoretic analysis of <i>but</i>. <i>Linguistics and</i></text>
<text top="732" left="123" width="152" height="15" font="7"><i>Philosophy</i> 12. 15-37.</text>
<text top="751" left="108" width="478" height="15" font="0">Blakemore, D. (1992). <i>Understanding Utterances</i>. Blackwell: Oxford.</text>
<text top="771" left="108" width="478" height="15" font="0">Blass, R. (1990). <i>Relevance Relations in Discourse</i>. CUP: Cambridge.</text>
<text top="791" left="108" width="612" height="15" font="0">Fraser, B. (1990). An approach to discourse markers. <i>Journal of Pragmatics</i> 14. 383-395.</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="613" height="15" font="0">Green, G. (1976). Main clause phenomena in subordinate clauses. <i>Language</i> 52. 382-397.</text>
<text top="831" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Grice, P. (1975). Logic and Conversation. In Grice (1989) <i>Studies in the Way of Words</i>. Harvard</text>
<text top="850" left="123" width="242" height="15" font="0">University Press: Cambridge, Mass.</text>
<text top="870" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Hoeksema, J. and D.J. Napoli (1993). Paratactic and subordinative <i>so</i>. <i>Journal of Linguistics</i> 29. 291-314.</text>
<text top="890" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Hovy, E. and Maier, E. (1994). Parsimonious or profligate: how many and which discourse structure</text>
<text top="910" left="123" width="95" height="15" font="0">relations? Ms.</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="617" height="15" font="0">Kempson, R. (1975). <i>Presupposition and the Delimitation of Semantics</i>. CUP: Cambridge.</text>
<text top="949" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Knott, A. and Dale, R. (1994). Using linguistic phenomena to motivate a set of coherence relations.</text>
<text top="969" left="123" width="215" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse Processes</i> 18. 35-62.</text>
<text top="989" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Mann, W. and Thompson, S. (1986). Relational propositions in discourse. <i>Discourse Processes</i> 9. 57-90.</text>
<text top="1009" left="108" width="701" height="15" font="0">Sanders, T., Spooren, W. and L. Noordman (1993). Coherence relations in a cognitive theory of discourse</text>
<text top="1029" left="123" width="345" height="15" font="0">representation. <i>Cognitive Linguistics</i> 4(2). 93-133.</text>
</page>
<page number="15" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="442" width="288" height="15" font="7"><i>Discourse connectives: what do they link?</i></text>
<text top="132" left="790" width="20" height="18" font="5">15</text>
<text top="193" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Sperber, D. and D. Wilson (1986). <i>Relevance: Communication and Cognition</i>. Blackwell: Oxford. (second</text>
<text top="213" left="123" width="100" height="15" font="0">edition, 1995).</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="592" height="15" font="0">Warner, R. (1979). <i>Discourse Connectives in English</i>. PhD, The Ohio State University.</text>
<text top="253" left="108" width="398" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. (1990). Semantic Theory. Lecture Notes. UCL.</text>
<text top="273" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. (1991) Varieties of non-truth-conditional meaning. Talk delivered at the LAGB 1991 spring</text>
<text top="292" left="123" width="58" height="15" font="0">meeting.</text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="681" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. (1994a). Discourse Markers: social and cognitive approaches. <i>Tokyo Lectures</i>. UCL, Ms.</text>
<text top="332" left="108" width="447" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. (1994b). Lectures on Coherence. Lecture Notes. UCL.</text>
<text top="352" left="108" width="702" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. and D. Sperber (1979). Ordered entailments: an alternative to presuppositional theories. In C.K.</text>
<text top="372" left="123" width="656" height="15" font="0">Oh and D. Dineen (eds) <i>Syntax and Semantics</i> 11,<i> Presuppositions</i>. New York: Academic Press.</text>
<text top="391" left="108" width="565" height="15" font="0">Wilson, D. and D. Sperber (1993). Linguistic form and relevance. <i>Lingua</i> 90. 1-25.</text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
