<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pdf2xml SYSTEM "pdf2xml.dtd">

<pdf2xml producer="poppler" version="0.86.1">
<page number="1" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="0" size="12" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="1" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="2" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="3" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="4" size="36" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="5" size="21" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
	<fontspec id="6" size="20" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="1007" left="123" width="6" height="11" font="0">*</text>
<text top="1012" left="129" width="680" height="16" font="1">We would like to thank François Récanati, Robyn Carston, Eric Lormand, Peter Carruthers, Gloria</text>
<text top="1024" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Origgi, Anna Papafragou and Richard Breheny for valuable discussions on the topic of this paper and</text>
<text top="1044" left="108" width="208" height="16" font="1">comments on earlier versions.</text>
<text top="133" left="108" width="367" height="18" font="2"><i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics</i> 9 (1997)</text>
<text top="185" left="108" width="702" height="32" font="4"><i><b>The mapping between the mental and the public</b></i></text>
<text top="227" left="108" width="108" height="32" font="4"><i><b>lexicon</b></i></text>
<text top="222" left="216" width="11" height="19" font="5"><i><b>*</b></i></text>
<text top="312" left="108" width="336" height="18" font="3">DAN SPERBER &amp; DEIRDRE WILSON</text>
<text top="409" left="143" width="76" height="18" font="6"><b>Abstract</b></text>
<text top="456" left="143" width="631" height="16" font="1">This paper considers the possible relations between mental concepts and public words, and</text>
<text top="476" left="143" width="631" height="16" font="1">argues that there are many more concepts in our minds than words in the language we speak.</text>
<text top="497" left="143" width="631" height="16" font="1">These concepts may be both stable and communicable without being encoded in words. The</text>
<text top="517" left="143" width="631" height="16" font="1">concept communicated by use of a word on a given occasion may go well beyond the concept</text>
<text top="537" left="143" width="632" height="16" font="1">encoded. We show how these facts provide evidence against a code theory of communication</text>
<text top="558" left="143" width="632" height="16" font="1">and in favour of an inferential theory (relevance theory) whose implications for lexical</text>
<text top="578" left="143" width="322" height="16" font="1">semantics and pragmatics are briefly explored.</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="126" height="18" font="6"><b>1 Introduction</b></text>
<text top="691" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">There are words in the language we speak and concepts in our minds. For present</text>
<text top="715" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">purposes, we can use a relatively common-sense, unsophisticated notion of a linguistic</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">word. A bit more needs to be said, now and later, about what we mean by a concept. We</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">assume that mental representations have a structure not wholly unlike that of a sentence,</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and combine elements from a mental repertoire not wholly unlike a lexicon. These</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">elements are mental concepts: so to speak, 'words of mentalese'. Mental concepts are</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relatively stable and distinct structures in the mind, comparable to entries in an</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">encyclopaedia or to permanent files in a data-base. Their occurrence in a mental</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">representation may determine matching causal and formal (semantic or logical)</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relationships. On the one hand, there are relationships between the mind and the world.</text>
<text top="930" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">The activation of a concept may play a major role in causal interactions between the</text>
</page>
<page number="2" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
	<fontspec id="7" size="17" family="Times" color="#000000"/>
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="9" height="16" font="1">2</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">organism and external objects that fall under that concept. On the other hand, there are</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">relationships among representations within the mind. The occurrence of a concept in a</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">mental representation may play a causal role in the derivation of further representations,</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="496" height="18" font="3">and may also contribute to the justification of this derivation.</text>
<text top="333" left="108" width="222" height="18" font="6"><b>2 Three types of mapping</b></text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">What kind of mapping is there (if any) between mental concepts and public words? One</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">extreme view is that natural languages such as English or Swahili are the sole medium</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">of thought. In this case, obviously, there is a genuine one-to-one correspondence between</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">public words and mental concepts. An opposite extreme view is that there are no such</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">things as individual mental concepts at all, and therefore no conceptual counterparts to</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">public words. We will ignore these extreme views. We assume that there are mental</text>
<text top="524" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concepts, and that they are not just internalisations of public words, so that the kind and</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">degree of correspondence between concepts and words is a genuine and interesting</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="127" height="18" font="3">empirical issue.</text>
<text top="596" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">In principle, the mapping between mental concepts and public words might be</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">exhaustive (so that every concept corresponds to a word and conversely), or partial. If</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it is partial, this may be because some concepts lack a corresponding word, because some</text>
<text top="667" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">words lack a corresponding concept, or both. The mapping between words and concepts</text>
<text top="691" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">may be one-to-one, one-to-many, many-to-one, or a mixture of these. However, the idea</text>
<text top="715" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">that there is an exhaustive, one-to-one mapping between concepts and words is quite</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="100" height="18" font="3">implausible.</text>
<text top="763" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Some words (for instance the third person pronoun 'it') are more like placeholders and</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">do not encode concepts at all. Many words seem to encode not a full-fledged concept but</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">what might be called a pro-concept (for example 'my', 'have', 'near', 'long' — while each</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of these examples may be contentious, the existence of the general category should not</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">be). Unlike pronouns, these words have some conceptual content. As with pronouns,</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">their semantic contribution <i>must</i> be contextually specified for the associated utterance</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to have a truth-value. For instance, 'this is my book' may be true if 'my book' is</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">interpreted as meaning <i>the book I am thinking of</i>, and false if it means <i>the book I wrote</i></text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">(and since there are indefinitely many possible interpretations, finding the right one</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">involves more than merely disambiguation). Similarly, whether 'the school is near the</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">house' is true or false depends on a contextually specified criterion or scale; and so on.</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">We believe that pro-concepts are quite common, but the argument of this chapter does</text>
</page>
<page number="3" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="801" width="9" height="16" font="1">3</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">not depend on that assumption (or even on the existence of pro-concepts). What we will</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">argue is that, quite commonly, all words behave <i>as if</i> they encoded pro-concepts: that is,</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">whether or not a word encodes a full concept, the concept it is used to convey in a given</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="360" height="18" font="3">utterance has to be contextually worked out.</text>
<text top="305" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Some concepts have no corresponding word, and can be encoded only by a phrase. For</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">instance, it is arguable that most of us have a non-lexicalised concept of <i>uncle-or-aunt</i>.</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">We have many beliefs and expectations about uncles-or-aunts (i.e. siblings of parents,</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">and, by extension, their spouses). It makes sense to assume that these beliefs and</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">expectations are mentally stored together in a non-lexicalised mental concept, which has</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the lexicalised concepts of <i>uncle</i> and <i>aunt</i> as sub-categories. Similarly, people who do</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">not have the word 'sibling' in their public lexicon (or speakers of French, where no such</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">word exists) may nonetheless have the concept of <i>sibling</i> characterised as child of same</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">parents, and object of many beliefs and expectations, a concept which has <i>brother</i> and</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>sister</i> as sub-categories. So it seems plausible that not all words map onto concepts, nor</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="198" height="18" font="3">all concepts onto words.</text>
<text top="568" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">The phenomenon of polysemy is worth considering here. Suppose Mary says to Peter:</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(1)</text>
<text top="616" left="162" width="136" height="18" font="3">Open the bottle. </text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">In most situations, she would be understood as asking him to uncork or uncap the bottle.</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">One way of accounting for this would be to suggest that the general meaning of the verb</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">'open' gets specified by the properties of its direct object: thus, opening a corked bottle</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">means uncorking it, and so on. However, this cannot be the whole story. Uncorking a</text>
<text top="760" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">bottle may be the standard way of opening it, but another way is to saw off the bottom,</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and on some occasion, this might be what Mary was asking Peter to do. Or suppose Mary</text>
<text top="808" left="108" width="108" height="18" font="3">says to Peter:</text>
<text top="856" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(2)</text>
<text top="856" left="162" width="231" height="18" font="3">Open the washing machine. </text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">In most situations, she will probably be asking him to open the lid of the machine.</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">However, if Peter is a plumber, she might be asking him to unscrew the back; in other</text>
<text top="951" left="108" width="615" height="18" font="3">situations, she might be asking him to blow the machine open, or whatever.</text>
<text top="975" left="123" width="688" height="18" font="3">The general point of these examples is that a word like 'open' can be used to convey</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">indefinitely many concepts. It is impossible for all of these to be listed in the lexicon. Nor</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">can they be generated at a purely linguistic level by taking the linguistic context, and in</text>
</page>
<page number="4" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="9" height="16" font="1">4</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">particular the direct object, into account. It seems reasonable to conclude that a word like</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">'open' is often used to convey a concept that is encoded neither by the word itself nor by</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the verb phrase 'open X'. (For discussion of similar examples from alternative</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">perspectives, see Caramazza &amp; Grober 1976; Lyons 1977; Searle 1980; 1983; Lehrer</text>
<text top="285" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">1990; Pinkal 1995; Pustejovsky 1995; Fodor &amp; Lepore 1996; Pustejovsky &amp; Boguraev</text>
<text top="309" left="108" width="53" height="18" font="3">1996.)</text>
<text top="332" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">So far, we have argued that there are words which do not encode concepts and</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concepts which are not encoded by words. More trivially, the existence of synonyms</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(e.g. 'snake' and 'serpent') shows that several words may correspond to a single concept,</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">and the existence of homonyms (e.g. 'cat' or 'bank') shows that several concepts may</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">correspond to a single word. So the mapping between concepts and words is neither</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="218" height="18" font="3">exhaustive nor one-to-one.</text>
<text top="476" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Although the mapping between words and concepts is imperfect, it is not haphazard.</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="675" height="18" font="3">Here are three contrasting claims about what this imperfect mapping might be like:</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">(3) Nearly all individual concepts are lexicalised, but many words encode complex</text>
<text top="572" left="143" width="666" height="18" font="3">conceptual structures rather than individual concepts. So there are fewer concepts</text>
<text top="596" left="143" width="666" height="18" font="3">than words, and the mapping is partial mostly because many words do not map onto</text>
<text top="620" left="143" width="164" height="18" font="3">individual concepts.</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(4) Genuine synonyms, genuine homonyms, non-lexicalised concepts and words that</text>
<text top="692" left="143" width="667" height="18" font="3">do not encode concepts are all relatively rare, so there is roughly a one-to-one</text>
<text top="716" left="143" width="315" height="18" font="3">mapping between words and concepts.</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(5) The mapping is partial, and the main reason for this is that only a fraction of the</text>
<text top="787" left="143" width="667" height="18" font="3">conceptual repertoire is lexicalised. Most mental concepts do not map onto words.</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">In <i>The Language of Thought</i> (1975), Jerry Fodor famously argued against (3) and in</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">favour of (4). According to the version of claim (3) he criticised, words correspond in</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the mind to definitions couched in terms of a relatively compact repertoire of primitive</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concepts: for example, the word 'bachelor' might have as its conceptual counterpart the</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">complex mental expression <i>unmarried man</i>; the word 'kill' might have as its conceptual</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">counterpart the complex mental expression <i>cause to die</i>, and so on. Many words —</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">perhaps most — would be abbreviations for complex conceptual expressions, rather than</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">encoding individual concepts. Against this view, Fodor argued that most words have no</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">plausible definitions and must therefore correspond to mental primitives. There are</text>
</page>
<page number="5" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="801" width="9" height="16" font="1">5</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">psycholinguistic reasons for thinking that even a word like 'bachelor', which seems to</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">have a definition, is best treated as encoding a single concept <i>bachelor</i>, which would</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">itself be a (mental rather than public) abbreviation for a complex mental expression</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="150" height="18" font="3">(Fodor 1975:152).</text>
<text top="305" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">As Fodor points out, verbal comprehension is fast, and unaffected by the alleged</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">semantic complexity of lexical items. 'Kill' is no harder to process than 'die', and</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">'bachelor' is no harder than 'unmarried', even though it might be argued that the meaning</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of 'die' is included in the meaning of 'kill', and the meaning of 'unmarried' is included in</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">meaning of 'bachelor'. All this suggests to Fodor that the structure of mental messages</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">is very close to that of the public sentences standardly used to communicate them. 'It may</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">be that the resources of the inner code are rather directly represented in the resources we</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="346" height="18" font="3">use for communication' (Fodor 1975:156).</text>
<text top="496" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Fodor's argument against (3), combined with a rather traditional view of linguistic</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">communication, seems to weigh in favour of (4). Fodor does, as he says himself, view</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="233" height="18" font="3">language 'the good old way':</text>
<text top="592" left="143" width="633" height="18" font="3">A speaker is, above all, someone with something he intends to communicate.</text>
<text top="616" left="143" width="633" height="18" font="3">For want of a better term, I shall call what he has in mind a message. If he is to</text>
<text top="640" left="143" width="633" height="18" font="3">communicate by using a language, his problem is to construct a wave form</text>
<text top="664" left="143" width="633" height="18" font="3">which is a token of the (or a) type standardly used for expressing that message</text>
<text top="688" left="143" width="290" height="18" font="3">in that language (Fodor 1975: 106).</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">Here, Fodor is adopting an updated version of what we have called the code theory of</text>
<text top="760" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">verbal communication (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1986/1995). The classical code theory was</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="298" height="18" font="3">based on the following assumptions:</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">(6) For every thought that can be linguistically communicated, there is a sentence</text>
<text top="856" left="143" width="198" height="18" font="3">identical to it in content.</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">(7) The communication of a thought is achieved by uttering a sentence identical to it in</text>
<text top="927" left="143" width="65" height="18" font="3">content.</text>
<text top="975" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Assumption (7) is clearly too strong. Sentences with pronouns are obvious counter-</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">examples: they are used to communicate different thoughts on different occasions, and</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="421" height="18" font="3">are not identical in content to any of these thoughts.</text>
</page>
<page number="6" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="9" height="16" font="1">6</text>
<text top="189" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">The updated code theory accepts (6), but rejects (7) in favour of the weaker assumption</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="29" height="18" font="3">(8):</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">(8) The communication of any thought <i>can be</i> achieved by uttering a sentence identical</text>
<text top="285" left="143" width="123" height="18" font="3">to it in content.</text>
<text top="332" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">For the classical code theory, the only way to communicate thoughts is to encode them.</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">For the updated code theory, this is still the basic way, but there are also inferential short-</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">cuts. The updated theory admits that the basic coding-decoding process can be speeded</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">up, supplemented, or even by-passed by use of contextually informed inferential</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">routines. Though full encoding is possible, the theory goes, it is often unnecessary. By</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">exploiting shared contextual information and inferential abilities, communication can</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">succeed even when a name or description is replaced by a pronoun, a phrase is ellipsed,</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="578" height="18" font="3">or a whole thought is indirectly suggested rather than directly encoded.</text>
<text top="524" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Still, on both classical and updated versions of the code theory, the semantic resources</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of a language must be rich enough to encode all communicable thoughts. Every concept</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that can be communicated must be linguistically encodable. There may be a few non-</text>
<text top="596" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">lexicalised concepts (e.g. <i>uncle-or-aunt</i>) which are encodable only by a phrase; but it is</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">reasonable to think that, in general, the recurrent use of a concept in communication</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">would favour the introduction and stabilisation of a corresponding word in the public</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="79" height="18" font="3">language.</text>
<text top="692" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Because Fodor uncritically accepts the code theory of communication, and because he</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">does not even consider claim (5), let alone argue against it, his excellent arguments</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">against claim (3) do not unequivocally point to the conclusion in (4). Claim (5) might</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">still be correct. We want to argue that it is, and hence that most mental concepts do not</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="137" height="18" font="3">map onto words.</text>
<text top="811" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">There are two interpretations of claim (5) on which it would be trivially true, or at least</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">easily acceptable. First, it is clear that the number of perceptual stimuli that humans can</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">discriminate is vastly greater than the number of words available to name them: for</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">instance, it has been claimed that we can discriminate anything up to millions of colours,</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">while English has a colour vocabulary of a few hundred non-synonymous terms, only</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a dozen of which are in frequent use (Hardin 1988:182-3). If we have a concept for every</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">colour that we can discriminate (or even for every colour that we have had the</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">opportunity to discriminate), it is clear that we have many more concepts than words.</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">However, a discrimination is not the same as a conceptualisation of the items</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">discriminated. Someone may discriminate two shades of vermilion, and even think, <i>here</i></text>
</page>
<page number="7" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="801" width="9" height="16" font="1">7</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>are two shades of vermilion</i>, without forming a distinct mental structure, let alone a</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="327" height="18" font="3">stable one, for each of these two shades.</text>
<text top="257" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">A concept, as we understand the term, is an enduring elementary mental structure,</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">which is capable of playing different discriminatory or inferential roles on different</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">occasions in an individual's mental life. We are not considering ephemeral</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">representations of particulars (e.g. an individual tree, an individual person, a particular</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">taste), attended to for a brief moment and then forgotten. Nor are we considering</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">complex conceptual structures, built from more elementary mental concepts, which</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">correspond to phrases rather than words, and are not stored in long-term memory. Even</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">so, it might be argued that people do form many idiosyncratic, non-lexicalised concepts</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">on the basis of private and unshareable experience. For example, you may have a proper</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concept of a certain kind of pain, or a certain kind of smell, which allows you to</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">recognise new occurrences, and draw inferences on the basis of this recognition, even</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">though you cannot linguistically express this concept, or bring others to grasp and share</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it. More generally, it is arguable that each of us has ineffable concepts — perhaps a great</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="503" height="18" font="3">many of them. This would again make claim (5) trivially true.</text>
<text top="592" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">We will return to this point later, and argue that effability is a matter of degree. For the</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">time being, we will restrict ourselves to effable concepts: concepts that can be part of the</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">content of a communicable thought. We want to argue that, even on this interpretation,</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">claim (5) is true: there are a great many <i>stable</i> and<i> effable</i> mental concepts that do not</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="137" height="18" font="3">map onto words.</text>
<text top="760" left="108" width="223" height="18" font="6"><b>3 Inference and relevance</b></text>
<text top="807" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">The alternative to a code theory of verbal communication is an inferential theory; the</text>
<text top="831" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">basic idea for this comes from the work of Paul Grice (1989). We have developed such</text>
<text top="855" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a theory in detail in our book <i>Relevance: Communication and cognition</i> (1986/1995).</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">According to the inferential theory, all a communicator has to do in order to convey a</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">thought is to give her audience appropriate evidence of her intention to convey it. More</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">generally, a mental state may be revealed by a behaviour (or by the trace a behaviour</text>
<text top="951" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">leaves in the environment). Behaviour capable of revealing the content of a mental state</text>
<text top="975" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">may also succeed in <i>communicating</i> this content to an audience. For this to happen, it</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">must be used ostensively: that is, it must be displayed so as to make manifest an intention</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="310" height="18" font="3">to inform the audience of this content.</text>
</page>
<page number="8" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="9" height="16" font="1">8</text>
<text top="189" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Peter asks Mary if she wants to go to the cinema. Mary half-closes her eyes and mimes</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a yawn. This is a piece of ostensive behaviour. Peter recognises it as such and infers,</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">non-demonstratively, that Mary is tired, that she wants to rest, and that she therefore does</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">not want to go to the cinema. Mary has communicated a refusal to go to the cinema, and</text>
<text top="285" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">a reason for this refusal, by giving Peter some evidence of her thoughts. The evidence</text>
<text top="309" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">was her mimed yawning, which she could expect to activate in Peter's mind the idea of</text>
<text top="332" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">her being tired. The ostensive nature of her behaviour could be expected to suggest to</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Peter that she <i>intended</i> to activate this idea in his mind. Mary thought that the idea</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">activated, and the manifestly intentional nature of its activation, would act as the starting</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">point for an inferential process that would lead to the discovery of her meaning. She</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">might have achieved roughly the same effect by saying 'I'm tired.' This would also have</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">automatically activated the idea of her being tired (this time by linguistic decoding). It</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">would have done so in a manifestly intentional way, thus providing Peter with strong</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="268" height="18" font="3">evidence of Mary's full meaning.</text>
<text top="524" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">In general, inferential communication involves a communicator ostensively engaging</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">in some behaviour (e.g. a piece of miming or the production of a coded signal) likely to</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">activate in the addressee (via recognition or decoding) some specific conceptual structure</text>
<text top="596" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">or idea. The addressee takes this deliberately induced effect, together with contextual</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">information, as the starting point for an inferential process which should lead to the</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">discovery of the message (in the sense of proposition plus propositional attitude) that the</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="282" height="18" font="3">communicator intended to convey.</text>
<text top="692" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">The idea activated and the message inferred are normally very different. The idea is</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">merely a trigger for discovery of the message. Often, the triggering idea is a fragment,</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">or an incomplete schematic version, of the message to be communicated. The inferential</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="606" height="18" font="3">process then consists in complementing or fleshing out the triggering idea.</text>
<text top="787" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">It is possible, at least in principle, for the idea activated by the communicator's</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">behaviour to consist of a proposition and a propositional attitude (i.e. a full thought)</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">which is just the message she intended to convey. In this limiting case, the inferential</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">process will simply amount to realising that this is all the communicator meant. The</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">classical code theory treats this limiting case as the only one. Every act of</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">communication is seen as involving the production of a coded signal (e.g. a token of a</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">sentence) which encodes exactly the intended message. No inferential process is needed.</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">The sentence meaning (or, more generally, the signal meaning) is supposed to be</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">identical to the speaker's meaning. The updated code theory treats this limiting case as</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the basic and paradigmatic one. Hearers should assume by default that the sentence</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">meaning is the speaker's message, but be prepared to revise this assumption on the basis</text>
</page>
<page number="9" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="801" width="9" height="16" font="1">9</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of linguistic evidence (the sentence does not encode a full message) or contextual</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="653" height="18" font="3">evidence (the speaker could not plausibly have meant what the sentence means).</text>
<text top="257" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Since the classical code theory is patently wrong, the updated code theory might seem</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">more attractive. However, the classical theory had the advantage of offering a simple,</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">powerful and self-contained account of how communication is possible at all. The</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">updated theory loses this advantage by invoking an inferential mechanism to explain how</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">more can be communicated than is actually encoded. The updated theory offers two</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">distinct mechanisms — coding-decoding and inference — which may be singly or jointly</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">invoked to explain how a given message is communicated. Why should the first of these</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">be fundamental and necessary to human linguistic communication, while the second is</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">peripheral and dispensable? The classical theory, which treats coding-decoding as the</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>only</i> explanation of communication, entails as a core theoretical claim that every</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicable message is fully encodable. In the updated theory, this is a contingent</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="606" height="18" font="3">empirical claim, with little empirical support and no explanatory purchase.</text>
<text top="544" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">What is the role of inference in communication? Is it merely to provide short-cuts</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">along the normal paths of coding-decoding (in which case any inferentially</text>
<text top="592" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicated message could have been fully encoded)? Or does inference open up new</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">paths, to otherwise inaccessible end-points, making it possible to communicate meanings</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that were not linguistically encodable? (By 'not linguistically encodable' we mean not</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">encodable in the public language actually being used, rather than not encodable in any</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">possible language.) In the absence of any plausible account of the inferential processes</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">involved in comprehension, the reasonable, conservative option might be to assume that</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">inference does not enrich the repertoire of communicable meanings. For example, if all</text>
<text top="760" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">we had to go on was Grice's ground-breaking but very sketchy original account (in his</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">1967 William James lectures, reprinted in Grice 1989), we would have very little idea</text>
<text top="808" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">of how inferential comprehension processes actually work, how powerful they are, and</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="601" height="18" font="3">whether and how they might extend the range of communicable concepts.</text>
<text top="856" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Relevance theory (Sperber &amp; Wilson 1986/1995; see also references therein) offers a</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">more explicit account of comprehension processes, which claims that what can be</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicated goes well beyond what can be encoded. Here, we will give a brief,</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="399" height="18" font="3">intuitive outline of relevant aspects of the theory.</text>
<text top="951" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">The basic ideas of the theory are contained in a definition of relevance and two</text>
<text top="975" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">principles. Relevance is defined as a property of inputs to cognitive processes. The</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">processing of an input (e.g. an utterance) may yield some cognitive effects (e.g. revisions</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of beliefs). Everything else being equal, the greater the effects, the greater the relevance</text>
</page>
<page number="10" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">10</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of the input. The processing of the input (and the derivation of these effects) involves</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">some cognitive effort. Everything else being equal, the greater the effort, the lower the</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="571" height="18" font="3">relevance. On the basis of this definition, two principles are proposed:</text>
<text top="285" left="108" width="24" height="18" font="3">(9)</text>
<text top="285" left="162" width="276" height="18" font="6"><b>Cognitive principle of relevance</b></text>
<text top="309" left="162" width="571" height="18" font="3">Human cognition tends to be geared to the maximisation of relevance.</text>
<text top="357" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(10)</text>
<text top="357" left="162" width="331" height="18" font="6"><b>Communicative principle of relevance</b></text>
<text top="381" left="162" width="594" height="18" font="3">Every act of ostensive communication communicates a presumption of its</text>
<text top="405" left="162" width="123" height="18" font="3">own relevance.</text>
<text top="453" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">More specifically, we claim that the speaker, by the very act of addressing someone,</text>
<text top="477" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communicates that her utterance is the most relevant one compatible with her abilities</text>
<text top="501" left="108" width="658" height="18" font="3">and preferences, and is at least relevant enough to be worth his processing effort.</text>
<text top="525" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">As noted above, ostensive behaviour automatically activates in the addressee some</text>
<text top="549" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">conceptual structure or idea: for example, the automatic decoding of an utterance leads</text>
<text top="573" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">to the construction of a logical form. This initial step in the comprehension process</text>
<text top="597" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">involves some cognitive effort. According to the communicative principle of relevance,</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">the effort required gives some indication of the effect to expect. The effect should be</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">enough to justify the effort (or at least enough for it to have seemed to the speaker that</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it would seem to the hearer to justify the effort — but we will ignore this qualification,</text>
<text top="692" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">which plays a role only when the speaker deliberately or accidentally fails to provide the</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="524" height="18" font="3">hearer with sufficiently relevant information; see Sperber 1994).</text>
<text top="788" left="108" width="221" height="18" font="6"><b>4 Relevance and meaning</b></text>
<text top="836" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">The communicative principle of relevance provides the motivation for the following</text>
<text top="860" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">comprehension procedure, which we claim is automatically applied to the on-line</text>
<text top="884" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">processing of attended verbal inputs. The hearer takes the conceptual structure</text>
<text top="908" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">constructed by linguistic decoding; following a path of least effort, he enriches this at the</text>
<text top="932" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">explicit level and complements it at the implicit level, until the resulting interpretation</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="501" height="18" font="3">meets his expectations of relevance; at which point, he stops. </text>
<text top="979" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">We will illustrate this procedure by considering the interpretation of Mary's utterance</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="61" height="18" font="3">in (11):</text>
</page>
<page number="11" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="793" width="17" height="16" font="1">11</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(11)</text>
<text top="209" left="162" width="330" height="18" font="2"><i>Peter</i>: Do you want to go to the cinema?</text>
<text top="233" left="162" width="128" height="18" font="2"><i>Mary</i>: I'm tired.</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">Let's assume (though we will soon qualify this) that Peter decodes Mary's utterance as</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">asserting that Mary is tired. By itself, the information that Mary is tired does not answer</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Peter's question. However, he is justified in trying to use it to draw inferences that would</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">answer his question and thus satisfy his expectations of relevance. If the first assumption</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to occur to him is that Mary's being tired is a good enough reason for her not to want to</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">go to the cinema, he will assume she meant him to use this assumption as an implicit</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">premise and derive the implicit conclusion that she doesn't want to go to the cinema</text>
<text top="449" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">because she is tired. Peter's interpretation of Mary's utterance contains the following</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="106" height="18" font="3">assumptions:</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(12)</text>
<text top="520" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="520" left="216" width="110" height="18" font="3">Mary is tired.</text>
<text top="544" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="544" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">Mary's being tired is a sufficient reason for her not to want to go to the</text>
<text top="568" left="216" width="64" height="18" font="3">cinema.</text>
<text top="592" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">c.</text>
<text top="592" left="216" width="479" height="18" font="3">Mary doesn't want to go to the cinema because she is tired.</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">Mary could have answered Peter's question directly by telling him she didn't want to go</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to the cinema. Notice, though, that the extra (inferential) effort required by her indirect</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">reply is offset by extra effect: she conveys not just a refusal to go, but a reason for this</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">refusal. There may, of course, be many other conclusions that Peter could derive from</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="327" height="18" font="3">her utterance, for example those in (13):</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(13)</text>
<text top="784" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="784" left="216" width="176" height="18" font="3">Mary had a busy day.</text>
<text top="808" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="808" left="216" width="385" height="18" font="3">Mary wouldn't want to do a series of press-ups.</text>
<text top="856" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">But even if these conclusions were highly relevant to Peter, they would not help to</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">satisfy the specific expectations of relevance created by Mary's utterance. The fact that</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">she was replying to his question made it reasonable for him to expect the kind and degree</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of relevance that he himself had suggested he was looking for by asking this question,</text>
<text top="951" left="108" width="107" height="18" font="3">and no more.</text>
<text top="975" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">However, there is a problem. How plausible is it that the fact that Mary is tired is a</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">good enough reason for her not to want to go to the cinema? Why should Peter accept</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">this as an implicit premise of her utterance? Does Mary never want to go to the cinema</text>
</page>
<page number="12" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">12</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">when she is tired, even if she is just a little tired, tired enough for it not to be false to say</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that she is strictly speaking tired? Surely, in these or other circumstances, Peter might</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">have been aware that Mary was somewhat tired, without treating it as evidence that she</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="256" height="18" font="3">didn't want to go to the cinema.</text>
<text top="285" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">As noted above, a hearer using the relevance-theoretic comprehension procedure</text>
<text top="309" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">should follow a path of least effort, enriching and complementing the decoded</text>
<text top="332" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">conceptual structure until the resulting interpretation meets his expectations of relevance.</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">We have shown how this procedure would apply to Mary's utterance in (11) to yield the</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">implicatures (12b) and (12c). This is a case where the explicit content is complemented</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">at the implicit level. However, for this complementation to make sense, some enrichment</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="555" height="18" font="3">must also take place at the level of what is explicitly communicated.</text>
<text top="452" left="123" width="688" height="18" font="3">If comprehension is to be treated as a properly inferential process, the inferences must</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">be sound (in a sense that applies to non-demonstrative inference). From the mere fact that</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Mary is tired, Peter cannot soundly infer that she doesn't want to go to the cinema. For</text>
<text top="524" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">the implicatures (12b) and (12c) to be soundly derived, Mary must be understood as</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">saying something stronger than that she is tired <i>tout court</i>: her meaning must be enriched</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to the point where it warrants the intended inferences. The process is one of parallel</text>
<text top="596" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">adjustment: expectations of relevance warrant the derivation of specific implicatures, for</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="453" height="18" font="3">which the explicit content must be adequately enriched.</text>
<text top="644" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Mary is therefore conveying something more than simply the proposition that she is</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">tired, which would be satisfied by whatever is the minimal degree of tiredness: she is</text>
<text top="692" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">conveying that she is tired enough not to want to go to the cinema. If she were</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">'technically' tired, but not tired enough for it to matter, her utterance would be</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">misleading, not just by suggesting a wrong reason for her not wanting to go to the</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">cinema, but also by giving a wrong indication of her degree of tiredness. Suppose Peter</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">thought that she was being disingenuous in using her tiredness as an excuse for not going</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="264" height="18" font="3">to the cinema. He might answer:</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(14)</text>
<text top="859" left="162" width="251" height="18" font="3">Come on, you're not <i>that</i> tired!</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">He would not be denying that she is tired: merely that she is tired to the degree conveyed</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="136" height="18" font="3">by her utterance.</text>
<text top="955" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">How tired is that? Well, there is no absolute scale of tiredness (and if there were, no</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">specific value would be indicated here). Mary is communicating that she is tired enough</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">for it to be reasonable for her not to want to go to the cinema on that occasion. This is an</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">ad hoc, circumstantial notion of tiredness. It is the degree of tiredness that has this</text>
</page>
<page number="13" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="793" width="17" height="16" font="1">13</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="109" height="18" font="3">consequence.</text>
<text top="233" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">In saying (11), Mary thus communicates a notion more specific than the one encoded</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">by the English word 'tired'. This notion is not lexicalised in English. It may be that Mary</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">will never find another use for it, in which case it will not have the kind of stability in her</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">mental life that we took to be a condition for mental concepthood. Alternatively, she may</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">recognise this particular sort of tiredness, and have a permanent mental 'entry' or 'file' for</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">it, in which case it is a proper concept. In the same way, Peter's grasp of the notion of</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">tiredness Mary is invoking may be ephemeral, or he may recognise it as something that</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">applies to Mary, and perhaps others, on different occasions, in which case he has the</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="100" height="18" font="3">concept too.</text>
<text top="449" left="123" width="685" height="18" font="3">It might be argued that the word 'tired' in Mary's utterance, when properly enriched,</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">just means <i>too tired to want to go to the cinema</i>. This is a meaning which is perfectly</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">encodable in English, even though it is not lexicalised. Suppose this were so, and that</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Mary has a stable concept of this kind of tiredness: her utterance would still illustrate our</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">point that there may be many non-lexicalised mental concepts. The fact that this concept</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">is encodable by a complex phrase would be no reason to think Mary does not have it as</text>
<text top="592" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">an elementary concept, any more than the fact that 'bachelor' can be defined is any reason</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="489" height="18" font="3">to think we have no elementary mental concept of <i>bachelor</i>.</text>
<text top="640" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">In any case, it is unlikely that Mary's answer in (11) is really synonymous with her</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="123" height="18" font="3">answer in (15):</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(15)</text>
<text top="712" left="162" width="330" height="18" font="2"><i>Peter</i>: Do you want to go to the cinema?</text>
<text top="736" left="162" width="386" height="18" font="2"><i>Mary</i>: I'm too tired to want to go to the cinema.</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Mary's answer in (11) has a degree of indeterminacy that is lost in (15). Quite apart from</text>
<text top="808" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">this, the apparent paraphrasability of her answer in (11) is linked to the fact that she is</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">answering a yes-no question, which drastically narrows down the range of potential</text>
<text top="856" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures and the enrichment needed to warrant them. Yet the enrichment mechanism</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">is itself quite general, and applies in contexts where the range of implicatures is much</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="421" height="18" font="3">vaguer, as we will show with two further examples.</text>
<text top="927" left="123" width="681" height="18" font="3">Imagine that Peter and Mary, on holiday in Italy, are visiting a museum. Mary says:</text>
<text top="975" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(16)</text>
<text top="975" left="162" width="130" height="18" font="2"><i>Mary</i>: I'm tired!</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">As before, if her utterance is to be relevant to Peter, she must mean more than just that</text>
</page>
<page number="14" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">14</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">she is strictly speaking tired. This time, though, the implications that might make her</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="541" height="18" font="3">utterance relevant are only loosely suggested. They might include:</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(17)</text>
<text top="261" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">a.</text>
<text top="261" left="216" width="368" height="18" font="3">Mary's enjoyment of this visit is diminishing.</text>
<text top="285" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">b.</text>
<text top="285" left="216" width="444" height="18" font="3">Mary would like to cut short their visit to the museum.</text>
<text top="309" left="162" width="14" height="18" font="3">c.</text>
<text top="309" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">Mary is encouraging Peter to admit that he is also tired and wants to cut</text>
<text top="332" left="216" width="116" height="18" font="3">short the visit.</text>
<text top="356" left="162" width="15" height="18" font="3">d.</text>
<text top="356" left="216" width="594" height="18" font="3">Mary would like them to go back to their hotel after this visit to the</text>
<text top="380" left="216" width="505" height="18" font="3">museum, rather than visiting the Duomo, as they had planned.</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">If these and other such conclusions are implicatures of her utterance, they are only weak</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures: implications that Peter is encouraged to derive and accept, but for which</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">he has to take some of the responsibility himself (for the notion of 'weak implicature', see</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Sperber &amp; Wilson 1986/1995, chapter 4). Whatever implicatures he ends up treating as</text>
<text top="524" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">intended (or suggested) by Mary, he will have to adjust his understanding of her explicit</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">meaning so as to warrant their derivation. Mary will be understood as having conveyed</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">that she is tired to such a degree or in such a way as to warrant the derivation of these</text>
<text top="596" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures. This overall interpretation is itself justified by the expectation of relevance</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">created by Mary's utterance (i.e. by this particular instantiation of the communicative</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="189" height="18" font="3">principle of relevance).</text>
<text top="668" left="123" width="383" height="18" font="3">That evening, at a trattoria, Mary says to Peter:</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="34" height="18" font="3">(18)</text>
<text top="716" left="162" width="153" height="18" font="3">I love Italian food!</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">She does not, of course, mean that she loves all Italian food, nor does she merely mean</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">that there is some Italian food she loves. So what does she mean? It is often suggested</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that in a case like this, the expression 'Italian food' denotes a prototype, here <i>prototypical</i></text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="2"><i>Italian food</i>. This presupposes that there is a readily available and relatively context-</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">independent prototype. In the situation described above, it so happens that Mary is a</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">vegetarian. Moreover, her understanding of Italian food is largely based on what she</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">finds in an 'Italian' vegetarian restaurant in her own country where she sometimes goes</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">with Peter, which serves several dishes such as 'tofu pizza' that are definitely not Italian.</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Mary's utterance achieves relevance for Peter by implicating that she is enjoying her</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">food, and sees it as belonging to a distinct category which the expression 'Italian food'</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="252" height="18" font="3">suggests but does not describe.</text>
<text top="1027" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Even if Mary's use of the term 'Italian food' were less idiosyncratic, it would not follow</text>
</page>
<page number="15" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="793" width="17" height="16" font="1">15</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that all Peter has to do to understand it is recover a prototype. Much recent research has</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">cast doubt on the view that word meanings can be analysed in terms of context-</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">independent prototypes, and suggests instead that ad hoc meanings are constructed in</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">context (see e.g. Barsalou 1987; Franks &amp; Braisby 1990; Franks 1995; Butler 1995). We</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">would add that this contextual construction is a by-product of the relevance-guided</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">comprehension process. The explicit content of an utterance, and in particular the</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">meanings of specific expressions, are adjusted so as to warrant the derivation of</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures which themselves justify the expectations of relevance created by the</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">utterance act. These occasional meanings may stabilise into concepts, for the speaker, the</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="125" height="18" font="3">hearer, or both.</text>
<text top="449" left="123" width="689" height="18" font="3">These examples are designed to show how a word which encodes a given concept can</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">be used to convey (as a component of a speaker's meaning) another concept that neither</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">it nor any other expression in the language actually encodes. There is nothing exceptional</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">about such uses: almost any word can be used in this way. Quite generally, the</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">occurrence of a word in an utterance provides a piece of evidence, a pointer to a concept</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">involved in the speaker's meaning. It may so happen that the intended concept is the very</text>
<text top="592" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">one encoded by the word, which is therefore used in its strictly literal sense. However,</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">we would argue that this is no more than a possibility, not a preferred or default</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">interpretation. Any interpretation, whether literal or not, results from mutual adjustment</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of the explicit and implicit content of the utterance. This adjustment process stabilises</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">when the hypothesised implicit content is warranted by the hypothesised explicit content</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">together with the context, and when the overall interpretation is warranted by (the</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="560" height="18" font="3">particular instantiation of) the communicative principle of relevance.</text>
<text top="760" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">This approach sheds some light on the phenomenon of polysemy illustrated by the</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">example of 'open' above. A verb like 'open' acts as a pointer to indefinitely many notions</text>
<text top="808" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">or concepts. In some cases, the intended concept is jointly indicated by the verb and its</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">direct object (as with the ordinary sense of 'open the washing machine'), so that the</text>
<text top="856" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">inferential route is short and obvious. There may be cases where such routinely reachable</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">senses become lexicalised. In general, though, polysemy is the outcome of a pragmatic</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">process whereby intended senses are inferred on the basis of encoded concepts and</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">contextual information. These inferred senses may be ephemeral notions or stable</text>
<text top="951" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concepts; they may be shared by few or many speakers, or by whole communities; the</text>
<text top="975" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">inference pattern may be a first-time affair or a routine pattern — and it may be a first-</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">time affair for one interlocutor and a routine affair for another, who, despite these</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">differences, manage to communicate successfully. (For relevance-theoretic accounts of</text>
</page>
<page number="16" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">16</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">polysemy, see Carston 1996, in preparation; Deane 1988; Groefsema 1995; Papafragou</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="352" height="18" font="3">in preparation; Wilson &amp; Sperber in press.)</text>
<text top="285" left="108" width="124" height="18" font="6"><b>5 Implications</b></text>
<text top="332" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Our argument so far has been that, given the inferential nature of comprehension, the</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">words in a language can be used to convey not only the concepts they encode, but also</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">indefinitely many other related concepts to which they might point in a given context.</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">We see this not as a mere theoretical possibility, but as a universal practice, suggesting</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="668" height="18" font="3">that there are many times more concepts in our minds than words in our language.</text>
<text top="452" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Despite their different theoretical perspectives, many other researchers in philosophy,</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">psychology and linguistics have converged on the idea that new senses are constantly</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">being constructed in context (e.g. Braisby &amp; Franks 1990; Goshke &amp; Koppelberg 1992;</text>
<text top="524" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Barsalou 1993; Gibbs 1994; Franks 1995; Récanati 1995; Nunberg 1996; Carston 1996,</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">in preparation). However, it is possible to believe that new senses can be contextually</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="694" height="18" font="3">constructed without accepting that there are more mental concepts than public words.</text>
<text top="596" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">Someone might argue, for example, that the only stable concepts are linguistically</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">encodable ones. Unless a new sense constructed in context is linguistically encodable,</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">it cannot be a stable concept of the speaker's, and will never stabilise as a mental concept</text>
<text top="667" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">in the hearer. When Mary says at the museum that she is tired, the understanding that she</text>
<text top="691" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and Peter have of her kind and degree of tiredness cannot be divorced from their</text>
<text top="715" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">understanding of the whole situation. They do not construct or use an ad hoc concept of</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">tiredness. Rather, they have a global representation of the situation, which gives its</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="525" height="18" font="3">particular contextual import to the ordinary concept of tiredness.</text>
<text top="787" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">We would reply as follows. We do not deny — indeed, we insist — that most</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">occasional representations of a property (or an object, event or state) do not stabilise into</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a concept. Most contextually represented properties are not recognised as having been</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">previously encountered, and are not remembered when the situation in which they were</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">represented is itself forgotten. However, some properties are recognised and/or</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">remembered even when many or all of the contextual elements of their initial</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">identification are lost. For example, you look at your friend and recognise the symptoms</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of a mood for which you have no word, which you might be unable to describe exactly,</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and whose previous occurrences you only dimly remember; but you know that mood,</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and you know how it is likely to affect her and you. Similarly, you look at the landscape</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and the sky, and you recognise the weather, you know how it will feel, but you have no</text>
</page>
<page number="17" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="793" width="17" height="16" font="1">17</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">word for it. Or you feel a pain, you recognise it and know what to expect, but have no</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">word for it; and so on. You are capable not just of recognising these phenomena but also</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of anticipating them, imagining them, regretting or rejoicing that they are not actual. You</text>
<text top="281" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">can communicate thoughts about them to interlocutors who are capable of recognising</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">them, if not spontaneously, at least with the help of your communication. Your ability</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">to recognise and think about the mood, the weather, the pain, is evidence that you have</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a corresponding stable mental file or entry, i.e. a mental concept. The evidence is not, of</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">course, conclusive, and there could be a better hypothesis. However the suggestion that</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">what has been contextually grasped can only be remembered with all the relevant</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="489" height="18" font="3">particulars of the initial context is not that better hypothesis.</text>
<text top="449" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">There is a more general reason for believing that we have many more concepts than</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">words. The stabilisation of a word in a language is a social and historical affair. It is a</text>
<text top="496" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">slow and relatively rare process, involving co-ordination among many individuals over</text>
<text top="520" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">time. A plausible guess is that, in most relatively homogenous speech communities in</text>
<text top="544" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">human history, less than a dozen new words (including homonyms of older words and</text>
<text top="568" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">excluding proper names) would stabilise in a year. On the other hand, the addition of</text>
<text top="592" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">new concepts to an individual's mind is comparatively unconstrained. It is not a matter</text>
<text top="616" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">of co-ordinating with others, but of internal memory management. There is no question</text>
<text top="640" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that we are capable of acquiring a huge amount of new information every day. Do we</text>
<text top="664" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">store it all in pre-existing files, or do we sometimes — perhaps a few times a day — open</text>
<text top="688" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a new file, i.e. stabilise a new concept? Notice that this would not involve adding extra</text>
<text top="712" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">information to long term memory but merely organising information that we are going</text>
<text top="736" left="108" width="511" height="18" font="3">to add anyhow in a different, and arguably more efficient way.</text>
<text top="760" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Information filed together tends to be accessed together, and efficient memory</text>
<text top="784" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">management involves not only filing together what is generally best accessed together,</text>
<text top="808" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">but also filing separately what is generally best accessed separately. Thus, you may be</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">able to recognise a certain type of food (which the public linguistic expression 'Italian</text>
<text top="856" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">food' may hint at in an appropriate context but does not describe), and this ability may</text>
<text top="879" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">play a role in your mental life: say in deciding what to eat or cook on a given occasion.</text>
<text top="903" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">Where is information about this kind of food stored in your memory? Does it have its</text>
<text top="927" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">own address, or does it have to be reassembled from information filed elsewhere every</text>
<text top="951" left="108" width="122" height="18" font="3">time it is used?</text>
<text top="975" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">How and how often we open new files, and thus stabilise new mental concepts, is an</text>
<text top="999" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">empirical question, to be investigated with the methods of psychology. However, the</text>
<text top="1023" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">hypothesis that we can open a new file only when we have a public word that</text>
</page>
<page number="18" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">18</text>
<text top="189" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">corresponds to it is a costly one, with no obvious merit. It amounts to imposing an</text>
<text top="213" left="108" width="703" height="18" font="3">arbitrary and counter-productive constraint on memory management. (This is not, of</text>
<text top="237" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">course, to deny the converse point that on encountering a new word you may stabilise</text>
<text top="261" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a new concept, and that many of our concepts originate partly or wholly from linguistic</text>
<text top="285" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">communication — a point for which there is much evidence, in particular developmental,</text>
<text top="309" left="108" width="261" height="18" font="3">e.g. Gelman &amp; Markman 1987.)</text>
<text top="332" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">While the kind of collective co-ordination needed to stabilise a word in a speech</text>
<text top="356" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">community is an elaborate affair, the typically pairwise co-ordination involved in any</text>
<text top="380" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">given communicative act is a relatively simpler achievement — the kind of achievement</text>
<text top="404" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">that a pragmatic theory such as relevance theory aims to explain. This co-ordination may</text>
<text top="428" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">be somewhat loose. When Mary says at the museum that she is tired, her utterance gets</text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">its explicit meaning through adjustment to a set of weak implicatures: that is,</text>
<text top="476" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">implicatures whose exact content is not wholly determined by the utterance. The ad hoc</text>
<text top="500" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concept of tiredness that Peter constructs (i.e. the concept of tiredness which warrants the</text>
<text top="524" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">derivation of these weak implicatures) is unlikely to be exactly the same as the one Mary</text>
<text top="548" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">had in mind (since she did not foresee or intend exactly these implicatures). This is not</text>
<text top="572" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a failure of communication. It is an illusion of the code theory that communication aims</text>
<text top="596" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">at duplication of meanings. Sometime it does, but quite ordinarily a looser kind of</text>
<text top="620" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">understanding is intended and achieved. The type of co-ordination aimed at in most</text>
<text top="644" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">verbal exchanges is best compared to the co-ordination between people taking a stroll</text>
<text top="668" left="108" width="494" height="18" font="3">together rather than to that between people marching in step.</text>
<text top="692" left="123" width="687" height="18" font="3">Returning to the question of effability, we would maintain that this is a matter of</text>
<text top="716" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">degree. Some concepts are properly shared, and can be unequivocally expressed: a</text>
<text top="739" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">mathematical discussion would provide good examples. Other concepts are idiosyncratic,</text>
<text top="763" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">but as a result of common experience or communication, are close enough to the</text>
<text top="787" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">idiosyncratic concepts of others to play a role in the co-ordination of behaviour. Still</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">other concepts may be too idiosyncratic to be even loosely communicated. The fact that</text>
<text top="835" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a public word exists and is successfully used in communication does not make it safe to</text>
<text top="859" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">assume that it encodes the same concept for all successful users; and in any case, the</text>
<text top="883" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">concept communicated will only occasionally be the same as the one encoded.</text>
<text top="907" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">Communication can succeed, despite possible semantic discrepancies, as long as the</text>
<text top="931" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">word used in a given situation points the hearer in the direction intended by the speaker.</text>
<text top="955" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">Thus, Peter and Mary might differ as to the exact extension of 'tired': Peter might regard</text>
<text top="979" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">as genuine though minimal tiredness a state that Mary would not regard as tiredness at</text>
<text top="1003" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">all. Mary's successful use of the term in no way depends on their meaning exactly the</text>
<text top="1027" left="108" width="704" height="18" font="3">same thing by it. Similarly, their concepts of Italy might pick out different entities in</text>
</page>
<page number="19" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="756" width="54" height="16" font="7"><i>T h e</i></text>
<text top="152" left="108" width="305" height="16" font="7"><i>mapping between mental and public lexicon</i></text>
<text top="132" left="793" width="17" height="16" font="1">19</text>
<text top="209" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">space or time (for example, is Ancient Roman History part of Italian History? That</text>
<text top="233" left="108" width="700" height="18" font="3">depends on what you mean by 'Italy'). Mary's successful use of the term 'Italian' should</text>
<text top="257" left="108" width="302" height="18" font="3">be unaffected by these discrepancies.</text>
<text top="281" left="123" width="686" height="18" font="3">More generally, it does not much matter whether or not a word linguistically encodes</text>
<text top="305" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">a full-fledged concept, and, if so, whether it encodes the same concept for both speaker</text>
<text top="329" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">and hearer. Even if it does, comprehension is not guaranteed. Even if it does not,</text>
<text top="353" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">comprehension need not be impaired. Whether they encode concepts or pro-concepts,</text>
<text top="377" left="108" width="701" height="18" font="3">words are used as pointers to contextually intended senses. Utterances are merely pieces</text>
<text top="401" left="108" width="702" height="18" font="3">of evidence of the speaker's intention, and this has far-reaching implications, a few of</text>
<text top="425" left="108" width="292" height="18" font="3">which we have tried to outline here.</text>
<text top="521" left="108" width="95" height="18" font="6"><b>References</b></text>
<text top="567" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Barsalou, L. (1987). The instability of graded structure: implications for the nature of concepts. In U.</text>
<text top="588" left="123" width="687" height="16" font="1">Neisser (ed.) <i>Concepts and conceptual development: Ecological and intellectual factors in</i></text>
<text top="608" left="123" width="451" height="16" font="7"><i>categorisation</i>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 101-40.</text>
<text top="628" left="108" width="603" height="16" font="1">Butler, K. (1995). Content, context and compositionality. <i>Mind and language</i> 10. 3-24.</text>
<text top="649" left="108" width="701" height="16" font="1">Caramazza, A. &amp; E. Grober. (1976). Polysemy and the structure of the subjective lexicon. In C. Rameh</text>
<text top="669" left="123" width="687" height="16" font="1">(ed.)  <i>Semantics: Theory and application.</i> Georgetown University Round Table on Language and</text>
<text top="689" left="123" width="479" height="16" font="1">Linguistics. Washington DC: Georgetown University Press. 181-206.</text>
<text top="710" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Carston, R. (1996). Enrichment and loosening: Complementary processes in deriving the proposition</text>
<text top="730" left="123" width="395" height="16" font="1">expressed? <i>UCL Working Papers in Linguistics</i> 8. 61-88.</text>
<text top="750" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Carston, R. (in preparation). <i>Pragmatics and the explicit-implicit distinction.</i> PhD thesis. University of</text>
<text top="771" left="123" width="58" height="16" font="1">London.</text>
<text top="791" left="108" width="433" height="16" font="1">Deane, P. (1988). Polysemy and cognition. <i>Lingua </i>75. 325-61.</text>
<text top="811" left="108" width="440" height="16" font="1">Fodor, J. (1975). <i>The language of thought.</i> New York: Crowell.</text>
<text top="832" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Fodor, J. &amp; E. Lepore. (1996). The emptiness of the lexicon: Critical reflections on J. Pustejovsky's <i>The</i></text>
<text top="852" left="123" width="473" height="16" font="7"><i>generative lexicon</i>. RuCCS, Rutgers University,Technical report 27.</text>
<text top="872" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Franks, B. (1995). Sense generation: a 'quasi-classical' approach to concepts and concept combination.</text>
<text top="893" left="123" width="215" height="16" font="7"><i>Cognitive science</i> 19. 441-505.</text>
<text top="913" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Franks, B. &amp; N. Braisby. (1990). Sense generation or how to make a mental lexicon flexible. In</text>
<text top="933" left="123" width="687" height="16" font="7"><i>Proceedings of the 12th annual conference of the cognitive science society.</i> Cambridge, MA: MIT,</text>
<text top="954" left="123" width="72" height="16" font="1">July 1990.</text>
<text top="974" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Gelman, S. &amp; E. Markman. (1986). Categories and induction in young children. <i>Cognition</i> 23. 183-209.</text>
<text top="994" left="108" width="554" height="16" font="1">Gibbs, R. (1994). <i>The poetics of mind.</i> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</text>
</page>
<page number="20" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" height="1188" width="918">
<text top="132" left="162" width="124" height="16" font="7"><i>Sperber &amp; Wilson</i></text>
<text top="132" left="108" width="17" height="16" font="1">20</text>
<text top="188" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Goshke, T. &amp; D. Koppelberg. (1992). The concept of representation and the representation of concepts</text>
<text top="208" left="123" width="687" height="16" font="1">in connectionist models. In W. Ramsey, S. Stich &amp; D. Rumelhart (eds) <i>Philosophy and connectionist</i></text>
<text top="229" left="123" width="217" height="16" font="7"><i>theory</i>. Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum.</text>
<text top="249" left="108" width="636" height="16" font="1">Grice, H.P. (1989). <i>Studies in the way of words</i>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</text>
<text top="269" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Groefsema, M. (1995). 'Can', 'may', 'must' and 'should': A relevance-theoretic approach. <i>Journal of</i></text>
<text top="290" left="123" width="146" height="16" font="7"><i>linguistics</i> 31. 53-79.</text>
<text top="310" left="108" width="357" height="16" font="1">Hardin, C. (1988).<i> Color for philosophers.</i> Hackett.</text>
<text top="330" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Lehrer, A. (1990). Polysemy, conventionality and the structure of the lexicon. <i>Cognitive linguistics</i> 1-2.</text>
<text top="351" left="123" width="53" height="16" font="1">207-46.</text>
<text top="371" left="108" width="485" height="16" font="1">Lyons, J. (1977). <i>Semantics</i>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</text>
<text top="391" left="108" width="600" height="16" font="1">Nunberg, G. (1996). Transfers of meaning. In Pustejovsky &amp; Boguraev (eds). 109-132.</text>
<text top="412" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Papafragou, A. (in preparation). <i>Modality and the semantics-pragmatics interface.</i> PhD thesis.</text>
<text top="432" left="123" width="153" height="16" font="1">University of London </text>
<text top="452" left="108" width="400" height="16" font="1">Pinkal, M. (1995). <i>Logic and lexicon</i>. Dordrecht: Kluwer.</text>
<text top="473" left="108" width="527" height="16" font="1">Pustejovsky, J. (1995). <i>The generative lexicon</i>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</text>
<text top="493" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Pustejovsky, J. &amp; B. Boguraev. (eds) (1996). <i>Lexical semantics: The problem of polysemy</i>. Oxford:</text>
<text top="513" left="123" width="117" height="16" font="1">Clarendon Press.</text>
<text top="534" left="108" width="665" height="16" font="1">Récanati, F. (1995). The alleged priority of literal interpretation. <i>Cognitive science</i> 19. 207-232.</text>
<text top="554" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Searle, J. (1980). The background of meaning. In J. Searle &amp; F. Kiefer (eds) <i>Speech-act theory and</i></text>
<text top="574" left="123" width="273" height="16" font="7"><i>pragmatics</i>. Dordrecht: Reidel. 221-32.</text>
<text top="595" left="108" width="509" height="16" font="1">Searle, J. (1983). <i>Intentionality</i>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</text>
<text top="615" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Sperber, D. (1994). Understanding verbal understanding. In J. Khalfa (ed.) <i>What is intelligence?</i></text>
<text top="635" left="123" width="342" height="16" font="1">Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 179-98.</text>
<text top="656" left="108" width="702" height="16" font="1">Sperber, D. &amp; D. Wilson. (1986/1995). <i>Relevance: Communication and cognition.</i> Oxford: Blackwell.</text>
<text top="676" left="108" width="701" height="16" font="1">Wilson, D. &amp; D. Sperber. (in press) Pragmatics and time. To appear in R. Carston, S. Uchida and N.</text>
<text top="697" left="123" width="647" height="16" font="1">Song (eds) <i>Proceedings of the Osaka workshop on relevance theory.</i> Amsterdam: Benjamins.</text>
</page>
</pdf2xml>
